<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>95eaf05c578adb0f91063b12eec154e79fdf202f3f298742a05ab56c22c6b41a</job>
    <base_name>62</base_name>
    <doi>http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.1601785</doi>
    <warning>Name identification was not possible. </warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="1">www.econstor.eu</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="2">econstor Open-Access-Publikationsserver der ZBW – Leibniz-Informationszentrum Wirtschaft Open Access Publication Server of the ZBW – Leibniz Information Centre for Economics</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="3">Der The</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">Henrich, Joseph; Heine, Steven J.; Norenzayan, Ara Working Paper</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="5">The weirdest people in the world?</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">Working Paper Series des Rates für Sozial- und Wirtschaftsdaten, No. 139</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="7">Provided in Cooperation with: German Data Forum (RatSWD)</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx8">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="62.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="10" confidence="possible">Suggested Citation: Henrich, Joseph; Heine, Steven J.; Norenzayan, Ara (2010) : The weirdest people in the world?, Working Paper Series des Rates für Sozial- und Wirtschaftsdaten, No. 139 This Version is available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://hdl.handle.net/10419/43616" id="9">http://hdl.handle.net/10419/43616</ext-link> Standard-Nutzungsbedingungen: Terms of use: Die Dokumente auf EconStor dürfen zu eigenen wissenschaftlichen Documents in EconStor may be saved and copied for your Zwecken und zum Privatgebrauch gespeichert und kopiert werden. personal and scholarly purposes.</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="11">Sie dürfen die Dokumente nicht für öffentliche oder kommerzielle Zwecke vervielfältigen, öffentlich ausstellen, öffentlich zugänglich machen, vertreiben oder anderweitig nutzen.</region>
      <abstract class="DoCO:Abstract" id="12" confidence="possible">You are not to copy documents for public or commercial purposes, to exhibit the documents publicly, to make them publicly available on the internet, or to distribute or otherwise use the documents in public.</abstract>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" confidence="possible">Sofern die Verfasser die Dokumente unter Open-Content-Lizenzen (insbesondere CC-Lizenzen) zur Verfügung gestellt haben sollten, If the documents have been made available under an Open gelten abweichend von diesen Nutzungsbedingungen die in der dort Content Licence (especially Creative Commons Licences), you genannten Lizenz gewährten Nutzungsrechte. may exercise further usage rights as specified in the indicated licence.</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="14">zbw Leibniz-Informationszentrum Leibniz Information Centre for Wirtschaft Economics</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="15" confidence="possible">German Data Forum (RatSWD) www.germandataforum.de RatSWD Working Paper Series Working Paper No. 139 The Weirdest People in the World?</region>
      <region class="unknown" id="16">Joseph Henrich, Steven J. Heine and Ara Norenzayan April 2010</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx17">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62.page_002.image_02.png" thmb="62.page_002.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="18">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="23" confidence="possible">The Weirdest People in the World?  Joseph Henrich  University of British Columbia  Department of Psychology  Department of Economics  <email id="19">joseph.henrich@gmail.com </email> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.psych.ubc.ca/" id="20">http://www.psych.ubc.ca/</ext-link>~henrich/home.html    Steven J. Heine  Ara Norenzayan  University of British Columbia  University of British Columbia  Department of Psychology  Department of Psychology  <email id="21">heine@psych.ubc.ca </email> <email id="22">ara@psych.ubc.ca </email> To be published in "Behavioral and Brain Sciences" together with "Open Peer Commentaries"</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="24"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="25">1</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="26">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="27">Long Abstract   Behavioral scientists routinely publish broad claims about human psychology and behavior in  the world’s top journals based on samples drawn entirely from Western, Educated,  Industrialized, Rich and Democratic (WEIRD) societies. Researchers—often implicitly—assume  that either there is little variation across human populations, or that these “standard subjects”  are as representative of the species as any other population. Are these assumptions justified?  Here, our review of the comparative database from across the behavioral sciences suggests  both that there is substantial variability in experimental results across populations and that  WEIRD subjects are particularly unusual compared with the rest of the species—frequent  outliers. The domains reviewed include visual perception, fairness, cooperation, spatial  reasoning, categorization and inferential induction, moral reasoning, reasoning styles, self‐ concepts and related motivations, and the heritability of IQ. The findings suggest that members  of WEIRD societies, including young children, are among the least representative populations  one could find for generalizing about humans. Many of these findings involve domains that are  associated with fundamental aspects of psychology, motivation, and behavior—hence, there  are no obvious a priori grounds for claiming that a particular behavioral phenomenon is  universal based on sampling from a single subpopulation. Overall, these empirical patterns  suggests that we need to be less cavalier in addressing questions of human nature on the basis  of data drawn from this particularly thin, and rather unusual, slice of humanity. We close by  proposing ways to structurally re‐organize the behavioral sciences to best tackle these  challenges.     </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="28" confidence="possible"> </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="37">Keywords: external validity, population variability, experiments, cross‐cultural research, culture,  human universals, generalizability, evolutionary psychology, cultural psychology, behavioral  economics. <marker type="block"/> Acknowledgements. We thank several anonymous reviewers and the following colleagues for  their very helpful comments on an earlier version of this manuscript: Nicholas Epley, Alan Fiske,  Simon Gaechter, Jonathan Haidt, Shinobu Kitayama, Shaun Nichols, Richard Nisbett, Paul Rozin,  Mark Schaller, Natalie Henrich, Daniel Fessler, Michael Gurven, Clark Barrett, Ted Slingerland,  Rick Shweder, Mark Collard, Paul Bloom, Scott Atran, Doug Medin, Tage Rai, Ayse Uskul, Colin  Camerer, Karen Wynn, Tim Wilson, and Stephen Stich.  <marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> In the tropical forests of New Guinea the Etoro believe that for a boy to achieve manhood he  must ingest the semen of his elders. This is accomplished through ritualized rites of passage  that require young male initiates to fellate a senior member (Herdt, 1984; Kelley, 1980). In  contrast, the nearby Kaluli maintain that male initiation is only properly done by ritually  delivering the semen through the initiate’s anus, not his mouth. The Etoro revile these Kaluli  practices, finding them disgusting. To become a man in these societies, and eventually take a  wife, every boy undergoes these initiations. Such boy‐inseminating practices, which are  enmeshed in rich systems of meaning and imbued with local cultural values, were not  uncommon among the traditional societies of Melanesia and Aboriginal Australia (Herdt, 1993),  as well as in Ancient Greece and Tokugawa Japan.    <marker type="block"/> Such in‐depth studies of seemingly “exotic” societies, historically the province of anthropology,  are crucial for understanding human behavioral and psychological variation. However, this  paper is not about these peoples. It’s about a truly unusual group: people from Western,  Educated, Industrialized, Rich, and Democratic (WEIRD 1 ) societies. In particular, it’s about the  Western, and more specifically American, undergraduates who form the bulk of the database in  the experimental branches of psychology, cognitive science, and economics, as well as allied  fields (hereafter collectively labeled the “behavioral sciences”). Given that scientific knowledge  about human psychology is largely based on findings from this subpopulation, we ask just how  representative are these typical subjects in light of the available comparative database. How  justified are researchers in assuming a species‐level generality for their findings? Here, we  review the evidence regarding how WEIRD people compare to other populations. <marker type="block"/> We pursued this question by constructing an empirical review of studies involving large‐scale  comparative experimentation on important psychological or behavioral variables. Although  such larger‐scale studies are highly informative, they are rather rare, especially when compared  to the frequency of species‐generalizing claims. When such comparative projects were absent  we relied on large assemblies of studies comparing 2 or 3 populations, and, when available, on  meta‐analyses.  <marker type="block"/> Of course, researchers do not implicitly assume psychological or motivational universality with  everything they study. The present review does not address those phenomena assessed by  individual difference measures for which the guiding assumption is variability among  populations. Phenomena such as personal values, emotional expressiveness, and personality  traits are expected a priori to vary across individuals, and by extension, societies. Indeed, the  goal of much research on these topics is to identify the ways that people and societies differ  from one another. For example, a number of large projects have sought to map out the world  on dimensions such as values (Hofstede, 2001; Inglehart, Basanez, &amp; Moreno, 1998; Schwartz &amp;  Bilsky, 1990), personality traits, (e.g., McCrae, Terraciano, &amp; Project, 2005; Schmitt, Allik, </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="31"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="32">2</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="33">Weird People</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="38"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="39">3</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="40">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="41" confidence="possible">McCrae, Benet‐Martinez, &amp; al., 2007), and levels of happiness, (e.g., Diener, Diener, &amp; Diener,  1995). Similarly, we avoid the vast psychopathology literature, which finds much evidence for  both variability and universality in psychological pathologies (Kleinman, 1988; Tseng, 2001),  because this work focuses on individual‐level (and unusual) variations in psychological  functioning. Instead, we restrict our exploration to those domains which have largely been  assumed, at least until recently, to be de facto psychological universals. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="49">Finally, we also do not address societal‐level behavioral universals, or claims thereof, related to  phenomena like dancing, fire‐making, cooking, kinship systems, body adornment, play, trade,  and grammar for two reasons. First, at this surface level alone such phenomena do not make  specific claims about universal underlying psychological or motivational processes. Second,  systematic, quantitative, comparative data based on individual‐level measures is typically  lacking for these domains. <marker type="block"/> Our examination of the representativeness of WEIRD subjects is necessarily restricted to the  rather limited database currently available. We have organized our presentation into a series of  telescoping contrasts showing, at each level of contrast, how WEIRD people measure up  relative to the available reference populations. Our first contrast compares people from  modern industrialized societies with those from small‐scale societies. Our second telescoping  stage contrasts people from Western societies with those from non‐Western industrialized  societies. Next, we contrast Americans with people from other Western societies. Finally, we  contrast university‐educated Americans with non‐university educated Americans, or university  students with non‐student adults, depending on the available data. At each level we discuss  behavioral and psychological phenomena for which there are available comparative data, and  we assess how WEIRD people compare with other samples.  <marker type="block"/> We emphasize that our presentation of telescoping contrasts is only a rhetorical approach  guided by the nature of the available data. It should not be taken as capturing any uni‐ dimensional continuum, or suggesting any single theoretical explanation for the variation.  Throughout this paper we take no position regarding the substantive origins of the observed  differences between populations. While many of the differences are probably cultural in nature  in that they were socially transmitted (Boyd &amp; Richerson, 1985; Nisbett, Peng, Choi, &amp;  Norenzayan, 2001), other differences are likely environmental and represent some form of non‐ cultural phenotypic plasticity, which may be developmental or facultative, as well as either  adaptive or maladaptive (Gangestad, Haselton, &amp; Buss, 2006; Tooby &amp; Cosmides, 1992). Other  population differences could arise from genetic variation, as observed for lactose processing  (Beja‐Pereira et al., 2003). Regardless of the reasons underlying these population differences,  our concern is whether researchers can reasonably generalize from WEIRD samples to  humanity at large. <marker type="page" number="7"/><marker type="block"/>  Many radical versions of interpretivism and cultural relativity deny any shared commonalities  in human psychologies across populations (Gergen, 1973; see discussion in Slingerland, 2008:  Chapter 2). To the contrary, we expect humans from all societies to share, and probably share  substantially, basic aspects of cognition, motivation, and behavior. As researchers who see  great value in applying evolutionary thinking to psychology and behavior, we have little doubt  that if a full accounting were taken across all domains among peoples past and present, the  number of similarities would indeed be large, as much ethnographic work suggests (e.g.,  Brown, 1991)—ultimately, of course, this is an empirical question. Thus, our thesis is not that  humans share few basic psychological properties or processes; rather we question our current  ability to distinguish these reliably developing aspects of human psychology from more  developmentally, culturally, or environmentally contingent aspects of our psychology given the  disproportionate reliance on WEIRD subjects. Our aim here, then, is to inspire efforts to place  knowledge of such universal features of psychology on a firmer footing by empirically  addressing, rather than a priori dismissing or ignoring, questions of population variability.  <marker type="block"/> 1. Background  Before commencing with our telescoping contrasts, we first discuss two observations regarding  the existing literature: (1) the database in the behavioral sciences is drawn from an extremely  narrow slice of human diversity; and (2) behavioral scientists routinely assume, at least  implicitly, that their findings from this narrow slice generalize to the species.   1.1. The Behavioral Sciences Database is Narrow    Who are the people studied in behavioral science research?  A recent analysis of the top  journals in six sub‐disciplines of Psychology from 2003‐2007 revealed that 68% of subjects came  from the US, and a full 96% of subjects were from Western industrialized countries, specifically  North America, Europe, Australia, and Israel (Arnett, 2008). The make‐up of these samples  appears to largely reflect the country of residence of the authors, as 73% of first authors were  at American universities, and 99% were at universities in Western countries. This means that  96% of psychological samples come from countries with only 12% of the world’s population.  </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="45"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="46">4</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="47">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="50" confidence="possible">Even within the West, however, the typical sampling method for experimental studies is far  from representative. In the Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, the premier journal in  social psychology—the sub‐discipline of psychology that should (arguably) be the most  attentive to questions about the subjects’ backgrounds—67% of the American samples (and  80% of the samples from other countries) were composed solely of undergraduates in  psychology courses (Arnett, 2008).  In other words, a randomly selected American  undergraduate is more than 4000 times more likely to be a research participant than is a  randomly selected person from outside of the West.  Furthermore, this tendency to rely on </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="51"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="52">5</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="53">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="54" confidence="possible">undergraduate samples has not decreased over time (Peterson, 2001; Wintre, North, &amp; Sugar,  2001). Such studies are thus sampling from a rather limited subpopulation within each country  (see Rozin, 2001).   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="56">It is possible that the dominance of American authors in psychology publications just reflects  that American universities have the resources to attract the best international researchers, and  that similar tendencies exist in other fields. However, psychology is a distinct outlier here: 70%  of all psychology citations come from the US—a larger percentage than any of the other 19  sciences that were compared in one extensive international survey (May, 1997). In chemistry,  by contrast, the percentage of citations that come from the U.S. is only 37%.  It seems  problematic that the discipline in which there are the strongest theoretical reasons to  anticipate population‐level variation, is precisely the discipline in which the American bias for  research is most extreme. <marker type="block"/> Beyond psychology and cognitive science, the subject pools of experimental economics and  decision science are not much more diverse, still largely dominated by Westerners, and  specifically Western undergraduates. However, to give credit where it is due, the nascent field  of experimental economics has begun taking steps to address the problem of narrow samples. 2   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="57" confidence="possible">In sum, the available database does not reflect the full breadth of human diversity. Rather, we  have largely been studying the nature of WEIRD people, a certainly narrow and potentially  peculiar subpopulation.   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="65">1.2. Researchers Often Assume their Findings are Universal  Sampling from a thin slice of humanity would be less problematic if researchers confined their  interpretations to the populations from which they sampled. However, despite their narrow  samples, behavioral scientists often are interested in drawing inferences about the human mind  and human behavior. This inferential step is rarely challenged or defended—with important  exceptions (e.g.,  Medin &amp; Atran, 2004; Rozin, 2001; Witkin &amp; Berry, 1975)—despite the lack of  any general effort to assess how well results from WEIRD samples generalize to the species.  This lack of epistemic vigilance underscores the prevalent, though implicit, assumption that the  findings one derives from a particular sample will generalize broadly; one adult human sample  is pretty much the same as the next. <marker type="block"/> Leading scientific journals and university textbooks routinely publish research findings claiming  to generalize to “humans” or “people” based on research done entirely with WEIRD  undergraduates. In top journals such as Nature and Science researchers frequently extend their  findings from undergraduates to the species—often declaring this generalization in their titles.  These contributions typically lack even a cautionary footnote about these inferential  extensions.  <marker type="page" number="9"/><marker type="block"/> In psychology, much of this generalization is implicit. A typical article does not claim to be  discussing “humans” but will rather simply describe a decision bias, psychological process, set  of correlations, etc., without addressing issues of generalizability, though findings are often  linked to “people.” Commonly, there is no demographic information about the participants,  aside from their age and gender. In recent years there is a trend to qualify some findings with  disclaimers such as “at least within Western culture,” though there remains a robust tendency  to generalize to the species. Arnett (2008) notes that psychologists would surely bristle if  journals were renamed to more accurately reflect the nature of their samples (e.g., Journal of  Personality and Social Psychology of American Undergraduate Psychology Students).  They  would bristle, presumably, because they believe that their findings generalize much beyond this  sample. Of course, there are important exceptions to this general tendency as some  researchers have assembled a broad database to provide evidence for universality (Buss, 1989;  Daly &amp; Wilson, 1988; Ekman, 1999b; Elfenbein &amp; Ambady, 2002; Tracy &amp; Matsumoto, 2008). <marker type="block"/> When is it safe to generalize from a narrow sample to the species? First, if one had good  empirical reasons to believe that little variability existed across diverse populations in a  particular domain it would be reasonable to tentatively infer universal processes from a single  subpopulation. Second, one could make an argument that as long as one’s samples were drawn  from near the center of the human distribution, then it would not be overly problematic to  generalize across the distribution more broadly—at least the inferred pattern would be in the  vicinity of the central tendency of our species. Below, with these assumptions in mind, we  review the evidence for the representativeness of findings from WEIRD people. <marker type="block"/> 2. Contrast 1: Industrialized Societies vs. SmallScale Societies  Our theoretical perspective, which is informed by evolutionary thinking, leads us to suspect that  many aspects of people’s psychological repertoire are universal. However, the current empirical  foundations for our suspicions are rather weak because the database of comparative studies  that include small‐scale societies is scant, despite the obvious importance of such societies in  understanding both the evolutionary history of our species and the potential impact of diverse  environments on our psychology. Here we first discuss the evidence for differences between  populations drawn from industrialized and small‐scale societies in some seemingly basic  psychological domains, and follow this with research indicating universal patterns across this  divide. </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="60"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="61">6</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="62">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="66" confidence="possible">2.1. Visual Perception  Many readers may suspect that tasks involving “low‐level” or “basic” cognitive processes such  as vision will not vary much across the human spectrum (Fodor, 1983). However, in the 1960s  an interdisciplinary team of anthropologists and psychologists systematically gathered data on </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="67"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="68">7</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="69">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="70">the susceptibility of both children and adults from a wide range of human societies to five  “standard illusions” (Segall, Campbell, &amp; Herskovits, 1966). Here we highlight the comparative  findings on the famed Mueller‐Lyer illusion, because of this illusion’s importance in textbooks,  and its prominent role as Fodor’s indisputable example of “cognitive impenetrability” in  debates about the modularity of cognition (McCauley &amp; Henrich, 2006). Note, however, that  population‐level variability in illusion susceptibility is not limited to Mueller‐Lyer illusion; it was  also found for the Sander‐Parallelogram and both Horizontal‐Vertical illusions.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="76" confidence="possible"> Segall et al. manipulated the length of the two lines in the  Mueller‐Lyer illusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FMueller‐Lyer illusion (Figure 1" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>) and estimated the magnitude  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FThe lines labeled ‘a’ and ‘b’ in " id="72" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>: Mueller‐Lyer Illusion.  The lines labeled ‘a’ and ‘b’ in  Mueller‐Lyer illusion (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fof the illusion by determining the approximate point at " id="73" class="deo:Reference">Figure 1</xref>) and estimated the magnitude  of the illusion by determining the approximate point at  each figure are the same  which the two lines were perceived as being the same  length. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Flength. Figure 2" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref> shows the results from 16 societies,  length. Many subjects perceive  length. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fincluding 14 small‐scale societies. The vertical axis gives the " id="75" class="deo:Reference">Figure 2</xref> shows the results from 16 societies,  including 14 small‐scale societies. The vertical axis gives the  line ‘b’ as longer than line ‘a’.  ‘point of subjective equality’ (PSE), which measures the  amount that segment ‘a’ must be longer than ‘b’ before the  two segments are judged equal in length. PSE measures the    strength of the illusion. </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="77"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="78">8</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="79">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx80">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62.page_011.image_03.png" thmb="62.page_011.image_03-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="81" confidence="possible"> </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F2">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="82">Figure 2: Mueller‐Lyer Results for Segall et. al.'s cross‐cultural project. PSE is the percentage that segment ‘a’ must be longer  than ‘b’ before individuals perceive them as equal. Children were sampled in the 5 to 11 age range. </caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="83">The results show substantial differences among populations, with American undergraduates  anchoring the extreme end of the distribution followed by the South African European sample,  from Johannesburg. On average, the undergraduates required that segment ‘a’ be about a fifth  longer than ‘b’ before the two segments were perceived as equal. At the other end, the San  foragers of the Kalahari were unaffected by the so‐called “illusion” (it’s not an illusion for  them). While the San’s PSE value cannot be distinguished from zero, the American  undergraduates’ PSE value is significantly different from all the other societies studied.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="84" confidence="possible">As discussed by Segall et. al., these findings suggest that visual exposure during ontogeny to  factors such as the “carpentered corners” of modern environments may favor certain optical  calibrations and visual habits that create and perpetuate this illusion. That is, the visual system  ontogenetically adapts to the presence of recurrent features in the local visual environment.  Since elements such as carpentered corners are products of particular cultural evolutionary  trajectories, and were not part of most environments for most of human history, the Mueller‐ Lyer illusion is a kind of culturally‐evolved byproduct (Henrich, 2008).  </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="85"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="86">9</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="87">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="89">These findings highlight three important considerations. First, this work suggests that even a  process as apparently basic as visual perception can show substantial variation across  populations. If visual perception can vary, what kind of psychological processes can we be sure  will not vary? It’s not merely that the strength of the illusory effect varies across populations –  the effect cannot be detected in two populations. Second, both American undergraduates and  children are at the extreme end of the distribution, showing significant differences from all  other populations studied, whereas many of the other populations cannot be distinguished  from one another. Since children already show large population‐level differences, it is not  obvious that developmental work can substitute for research across diverse human  populations. Children likely have different developmental trajectories in different societies.  Finally, this provides an example of how population‐level variation can be useful for illuminating  the nature of a psychological process, which would not be as evident in the absence of  comparative work.  2.2. Fairness and Cooperation in Economic Decision Making   By the mid‐1990s researchers were arguing that a set of robust experimental findings from  behavioral economics were evidence for a set of evolved universal motivations (Fehr &amp; Gächter,  1998; Hoffman, McCabe, &amp; Smith, 1998). Foremost among these experiments, the Ultimatum  Game, provides a pair of anonymous subjects with a sum of real money for a one‐shot  interaction. One of the pair—the proposer—can offer a portion of this sum to a second subject,  the responder. Responders must decide whether to accept or reject the offer. If a responder  accepts, she gets the amount of the offer and the proposer takes the remainder; if she rejects  both players get zero. If subjects are motivated purely by self‐interest, responders should  always accept any positive offer; knowing this, a self‐interested proposer should offer the  smallest non‐zero amount. Among subjects from industrialized populations—mostly  undergraduates from the U.S., Europe, and Asia—proposers typically offer an amount between  40% and 50% of the total, with a modal offer of 50% (Camerer, 2003). Offers below about 30%  are often rejected. <marker type="block"/> With this seemingly robust empirical finding in their sights, Nowak, Page and Sigmund (2000)  constructed an evolutionary analysis of the Ultimatum Game. When they modeled the  Ultimatum Game exactly as played, they did not get results matching the undergraduate  findings. However, if they added reputational information, such that players could know what  their partners did with others on previous rounds of play, the analysis predicted offers and  rejections in the range of typical undergraduate responses. They concluded that the Ultimatum  Game reveals humans’ species‐specific evolved capacity for fair and punishing behavior in  situations with substantial reputational influence. But, since the Ultimatum Game is typically  done one‐shot without reputational information, they argued that people make fair offers and  reject unfair offers because their motivations evolved in a world where such interactions were </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="90"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="91">10</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="92">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="93" confidence="possible">not fitness relevant—thus, we are not evolved to fully incorporate the possibility of non‐ reputational action in our decision‐making, at least in such artificial experimental contexts.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="95">Recent comparative work has dramatically altered this initial picture. Two unified projects  (which we call Phase 1 and Phase 2) have deployed the Ultimatum Game and other related  experimental tools across thousands of subjects randomly sampled from 23 small‐scale human  societies, including foragers, horticulturalists, pastoralists, and subsistence farmers, drawn from  Africa, Amazonia, Oceania, Siberia and New Guinea (Henrich et al., 2005; Henrich et al., 2006).  Three different experimental measures show that the people in industrialized societies  consistently occupy the extreme end of the human distribution. Notably, some of the smallest  scale societies, where real life is principally face‐to‐face, behaved in a manner reminiscent of  Nowak et. al.’s analysis before they added the reputational information. That is, these  populations made low offers and did not reject. <marker type="block"/> To concisely present these diverse empirical finding, we show results only from the Ultimatum  and Dictator Games in Phase II. The Dictator Game is the same as the Ultimatum Game except  that the second player cannot reject the offer. If subjects are motivated purely by self‐interest,  they would offer zero in the Dictator Game. Thus, Dictator Game offers yield a measure of  “fairness” (equal divisions) among two anonymous people. By contrast, Ultimatum Game offers  yield a measure of fairness combined with an assessment of the likelihood of rejection  (punishment). Rejections of offers in the Ultimatum Game provide a measure of people’s  willingness to punish unfairness.   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx96">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62.page_013.image_04.png" thmb="62.page_013.image_04-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="97" confidence="possible"> </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="98"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="99">11</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="100">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx101">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62.page_014.image_05.png" thmb="62.page_014.image_05-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="102" confidence="possible"> </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx103">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62.page_014.image_06.png" thmb="62.page_014.image_06-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="104" confidence="possible"> </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F3">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="106">Figure 3. Behavioral measures of fairness and punishment from the Dictator and Ultimatum Game for 15 societies  (Phase II). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FFigure 3C gives the income‐maximizing offer (IMO) for each society.  " id="105" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3A</xref> and 3B show mean offers for each society in the Dictator and Ultimatum Games, respectively.  Figure 3C gives the income‐maximizing offer (IMO) for each society.  </caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="119">Using aggregate measures, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fsample occupies the extreme end of the distribution in each case. For Dictator Game offers, " id="107" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3</xref> shows that the behavior of the U.S. adult (non‐student)  sample occupies the extreme end of the distribution in each case. For Dictator Game offers,  sample occupies the extreme end of the distribution in each case. For Dictator Game offers,  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FFigure 3A" id="108" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3A</xref> shows that the U.S. sample has the highest mean offer followed by the Sanquianga  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Ffrom Colombia, who are renowned for their prosociality (Kraul, 2008). The U.S. offers are nearly " id="109" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3A</xref> shows that the U.S. sample has the highest mean offer followed by the Sanquianga  from Colombia, who are renowned for their prosociality (Kraul, 2008). The U.S. offers are nearly <marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> double that of the Hadza, foragers from Tanzania, and the Tsimane, forager‐horticulturalists  from the Bolivian Amazon. For Ultimatum Game offers, the U.S. has the second highest mean  offer behind the Sursurunga, from Papua New Guinea. On the punishment side in the  Ultimatum Game, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FUltimatum Game, Figure 3C" id="114" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3C</xref> shows the income maximizing offers (IMO) for each population,  Ultimatum Game, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fwhich is a measure of the population’s willingness to punish inequitable offers. IMO is the offer " id="115" class="deo:Reference">Figure 3C</xref> shows the income maximizing offers (IMO) for each population,  which is a measure of the population’s willingness to punish inequitable offers. IMO is the offer  that an income‐maximizing proposer would make if he knew the probability of rejection for  each of the possible offer amounts. The U.S. sample is tied with the Sursurunga. These two  groups have an IMO five times higher than 70% of the other societies. While none of these  measures indicates that people from industrialized societies are entirely unique vis‐à‐vis other  populations, they do show that people from industrialized societies consistently occupy the  extreme end of the human distribution. <marker type="block"/> Analyses of these data show that a population’s degree of market integration and its  participation in a world religion both independently predict higher offers, and account for much  of the variation between populations. Community size positively predicts greater punishment  (Henrich et al., n.d.). The authors suggest that norms and institutions for exchange in  ephemeral interactions culturally coevolved with markets and expanding larger‐scale sedentary  populations. In some cases, at least in their most efficient forms, neither markets nor large  populations were feasible before such norms and institutions emerged. That is, it may be that  what behavioral economists have been measuring among undergraduates in such games is a  specific set of social norms, culturally evolved for dealing with money and strangers, that have  emerged since the origins of agriculture and the rise of complex societies. <marker type="block"/> In addition to revealing differences in populations’ willingness to reject offers that are too low,  almost half of the societies studied revealed an increasing willingness to reject offers that are  too high (Henrich et al., 2006). This phenomenon, which is not observed in undergraduates, has  now emerged among populations in Russia (Bahry &amp; Wilson, 2006) and China (Hennig‐Schmidt,  Li, &amp; Yang, 2008), as well as (to a lesser degree) among non‐student adults in Sweden (Wallace,  Cesarini, Lichtenstein, &amp; Johannesson, 2007), Germany (Guth et al., 2003) , and the Netherlands  (Bellemare et al., 2008). Efforts to explain this phenomena away, as a consequence of confusion  or misunderstanding, have not found support despite substantial efforts. <marker type="block"/> Suppose that Nowak and his coauthors were Tsimane, and that the numerous empirical  findings they had on hand were all from Tsimane villages. If this were the case, presumably  these researchers would have simulated the Ultimatum Game and found that there was no  need to add reputation to their model. This unadorned evolutionary solution would have  worked fine until they realized that the Tsimane are not representative of humanity. According  to the above data, the Tsimane are about as representative of the species as are Americans, but  at the opposite end of the spectrum. If the database of the behavioral sciences consisted </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="111"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="112">12</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="113">Weird People</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="120"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="121">13</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="122">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="123" confidence="possible">entirely of Tsimane subjects, researchers would likely be quite concerned about  generalizability.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="126">2.3. Folkbiological Reasoning  Recent work in small‐scale societies suggests that some of the central conclusions regarding the  development and operation of human folkbiological categorization, reasoning, and induction  are limited to urban subpopulations of non‐experts in industrialized societies. While much more  work needs to be done, it appears that typical subjects (children of WEIRD parents) develop  their folkbiological reasoning in a culturally and experientially impoverished environment, by  contrast to those of small‐scale societies (and of our evolutionary past), distorting both the  species‐typical pattern of cognitive development and the patterns of reasoning in WEIRD  adults. <marker type="block"/> Cognitive scientists using children drawn from U.S. urban centers, often surrounding  universities, have constructed an influential, though actively debated, developmental theory in  which folkbiological reasoning emerges from folkpsychological reasoning. Before age 7, urban  children reason about biological phenomena by analogy to, and by extension from, humans.  Between ages 7 and 10 urban children undergo a conceptual shift to the adult pattern of  viewing humans as one animal among many. These conclusions are underpinned by three  robust findings from urban children: (1) inferential projections of properties from humans are  stronger than projections from other living kinds, (2) inferences from humans to mammals  emerge as stronger than inferences from mammals to humans, and (3) children’s inferences  violate their own similarity judgments by, for example, providing stronger inference from  humans to bugs than from bugs to bees (Carey, 1985, 1995).  <marker type="block"/> However, when the folkbiological reasoning of children in rural Native American communities  in Wisconsin and Yukatek Maya in Mexico was investigated (Atran et al., 2001; Ross, Medin,  Coley, &amp; Atran, 2003; Waxman &amp; Medin, 2007) none of these three empirical patterns  emerged. Among the American urban children, the human category appears to be incorporated  into folkbiological induction relatively late compared to these other populations. The results  indicate that some background knowledge of the relevant species is crucial for the application  and induction across a hierarchical taxonomy (Atran et al., 2001). In rural environments both  exposure to, and interest in, the natural world is commonplace, unavoidable, and an inevitable  part of the enculturation process. This suggests that the anthropocentric patterns seen in U.S.  urban children results from insufficient cultural input and a lack of exposure to the natural  world. The only real animal that most urban children know much about is Homo sapiens, so it is  not surprising that this species dominates their inferential patterns. Since such urban  environments are highly “unnatural” from the perspective of human evolutionary history, any  conclusions drawn from subjects reared in such informationally impoverished environments </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="127"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="128">14</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="129">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="130" confidence="possible">must remain rather tentative. Indeed, studying the cognitive development of folkbiology in  urban children would seem the equivalent of studying “normal” physical growth in  malnourished children. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="140">This deficiency of input likely underpins the fact that the basic level folkbiological categories for  WEIRD adults are life‐form categories (e.g., bird, fish, and mammal) and these are also the first  categories learned by children: e.g., If you say “what’s that” (pointing at a maple tree), the  common answer is “tree”. However, in all small‐scale societies studied, the generic species  (e.g., maple, trout, and fox) are the basic level category and the first learned by children (Atran,  1993; Berlin, 1992). <marker type="block"/> Impoverished interactions with the natural world may also distort assessments of the typicality  of natural kinds in categorization. The standard conclusion from American undergraduate  samples has been that goodness of example, or typicality, is driven by similarity relations. A  robin is a typical bird because this species shares many of the perceptual features that are  commonly found in the category BIRD. In the absence of close familiarity with natural kinds,  this is the default strategy of American undergraduates, and psychology has assumed it is the  universal pattern. However in samples which interact with the natural world regularly, such as  Itza Maya villagers, typicality is based not on similarity, but on knowledge of cultural ideals,  reflecting the symbolic or material significance of the species in that culture. For the Itza, the  wild turkey is a typical bird because of its rich cultural significance, even though it is in no way  most similar to other birds. The same pattern holds for similarity effects in inductive  reasoning—WEIRD people make strong inferences from computations of similarity, whereas  populations with greater familiarity with the natural world, despite their capacity for similarity  –based inductions, prefer to make strong inferences from folkbiological knowledge that takes  into account ecological context and relationships among species (Atran, Medin, &amp; Ross, 2005).  In general, research suggests that what people think about can affect how they think (Bang,  Medin, &amp; Atran, 2007). To the extent that there is population‐level variability in the content of  folbiological beliefs, such variability affects cognitive processing in this domain. <marker type="block"/> Above we emphasized differences in folkbiological cognition uncovered by comparative  research. This same work has also uncovered reliably developing aspects of human  folkbiological cognition that do not vary, such as categorizing plants and animals in a  hierarchical taxonomy, or that the generic species level has the strongest inductive potential,  despite the fact that this level is not always the basic level across populations. Our goal in  emphasizing the differences here is to show (1) how peculiar industrialized (urban in this case)  samples are given the unprecedented environment they grow up in, and (2) how difficult it is to  conclude a priori what aspects will be reliably developing and robust across diverse slices of  humanity if research is largely conducted with WEIRD samples.  <marker type="page" number="18"/><marker type="block"/> 2.4. Spatial Cognition   Human societies vary in their linguistic tools for, and cultural practices associated with,  representing and communicating (1) directions in physical space, (2) the color spectrum, and (3)  integer amounts. There is some evidence that each of these differences in cultural content may  influence some aspects of non‐linguistic cognitive processes (D'Andrade, 1995; Gordon, 2005;  Kay, 2005; Levinson, 2003; Roberson, Davies, &amp; Davidoff, 2000). Here we focus on spatial  cognition, for which the evidence is most provocative. As above, it appears that industrialized  societies are at the extreme end of the continuum in spatial cognition. Human populations  show differences in how they think about spatial orientation and deal with directions, and  these differences may be influenced by linguistically‐based spatial reference systems. <marker type="block"/> Speakers of English and other Indo‐European languages favor the use of an egocentric (relative)  system to represent the location of objects relative to the self (e.g., “the man is on the right  side of the flagpole”). In contrast, many if not most, languages, favor an allocentric frame which  comes in two flavors. Some allocentric languages such as Guugu Yimithirr (an Australian  language) and Tzeltal (a Mayan language) favor a geocentric system in which absolute  reference is based on cardinal directions (“the man is west of the house”). The other allocentric  frame is an object‐centered (intrinsic) approach that locates objects in space, relative to some  coordinate system anchored to the object (“the man is behind the house”). When languages  possess systems for encoding all of these spatial reference frames, they often privilege one at  the expense of the others. However, the fact that some languages lack one or more of the  reference systems suggests that the accretion of all three systems into most contemporary  languages may be a product of long‐term cumulative cultural evolution.  <marker type="block"/> In data on spatial reference systems from 20 languages drawn from diverse societies—including  foragers, horticulturalists, agriculturalists, and industrialized populations—only three languages  relied on egocentric frames as their single preferred system of reference. All three were from  industrialized populations: Japanese, English and Dutch (Majid, Bowerman, Kita, Haun, &amp;  Levinson, 2004). <marker type="block"/> The presence of, or emphasis on, different reference systems may influence non‐linguistic  spatial reasoning (Levinson, 2003). In one study, Dutch and Tzeltal speakers were seated at a  table and shown an arrow pointing either to the right (north) or the left (south). They were  then rotated 180 degrees to a second table where they saw two arrows: one pointing to the left  (north) and the other one pointing to the right (south). Participants were asked which arrow on  the second table was like the one they saw before. Consistent with the spatial‐marking system  of their languages, Dutch speakers chose the relative solution, whereas the Tzeltal speakers  chose the absolute solution. Several other comparative experiments testing spatial memory </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="134"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="135">15</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="136">Weird People</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="141"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="142">16</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="143">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="144" confidence="possible">and reasoning are consistent with this pattern, although lively debates about interpretation  persist (Levinson, Kita, Haun, &amp; Rasch, 2002; Li &amp; Gleitman, 2002). </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="150">Extending the above exploration, Haun and colleagues (Haun, Call, Janzen, &amp; Levinson, 2006;  Haun, Rapold, Call, Janzen, &amp; Levinson, 2006) examined performance on a spatial reasoning  task similar to the one described above using children and adults from different societies and  great apes. In the first step, Dutch‐speaking adults and eight‐year olds (speakers of an  egocentric language) showed the typical egocentric bias, whereas Hai//om‐speaking adults and  eight‐year olds (a Namibian foraging population who speak an allocentric language) showed a  typical allocentric bias. In the second step, four‐year old German‐speaking children, gorillas,  orangutans, chimpanzees, and bonobos were tested on a simplified version of the same task.  All showed a marked preference for allocentric reasoning. These results suggest that children  share with other great apes an innate preference for allocentric spatial reasoning, but that this  bias can be overridden by input from language and cultural routines. <marker type="block"/> If one were to work on spatial cognition exclusively with WEIRD subjects (say, using subjects  from the U.S. and Europe) one might conclude that children start off with an allocentric bias but  naturally shift to an egocentric bias with maturation. The problem with this conclusion is that it  would not apply to many human populations, and may be the product of particular cultural  environments. The next telescoping contrast highlights some additional evidence suggesting  that WEIRD people may even be unusual in their egocentric bias vis‐à‐vis most other  industrialized populations.   2.5. Other Potential Differences  We have discussed several lines of data suggesting, not only population‐level variation, but that  industrialized populations are consistently unusual compared to small‐scale societies. There are  also numerous studies that have found differences between much smaller numbers of samples  (usually two samples). In these studies it is impossible to discern who is unusual, the small‐scale  society or the WEIRD population. For example, one study found that both samples from two  different industrialized populations were risk‐averse decision makers when facing monetary  gambles involving gains (Henrich &amp; McElreath, 2002) while both samples of small‐scale societies  were risk‐prone. Risk‐aversion for monetary gains may be a recent, local phenomenon.  Similarly, extensive inter‐temporal choice experiments using a panel method of data collection  indicates that the Tsimane, an Amazonian population of forager‐horticulturalists, discount the  future 10 times more steeply than WEIRD people (Godoy et al., 2004). In Uganda, a study of  individual decision‐making among small‐scale farmers showed qualitatively different deviations  from expected utility maximization then is typically found among undergraduates. For example,  rather than the inverse S‐shape for probabilities in Prospect Theory, a regular S‐shape was  found. 3  <marker type="page" number="20"/><marker type="block"/> 2.6. Similarities Between Industrialized and SmallScale Societies  Some larger‐scale comparative projects show universal patterns in human psychology. Here we  list some noteworthy examples: </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="147"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="148">17</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="149">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="151" confidence="possible">1) Some illusions: We discussed the Mueller‐Lyer illusion above. However, there are  illusions, such as the Perspective Drawing Illusion, for which the industrialized populations  are not extreme outliers, and for which perception varies little in the populations studied  (Segall et al., 1966).   2) Perceiving color: While the number of basic color terms systematically varies across  human languages (Regier, Kay, &amp; Cook, 2005), the ability to perceive different colors does  emerge in small‐scale societies (Rivers, 1901), 4  although terms and categories do  influence color perception at the margins (Kay &amp; Regier, 2006).   3) Emotional expression: In studying facial displays of emotions, Ekman and colleagues  have shown much evidence for universality in recognition of the “basic” facial expressions  of emotions, although this work has included only a small—yet convincing—sampling of  small‐scale societies (Ekman, 1999a, 1999b). There is also evidence for the universality of  pride displays (Tracy &amp; Matsumoto, 2008; Tracy &amp; Robins, 2008). This main effect for  emotional recognition across population (58% of variance) is qualified by a smaller effect  for cultural specificity of emotional expressions (9% of variance:  Elfenbein &amp; Ambady,  2002).  4) False Belief Tasks: Comparative work in China, the U.S., Canada, Peru, India, Samoa  and Thailand suggests that the ability to explicitly pass the false belief task emerges in all  populations studied (Callaghan et al., 2005; Liu, Wellman, Tardif, &amp; Sabbagh, 2008),  although the age at which subjects can pass the explicit version of the false belief task  varies from 4 to at least 9 (Boesch, 2007; Callaghan et al., 2005; Liu et al., 2008), with  industrialized populations at the extreme low end.  5) Analog numeracy: There is growing consensus in the literature on numerical thinking  that quantity estimation relies on a primitive “analog” number sense that is sensitive to  quantity but limited in accuracy. This cognitive ability appears to be independent of  counting practices and was shown to operate in similar ways among two Amazonian  societies with very limited counting systems (Gordon, 2005; Pica, Lerner, Izard, &amp;  Dehaene, 2004), as well as in infants and primates (e.g., Dehaene, 1997).   6) Social relationships: Research on the cognitive processes underlying social  relationships reveals similar patterns across distinct populations. Fiske (1993) studied  people’s tendency to confuse one person with another (e.g., intending to phone your son </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="152"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="153">18</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="154">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" confidence="possible">Bob but accidently calling your son Fred). Chinese, Korean, Bengali and Vai (Liberia and  Sierra Leone) immigrants tended to confuse people in the same category of social  relationship. Interestingly, the social categories in which the most confusion occurred  varied across populations.   7) Psychological essentialism: Research from a variety of societies, including Vezo  children in Madagascar (Astuti, Solomon, &amp; Carey, 2004), children from impoverished  neighborhoods in Brazil (Sousa, Atran, &amp; Medin, 2002), Menominee in Wisconsin  (Waxman, Medin, &amp; Ross, 2007), and middle‐class children and adults in the United States  (Gelman, 2003), show evidence of perceiving living organisms as having an underlying and  non‐trivial nature that makes them what they are. Psychological essentialism also extends  to the understanding of social groups, which may be found in Americans (Gelman, 2003),  rural Ukranians (Kanovsky, 2007), Vezo (Astuti, 2001), Mapuche farmers (Chile), Iraqi  Chaldean immigrants in Detroit (Henrich &amp; Henrich, 2007), and Mongolian herdsmen (Gil‐ White, 2001). Notably, this evidence is not well suited to examining differences in the  degree of psychological essentialism across populations, though it suggests that inter‐ population variation may be substantial.  There are also numerous studies involving dyadic comparisons between a single small‐scale  society and a western population (or a pattern of western results) in which cross‐population  similarities have been found. Examples are numerous but include the development of an  understanding of death (Barrett &amp; Behne, 2005), shame (Fessler, 2004) 5  and cheater detection  (Sugiyama, Tooby, &amp; Cosmides, 2002). Finding evidence for similarities across two such  disparate populations is an important step towards providing evidence for universality  (Norenzayan &amp; Heine, 2005); however, the case would be considerably stronger if it was found  across a larger number of diverse populations. 6     2.7. Summary for Contrast 1  Although there are several domains in which the data from small‐scale societies appear similar  to that from industrialized societies, comparative projects involving visual illusions, social  motivations (fairness), folkbiological cognition, and spatial cognition all show industrialized  populations as outliers. Given all this, it seems problematic to generalize from industrialized  populations to humans more broadly, in the absence of supportive empirical evidence. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="156">3. Contrast 2: Western 7  vs. NonWestern Societies     For our second contrast, we review evidence comparing Western to non‐Western populations.  Here we examine four of the most studied domains, including social decision‐making (fairness,  cooperation and punishment), independent vs. interdependent self‐concepts (and associated </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="157"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="158">19</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="159">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="160" confidence="possible">motivations), analytic vs. holistic reasoning, and moral reasoning. We also briefly return to  spatial cognition.  3.1. Antisocial punishment and cooperation   In the previous contrast we reviewed social decision‐making experiments showing that  industrialized populations occupy the extreme end of the behavioral distribution vis‐à‐vis a  broad swath of smaller‐scale societies. Here we show that even among industrialized  populations, Westerners are again clumped at the extreme end of the behavioral distribution.  Notably, the behaviors measured in the experiments discussed below are strongly correlated  with the strength of formal institutions, norms of civic cooperation, and GDP per capita.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="162">In 2002 Fehr and Gächter published their classic paper, “Altruistic Punishment in Humans,” in  Nature, based on public goods games with and without punishment conducted with  undergraduates at the University of Zurich. The paper demonstrated that adding the possibility  of punishment to a cooperative dilemma dramatically altered the outcome from a gradual slide  towards little cooperation (and rampant free‐riding) to a steady increase towards stable  cooperation. Enough subjects were willing to punish non‐cooperators at a cost to themselves to  shift the balance from free‐riding to cooperation. In stable groups this cooperation‐punishment  combination dramatically increases long‐run gains (Gachter, Renner, &amp; Sefton, 2008). <marker type="block"/> To examine the generalizability of these results, which many took to be a feature of our species,  Herrmann, Thoni and Gächter (2008) conducted systematic comparable experiments among  undergraduates from a diverse swath of industrialized populations. In these public goods  games, subjects played with the same four partners for 10 rounds and could contribute during  each round to a group project. All contributions to the group project were multiplied by 1.6 and  distributed equally among all partners. Players could also pay to punish other players by taking  money away from them. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="165" confidence="possible">In addition to finding population‐level differences in their initial willingness to cooperate,  Gächter’s team unearthed a phenomena in about half of these samples that is not observed  beyond a trivial degree among typical undergraduate subjects (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fbeyond a trivial degree among typical undergraduate subjects (see Figure 4" id="163" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>): many subjects  beyond a trivial degree among typical undergraduate subjects (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fengaged in anti‐social punishment; that is, they paid to reduce the earnings of “overly” " id="164" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>): many subjects  engaged in anti‐social punishment; that is, they paid to reduce the earnings of “overly”  cooperative individuals (those who contributed more than the punisher). The effect of this  behavior on levels of cooperation was dramatic, completely compensating for the cooperation‐ inducing effects of punishment in the Zurich experiment. Possibilities for altruistic punishment  do not generate high levels of cooperation in these populations. Meanwhile, participants from  a number of Western countries, such as the U.S., U.K, and Australia, behaved like the original  Zurich students. Thus, it appears that the Zurich sample works well for generalizing to the </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="166"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="167">20</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="168">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169">patterns of other Western samples (as well as the Chinese sample), but such findings cannot be  readily extended beyond this.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx170">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62.page_023.image_07.png" thmb="62.page_023.image_07-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="171" confidence="possible"> </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F4">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="172">Fig. 4. Mean punishment expenditures from each sample for a given deviation from the punisher’s contribution to the public  good. The deviations of the punished subject’s contribution from the punisher’s contribution are grouped into five intervals,  where [‐20,‐11] indicates that the punished subjects contributed between 11 and 20 less than the punishing subject; [0]  indicates that the punished subject contributed exactly the same amount as the punishing subject and [1,10] ([11,20)]  indicates that the punished subject contributed between 1 and 10 (11 and 20) more than the punishing subject. Adapted  from Herrmann et. al. (2008).  </caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="173" confidence="possible">3.2. Independent and Interdependent SelfConcepts  Much psychological research has explored the nature of people’s self‐concepts. Self‐concepts  are important as they organize the information that people have about themselves, direct  attention to information that is perceived to be relevant, shape motivations, influence how  people appraise situations that influence their emotional experiences, and guide their choices  of relationship partners. Markus and Kitayama (1991) posited that self‐concepts can take on a  continuum of forms stretching between two poles, termed independent and interdependent  self‐views, which relate to the individualism‐collectivism construct (Triandis, 1989, 1994). Do  people conceive of themselves primarily as self‐contained individuals, understanding  themselves as autonomous agents that consist largely of component parts, such as attitudes,  personality traits, and abilities? Or do they conceive of themselves as interpersonal beings </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="174"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="175">21</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="176">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="177" confidence="possible">intertwined with one another in social webs, with incumbent role‐based obligations towards  others within those networks? The extent to which people perceive themselves in ways similar  to these independent or interdependent poles has significant consequences for a variety of  emotions, cognitions, and motivations.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="178">Much research has underscored how Westerners have more independent views of self than  non‐Westerners. For example, research using the Twenty Statements Test (Kuhn &amp; McPartland,  1954) reveals that people from Western populations (e.g., Australians, Americans, Canadians,  Swedes) are far more likely to understand their selves in terms of internal psychological  characteristics, such as their personality traits and attitudes, and are less likely to understand  them in terms of roles and relationships, than are people from non‐Western populations, such  as Native Americans, Cook Islanders, Maasai, Samburu (both African pastoralists), Malaysians,  and East Asians (for a review see Heine, 2008). Studies using other measures (Hofstede, 1980;  Morling &amp; Lamoreaux, 2008; Oyserman, Coon, &amp; Kemmelmeier, 2002; Triandis, Mccusker, &amp;  Hui, 1990) provide convergent evidence that Westerners tend to have more independent, and  less interdependent, self‐concepts than those of other populations. These data converge with  much ethnographic observation, in particular Geertz’s (1974: 16) claim that the Western self is,  “a rather peculiar idea within the context of the world’s cultures.” </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="179" confidence="possible">There are numerous psychological patterns associated with self‐concepts. For example, people  with independent self‐concepts are more likely to demonstrate (1) positively biased views of  themselves; (2) a heightened valuation of personal choice; and (3) an increased motivation to  “stand out” rather than to “fit in.” Each of these represents a significant research enterprise,  and we discuss them in turn.   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="180">3.2.1. Positive SelfViews  The most widely endorsed assumption regarding the self is that people are motivated to view  themselves positively. Brown (1986) famously declared this motivation to maintain high self‐ esteem an “urge so deeply human, we can hardly imagine its absence” (p. 534). The strength of  this motivation has been perhaps most clearly documented by assessing the ways that people  go about exaggerating their self‐views by engaging in self‐serving biases, in which people view  themselves more positively than objective benchmarks would justify. For example, in one  study, ninety‐four percent of American professors rated themselves as better‐than‐average  (Cross, 1977).  However, meta‐analyses reveals that these self‐serving biases tend to be more  pronounced in Western populations than in non‐Western ones (Heine &amp; Hamamura, 2007;  Mezulis, Abramson, Hyde, &amp; Hankin, 2004)—for example, Mexicans (Tropp &amp; Wright, 2003),  Native Americans (Fryberg &amp; Markus, 2003), Chileans (Heine &amp; Raineri, 2009), and Fijians  (Rennie &amp; Dunne, 1994) score much lower on various measures of positive self‐views than do  Westerners (although there are some exceptions to this general pattern: Harrington &amp; Liu, </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="181"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="182">22</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="183">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="184" confidence="possible">2002). Indeed, in some cultural contexts, most notably East Asian ones, evidence for self‐ serving biases tends to be null, or in some cases, show significant reversals, with East Asians  demonstrating self‐effacing biases (Heine &amp; Hamamura, 2007). At best, the sharp self‐ enhancing biases of Westerners are less pronounced in much of the rest of the world, though  self‐enhancement has long been discussed as if it were a fundamental aspect of human  psychology (e.g., Rogers, 1951; Tesser, 1988). </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="193">3.2.2. Personal Choice  Psychology has long been fascinated with how people assert agency by making choices  (Bandura, 1982; Kahneman &amp; Tversky, 2000; Schwartz, 2004), and has explored the efforts that  people go through to ensure that their actions feel freely chosen and that their choices are  sensible. However, there is considerable variation across populations in the extent to which  people value choice and the range of behaviors over which they feel that they are making  choices. For example, one study found that European‐American children preferred working on a  task, worked on it longer, and performed better on it, if they had made some superficial choices  regarding the task than if others made the same choices for them. In contrast, Asian‐American  children were equally motivated by the task if a trusted other made the same choices for them  (Iyengar &amp; Lepper, 1999). Another pair of studies found that Indians were slower at making  choices, were less likely to make choices consistent with their personal preferences, and were  less likely to view their actions as expressions of choice, than were Americans (Savani, Markus,  &amp; Conner, 2008; Savani, Markus, Naidu, Kumar, &amp; Berlia, in press). Likewise, the extent to which  people feel that they have much choice in their lives varies across populations. Surveys  conducted at bank branches in Argentina, Brazil, Mexico, the Philippines, Singapore, Taiwan,  and the United States found that Americans were more likely to perceive having more choice at  their jobs than those from the other countries (Iyengar &amp; DeVoe, 2003). Another survey  administered in over 40 countries found, in general, that feelings of free choice in one’s life  were considerably higher in Western nations (e.g., Finland, the US, and Northern Ireland) than  in various non‐Western nations (e.g., Turkey, Japan, and Belarus: Inglehart et al., 1998). This  research reveals that perceptions of choice are experienced less often, and are a lesser  concern, among those from non‐Western populations.  3.2.3. Motivations to Conform  Many studies have explored whether motivations to conform are similar across populations by  employing a standard experimental procedure (Asch, 1951, 1952). In these studies, which were  initially conducted with Americans, participants first hear a number of confederates making a  perceptual judgment that is obviously incorrect, and then participants are given the  opportunity to state their own judgment. A majority of American participants were found to go  along with the majority’s incorrect judgment at least once. This research sparked much interest, <marker type="page" number="26"/><marker type="block"/> apparently because Westerners typically feel that they are acting on their own independent  resolve and are not conforming. A meta‐analysis of studies performed in 17 societies (Bond &amp;  Smith, 1996), including subjects from Oceania, the Middle East, South America, Africa, South  America, East Asia, Europe, and the U.S., found that motivations for conformity are weaker in  Western societies than elsewhere. Other research converges with this conclusion. For example,  Kim and Markus (1999) found that Koreans preferred objects that were more common whereas  Americans showed a greater preference for objects that were more unusual.   3.3. Analytic vs. Holistic Reasoning  Variation in favored modes of reasoning has been compared across several populations. Most  of the research has contrasted Western (American, Canadian, Western European) with East  Asian (Chinese, Japanese, Korean) populations with regard to their relative reliance on what is  known as holistic vs. analytic reasoning (Nisbett, 2003; Peng &amp; Nisbett, 1999). However,  growing evidence from other non‐Western populations point to a divide between Western  nations and most everyone else, including groups as diverse as Arabs, Malaysians, and Russians  (see Norenzayan, Choi, &amp; Peng, 2007 for review), as well as subsistence farmers in Africa and  South America and sedentary foragers (Norenzayan, Henrich, &amp; McElreath, n.d.; Witkin &amp; Berry,  1975), rather than an East‐West divide.  Holistic thought involves an orientation to the context or field as a whole, including attention to  relationships between a focal object and the field, and a preference for explaining and  predicting events on the basis of such relationships. Analytic thought involves a detachment of  objects from contexts, a tendency to focus on objects’ attributes, and a preference for using  categorical rules to explain and predict behavior. This distinction between habits of thought  rests on a theoretical partition between two reasoning systems. One system is associative, and  its computations reflect similarity and contiguity (i.e., whether two stimuli share perceptual  resemblances and co‐occur in time); the other system relies on abstract, symbolic  representational systems, and its computations reflect a rule‐based structure (e.g., Neisser,  1963; Sloman, 1996).   Although both cognitive systems are available in all normal adults, different environments,  experiences, and cultural routines may encourage reliance on one system at the expense of  another, giving rise to population‐level differences in the use of these different cognitive  strategies to solve identical problems. There is growing evidence that a key factor influencing  the prominence of analytic vs. holistic cognition is the different self‐construals prevalent across  populations. First, independent self‐construal primes facilitate analytic processing, whereas  interdependent primes facilitate holistic processing (Oyserman &amp; Lee, 2008). Second,  geographic regions with greater prevalence of interdependent self‐construals show more  holistic processing, as can be seen in comparisons of Northern and Southern Italians, Hokkaido <marker type="page" number="27"/><marker type="block"/> and mainland Japanese, and Western and Eastern Europeans (Varnum, Grossmann, Kitayama,  &amp; Nisbett, 2008).  Furthermore, the analytic approach is culturally more valued in Western contexts, whereas the  holistic approach is more valued in East Asian contexts, leading to normative judgments about  cognitive strategies that differ across the respective populations (Buchtel &amp; Norenzayan, 2008).  Below we highlight some findings from this research showing that, compared to diverse  populations of non‐Westerners, Westerners (1) attend more to objects than fields; (2) explain  behavior in more decontextualized terms; and (3) rely more on rules over similarity relations to  classify objects; (for further discussion of the cross‐cultural evidence Nisbett, 2003; Norenzayan  et al., 2007).</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="186"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="187">23</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="188">Weird People</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="190"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="191">24</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="192">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="194" confidence="possible">1) Using evidence derived from the Rod &amp; Frame Test and Embedded Figures Test, Witkin  and Berry (1975) summarize a wide range of evidence from migratory and sedentary  foraging populations (Arctic, Australia and Africa), sedentary agriculturalists, and  industrialized Westerners. Only Westerners and migratory foragers consistently  emerged at the field independent end of the spectrum. Recent work among East Asians   (Ji, Nisbett, &amp; Zhang, 2004) in industrialized societies using the Rod &amp; Frame Test, the  Framed Line Test (Kitayama, Duffy, Kawamura, &amp; Larsen, 2003), and the Embedded  Figures Test again shows Westerners at the field independent end of the spectrum,  compared to field dependent East Asians, Malays and Russians (Grossmann, Na,  Varunum, Kitayama, &amp; Nisbett, 2008; Kuhnen et al., 2001). Similarly, Norenzayan et. al.  (2007)  found that Canadians showed less field‐dependent processing than Chinese,  who in turn were less field‐dependent than Arabs (also see Zebian &amp; Denny, 2001).    2) East Asians’ recall for objects is worse than Americans if the background has been  switched (Masuda &amp; Nisbett, 2001), indicating that they are attending to the field more.   This difference in attention has also been found in saccadic eye‐movements as  measured with eye‐trackers. Americans gaze at focal objects longer than East Asians,  who in turn gaze at the background more than Americans (Chua, Boland, &amp; Nisbett,  2005).  Furthermore, when performing identical cognitive tasks, East Asians and  Westerners show differential brain activation, corresponding to the predicted cultural  differences in cognitive processing (Gutchess, Welsh, Boduroglu, &amp; Park, 2006; Hedden,  Ketay, Aron, Markus, &amp; Gabrieli, 2008).  3) Several classic studies, initially conducted with Western participants, found that  “people” tend to make strong attributions about a person’s disposition, even when  there are compelling situational constraints (Jones &amp; Harris, 1967; Ross, Amabile, &amp;  Steinmetz, 1977).  This tendency to ignore situational information in favor of  dispositional information is so commonly observed—among typical subjects—that it </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="195"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="196">25</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="197">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="198" confidence="possible">was dubbed the “fundamental attribution error” (Ross et al., 1977).  However,  consistent with much ethnography in non‐Western cultures (e.g., Geertz, 1975),  comparative experimental work demonstrates differences that, while Americans attend  to dispositions at the expense of situations (Gilbert &amp; Malone, 1995), East Asians are  more likely than Americans to infer that behaviors are strongly controlled by the  situation (Miyamoto &amp; Kitayama, 2002; Morris &amp; Peng, 1994; Norenzayan, Choi, &amp;  Nisbett, 2002; Van Boven, Kamada, &amp; Gilovich, 1999), particularly when situational  information is made salient (Choi &amp; Nisbett, 1998). 8  Grossmann (2008) provides parallel  findings with Russians. Likewise, in an investigation of people’s lay beliefs about  personality across eight populations, Church et al. (2006) found that people from  Western populations (i.e., American and Euro‐Australian) strongly endorsed the notion  that traits remain stable over time and predict behavior over many situations, while  those from non‐Western populations (i.e., Asian‐Australian, Chinese‐Malaysian, Filipino,  Japanese, Mexican, and Malay) more strongly endorsed contextual beliefs about  personality, such as ideas suggesting that traits do not describe a person as well as roles  or duties, and that trait‐related behavior changes from situation to situation. These  patterns are consistent with earlier work on attributions comparing Euro‐Americans  with Hindu Indians (see Miller, 1984; Shweder &amp; Bourne, 1982).  Thus, although  dispositional inferences can be found outside the West, the fundamental attribution  error seems less fundamental elsewhere (Choi, Nisbett, &amp; Norenzayan, 1999).  4) Westerners are also more likely to rely on rules over similarity relations in reasoning and  categorization. Chinese subjects were found to be more likely to group together objects  which shared a functional (e.g., pencil‐notebook) or contextual (e.g., sky‐sunshine)  relationship while Americans were more likely to group objects together if they  belonged to a category defined by a simple rule (e.g., notebook‐magazine, (Ji et al.,  2004). Similarly, work with Russian students (Grossmann et al., 2008), and Russian  small‐scale farmers (Luria, 1976), showed strong tendencies for participants to group  objects according to their practical functions. This appears widespread, as Norenzayan  et. al. (n.d.) examined classification among the Mapuche and Sangu subsistence farmers  in Chile and Tanzania, respectively, and found that their classification resembled the  Chinese pattern, although it was exaggerated towards holistic reasoning.  5) In a similar vein, research with East Asians found they were more likely to group objects  if they shared a strong family resemblance, whereas Americans were more likely to  group the same objects if they could be assigned to that group on the basis of a  deterministic rule (Norenzayan, Smith, Kim, &amp; Nisbett, 2002). When those results are  compared to Uskul et. al.’s (2008), which used the same stimuli, findings from herders, </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="199"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="200">26</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="201">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="203" confidence="possible"> fishermen, and farmers living on the Black Sea in Turkey, it is evident that European  Americans are again at the extreme (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="FAmericans are again at the extreme (Figure 5" id="202" class="deo:Reference">Figure 5</xref>).  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx204">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="62.page_029.image_08.png" thmb="62.page_029.image_08-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="205" confidence="possible"> </region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="F5">
        <caption class="deo:Caption" id="206">Fig. 5. Relative dominance of rule‐based versus family resemblance‐based judgments of categories for the same cognitive  task. European‐American, Asian‐American, and East Asian university students were tested by Norenzayan et al, 2002; the  herders, fishermen, and farmers of Turkey’s Black Sea coast were tested by Uskul et al, 2008. Positive scores indicate a  relative bias towards rule‐based judgments, whereas negative scores indicate a relative bias towards family‐resemblance  based judgments. It can be seen that European American students show the most pronounced bias towards rule‐based  judgments, and are outliers in terms of absolute deviation from zero. Adapted from Norenzayan et al, 2002, and Uskul et al  2008.  </caption>
      </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="217">In summary, although analytic and holistic cognitive systems are available to all normal adults, a  large body of evidence shows that the habitual use of what are considered “basic” cognitive  processes, including those involved in attention, perception, categorization, deductive  reasoning, and social inference, vary systematically across populations in predictable ways,  highlighting the difference between the West and the rest. Several biases and patterns are not  merely differences in strength or tendency, but show reversals of Western patterns. We  emphasize, however, that Westerners are not unique in their cognitive styles (Uskul et al.,  2008; Witkin &amp; Berry, 1975), but they do occupy the extreme end of the distribution.  3.4. Moral Reasoning  A central concern in the developmental literature has been the way people acquire the  cognitive foundations of moral reasoning. The most influential approach to the development of  moral reasoning has been Kohlberg’s (1971; 1976; 1981), in which people’s abilities to reason  morally are seen to hinge on cognitive abilities that develop over maturation. Kohlberg  proposed that people progressed through the same three levels: 1) children start out at a pre‐ conventional level, viewing right and wrong as based on internal standards regarding the <marker type="page" number="30"/><marker type="block"/> physical or hedonistic consequences of actions; 2) then they progress to a conventional level,  where morality is based on external standards, such as that which maintains the social order of  their group; and finally 3) some progress further to a post‐conventional level, where they no  longer rely on external standards for evaluating right and wrong, but instead do so on the basis  of abstract ethical principles regarding justice and individual rights—the moral code inherent in  most Western Constitutions.   <marker type="block"/> While all of Kohlberg’s levels are commonly found in WEIRD populations, much subsequent  research has revealed scant evidence for post‐conventional moral reasoning in other  populations. One meta‐analysis carried out with data from 27 countries found consistent  evidence for post‐conventional moral reasoning in all the Western urbanized samples, yet  found no evidence for this type of reasoning in small‐scale societies (Snarey, 1985).  Furthermore, it is not just that formal education is necessary to achieve Kohlberg’s post‐ conventional level. Some highly educated non‐Western populations do not show this post‐ conventional reasoning. At Kuwait University, for example, faculty members score lower on  Kohlberg’s schemes than the typical norms for Western adults, and the elder faculty there  scored no higher than the younger ones, contrary to Western patterns (Al‐Shehab, 2002; Miller,  Bersoff, &amp; Harwood, 1990).   <marker type="block"/> Research in moral psychology indicates that typical Western subjects rely principally on justice‐  and harm/care‐based principles in judging morality. However, recent work indicates that non‐ Western adults and Western religious conservatives rely on a wider range of moral principles  than these two dimensions of morality (Baek, 2002; Haidt &amp; Graham, 2007; Haidt, Koller, &amp;  Dias, 1993; e.g., Miller &amp; Bersoff, 1992). Shweder, Much, Mahapatra, and Park (1997) proposed  that in addition to a dominant justice‐based morality, which they termed an ethic of autonomy,  there are two other ethics that are commonly found outside the West: an ethic of community,  in which morality derives from the fulfillment of interpersonal obligations that are tied to an  individual’s role within the social order, and an ethic of divinity in which people are perceived  to be bearers of something holy or god‐like, and have moral obligations to not act in ways that  are degrading to or incommensurate with that holiness. The ethic of divinity requires that  people treat their bodies as temples, not as playgrounds, and so personal choices that seem to  harm nobody else (e.g., about food, sex, and hygiene) are sometimes moralized (for a further  elaboration of moral foundations see Haidt &amp; Graham, 2007).  In sum, the high‐SES, secular  Western populations that have been the primary target of study thus far appear unusual in a  global context, based on their peculiarly narrow reliance, relative to the rest of humanity, on a  single foundation for moral reasoning (based on justice, individual rights, and the avoidance of  harm to others; cf., Haidt &amp; Graham, 2007).  <marker type="page" number="31"/><marker type="block"/> 3.5. Other Potential Differences   There are many other psychological phenomena in which Western samples differ from non‐ Western ones; however, at present there are insufficient data in these domains derived from  diverse populations to assess where Westerners reside in the human spectrum. For example,  compared with Westerners, some non‐Westerners (1) have less dynamic social networks, in  which people work to avoid negative interactions among their existing networks rather than  seeking new relations (Adams, 2005), (2) prefer lower to higher arousal positive affective states  (Tsai, 2007), (3) are less egocentric when they try to take the perspective of others (Cohen,  Hoshino‐Browne, &amp; Leung, 2007; Wu &amp; Keysar, 2007), (4) have weaker motivations for  consistency (Kanagawa, Cross, &amp; Markus, 2001; Suh, 2002), (5) are less prone to “social‐loafing”  (i.e., reducing efforts on group tasks when individual contributions are not being monitored;  (Earley, 1993), (6) associate fewer benefits with a person’s physical attractiveness (Anderson,  Adams, &amp; Plaut, 2008), and (7) have more pronounced motivations to avoid negative outcomes  relative to their motivations to approach positive outcomes (Elliot, Chirkov, Kim, &amp; Sheldon,  2001; Lee, Aaker, &amp; Gardner, 2000).  </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="208"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="209">27</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="210">Weird People</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="214"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="215">28</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="216">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="218" confidence="possible">With reference to the spatial reasoning patterns discussed earlier, emerging evidence suggests  that a geocentric bias (i.e., a landscape‐ or earth‐fixed spatial coordinate system) may be much  more widespread than previously thought—indeed, it may be the common pattern outside of  the West (even among non‐Western speakers of languages which make regular use of  egocentric linguistic markers). Comparative research contrasting children and adults in Geneva  with samples in Indonesia, Nepal, and rural and urban India have found the typical geocentric  reasoning pattern in all of these populations except for the Geneva samples (Dasen, Mishra,  Niraula, &amp; Wassmann, 2006). While many of these population‐level differences are  pronounced, more research is needed before we can assess whether the geocentric pattern is  common across a broader swath of humanity.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="219">3.6. Similarities Between Western and NonWestern Societies  We expect that as more large‐scale comparative studies of Western and non‐Western  populations are conducted, they will reveal substantial similarities in psychological processes.  However, given the relative ease of conducting such studies (as compared to working in small‐ scale societies) there have been few comparative programs that have put universality claims to  the test. Here we highlight three examples of larger‐scale comparative projects that show  broad and important similarities across populations.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="220" confidence="possible">1) Mate preferences: First, Buss (1989) compared people from 37 (largely industrialized)  populations around the world and found some striking similarities in their mate  preferences. In all 37 of the populations, males ranked the physical attractiveness of  their mates to be more important than did females, and in 34 of the 37 populations, </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="221"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="222">29</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="223">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="225" confidence="possible">females ranked the ambition and industriousness of their mates as more important than  did males (but for other interpretations see Eagly &amp; Wood, 1999) 9  Likewise, Kenrick and  Keefe (1992a; 1992b) provide evidence of robust differences in age preferences of  mates across populations. Finally, comparative research examining men’s preferred  waist to hip ratios in potential mates finds that men in both industrialized and  developing large‐scale populations prefer a waist to hip ratio of around 0.7 (Singh, 2006;  Singh &amp; Luis, 1994; Streeter &amp; McBurney, 2003; Swami, Neto, Tovée, &amp; Furnham,  2007). 10     2) Personality structure: Recent efforts have taken personality instruments to university  students in 51 different countries (McCrae et al., 2005). In most of these populations the  same five factor structure emerges that has previously been found with American  samples, 11  indicating the universal structure of personality (also see Allik &amp; Mccrae,  2004; Yik, Russell, Ahn, Fernandez‐Dols, &amp; Suzuki, 2002). 12   3) Punishment of free‐riding: While in Hermann et. al.’s study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fcooperation and anti‐social punishment varied dramatically, the willingness of players to " id="224" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>) both initial  cooperation and anti‐social punishment varied dramatically, the willingness of players to  punish low contributors (free‐riders) was not different among populations, once age,  sex, and other socio‐demographic controls are included.   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="232">3.7. Summary of Contrast 2  While robust patterns have emerged among people from industrialized societies, Westerners  emerge as unusual—frequent global outliers—on several key dimensions. The experiments  reviewed are numerous, arise from different disciplines, use diverse methods, and are often  part of systematically comparable data sets created by unified projects. Many of these  differences are not merely differences in the magnitude of effects but often show qualitative  differences (reversals or novel phenomena, such as allocentric spatial reasoning and anti‐social  punishment). <marker type="block"/> 4. Contrast 3: Contemporary Americans vs. the Rest of the West  Above we compared WEIRD populations to non‐Western populations. However, given the  dominance of American research within psychology (May, 1997) and the cognitive sciences, it is  important to assess the similarity of American data with that from Westerners more generally.  Is it reasonable to generalize from Americans to the rest of the West? Americans are, of course,  people too, so they will share many psychological characteristics with other Homo sapiens. At  present, we could find no systematic research program to compare Americans to other  Westerners, so the evidence presented is assembled from many sources   <marker type="page" number="33"/><marker type="block"/> 4.1. Individualism and Related Psychological Phenomena  Americans stand out relative to Westerners on phenomena that are associated with  independent self‐concepts and individualism. A number of analyses, using a diverse range of  methods, reveal that Americans are, on average, the most individualistic people in the world  (e.g., Hofstede, 1980; Lipset, 1996; Morling &amp; Lamoreaux, 2008; Oyserman et al., 2002). The  observation that the U.S. is especially individualistic is not new, and dates at least as far back as  Toqueville (1835). The unusually individualistic nature of Americans may be caused by, or  reflect, an ideology that particularly stresses the importance of freedom and self‐sufficiency, as  well as various practices in education and child‐rearing that may help to inculcate this sense of  autonomy. American parents, for example, were the only ones in a survey of 100 societies who  created a separate room for their baby to sleep (Burton &amp; Whiting, 1961; also see Lewis, 1995),  reflecting that from the time they are born, Americans are raised in an environment that  emphasizes their independence (on unusual nature of American childrearing, see Lancy, 2009;  Rogoff, 2003) 13 . <marker type="block"/> The extreme individualism of Americans is evident on many demographic and political  measures.  In American Exceptionalism, sociologist Seymour Lipset (1996) documents a long list  of the ways that Americans are unique in the Western world. At the time of Lipset’s surveys,  compared with other Western industrialized societies, Americans were found to be the most  patriotic, litigious, philanthropic, and populist (they have the most positions for elections and  the most frequent elections, although they have among the lowest turnout rates). They were  also among the most optimistic, and the least class‐conscious. They were the most churchgoing  in Protestantism, and the most fundamentalist in Christendom, and were more likely than  others from Western industrialized countries to see the world in absolute moral terms. In  contrast to other large Western industrialized societies, the US had the highest crime rate, the  longest working hours, the highest divorce rate, the highest rate of volunteerism, the highest  percentage of citizens with a post‐secondary education, the highest productivity rate, the  highest GDP, the highest poverty rate, the highest income inequality rate, and were least  supportive of various governmental interventions. The U.S. is the only industrialized society  that never had a viable socialist movement, and was the last country to get a national pension  plan, unemployment insurance, accident insurance, and remains the only industrialized nation  that does not have a general allowance for families or a national health insurance plan. In sum,  there’s some reason to suspect that Americans might be different from other Westerners, as  Tocqueville noted. </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="228"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="229">30</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="230">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="233" confidence="possible">Given the centrality of self‐concept to so many psychological processes, it follows that the  unusual emphasis on American individualism and independence would be reflected in a wide  spectrum of self‐related phenomena. For example, self‐concepts are implicated when people  make choices (e.g., Vohs et al., 2008).  While Westerners tend to value choices more than non‐</region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="234"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="235">31</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="236">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="238">Westerners (e.g., Iyengar &amp; DeVoe, 2003), Americans value choices more still, and prefer more  opportunities, than do those from elsewhere (Savani et al., 2008). For example, in a survey of  people from six Western countries, only Americans preferred a choice from 50 different ice  cream flavors compared with 10 flavors. Likewise, Americans (and Britons) prefer to have more  choices on menus in upscale restaurants than do those from other European countries (Rozin,  Fischler, Shields, &amp; Masson, 2006). The array of choices available, and people’s motivation to  make such choices, is even more extreme in the U.S. compared to the rest of the West. <marker type="block"/> Likewise, because cultural differences in analytic and holistic reasoning styles appear to be  influenced by whether one views the social world as a collection of discrete individuals or as a  set of interconnected relationships (Nisbett, 2003), it follows that exceptionally individualistic  Americans should be exceptionally analytic as well. One recent study suggests that this might  indeed be the case: Americans showed significantly more focused attention in the Framed Line  Task than did people from other European countries (Britain and Germany) as well as Japanese  (Kitayama, Park, Sevincer, Karasawa, &amp; Uskul, 2009). Although more research is needed,  Americans may see the world in more analytic terms than the rest of the West.    </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="239" confidence="possible">Terror management theory maintains that because humans possess the conscious awareness  that they will someday die, they cope with the associated existential anxiety by making efforts  to align themselves with their cultural worldviews (Greenberg, Solomon, &amp; Pyszczynski, 1997).   The theory is explicit that the existential problem of death is a human universal, and indeed  posits that an awareness of death preceded the evolution of cultural meaning systems in  humans (Becker, 1973).  In support of this argument of universality, the tendency to defend  one’s cultural worldview following thoughts about death has been found in every one of the  more than a dozen diverse populations studied thus far.  However, there is also significant  cross‐population diversity in the magnitude of these effects.  A recent meta‐analysis of all  terror management studies reveals that the effect sizes for cultural worldview defense in the  face of thoughts of death are significantly more pronounced among American samples (r =  0.37) than among other Western (r = 0.30) or non‐Western samples (r = 0.26: Burke, Martens,  &amp; Faucher, n.d.). Curiously, Americans respond more defensively to death thoughts than do  those from other countries. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="242">In the previous section, we discussed Herrmann et. al.’s (2008) work showing substantial  qualitative differences in punishment between Western and non‐Western societies. While  Western countries all clump at one end of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="FWestern countries all clump at one end of Figure 4" id="240" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>, the Americans anchor the extreme end of  Western countries all clump at one end of <xref ref-type="fig" rid="Fthe West’s distribution. Perhaps it is this extreme tendency for Americans to punish free‐riders, " id="241" class="deo:Reference">Figure 4</xref>, the Americans anchor the extreme end of  the West’s distribution. Perhaps it is this extreme tendency for Americans to punish free‐riders,  while not punishing cooperators, that contributes to Americans having the world’s highest  worker productivity. American society is also anomalous, even relative to other Western  societies, in its low relational focus in work settings, which is reflected in practices such as the </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="243"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="244">32</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="245">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="246" confidence="possible">encouragement of an impersonal work style, direct (rather than indirect) communication, the  clear separation of the work domain from the non‐work, and discouragement of friendships at  work (Sanchez‐Burks, 2005). </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="252">4.2. Similarities between Americans and Westerners  We are unable to locate any research program (other than the ones reviewed in the first two  telescoping contrasts) that has demonstrated that American psychological and behavioral  patterns are similar to other Westerners. We reason that there should be many similarities  between the US and the rest of the West, and we assume that many researchers share our  impression. Perhaps this is why we are not able to find studies that have been conducted to  explicitly establish these similarities—many researchers likely would not see such studies as  worth the effort. In the absence of comparative evidence for a given phenomenon it might not  be unreasonable to assume that the Americans will look similar to the rest of the West.  However, the above findings provide a hint that, at least along some key dimensions, Americans  are extreme.   4.3. Summary of Contrast 3  There are few research programs that have explicitly sought to contrast Americans with other  Westerners on psychological or behavioral measures. However, those phenomena for which  sufficient data is available to make cross‐population comparisons reveal that American  participants are exceptional even within the unusual population of Westerners—outliers among  outliers. <marker type="block"/> 5. Contrast 4: Typical Contemporary American Subjects vs. Other  Americans  The previous contrasts have revealed that WEIRD populations frequently occupy the tail‐ends  of distributions of psychological and behavioral phenomena. However, it is important to  recognize, as a number of researchers have (e.g., Arnett, 2008; Medin &amp; Atran, 2004; Sears,  1986), that the majority of behavioral research on non‐clinical populations within North  America is conducted with undergraduates (Peterson, 2001; Wintre et al., 2001). Further,  within psychology, the individuals are usually psychology majors, or at least taking introductory  psychology courses. In the case of child participants, they are often the progeny of high  socioeconomic status (SES) people. Thus, there are numerous social, economic, and  demographic dimensions that tentatively suggest these subjects might be unusual. But, are  they?   <marker type="page" number="36"/><marker type="block"/> 5.1. Comparisons among Contemporary Adult Americans  Highly educated Americans differ from other Americans in many important respects. Below we  first highlight findings from social psychology and then behavioral economics. </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="249"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="250">33</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="251">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="253" confidence="possible">5.1.1. Findings from Social Psychology  For a number of the phenomena reviewed above in which Americans were identified as global  outliers, highly educated Americans occupy an even more extreme position than less educated  Americans.  Here we itemize 8 examples. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="254">1) Although college‐educated Americans have been found to rationalize their choices in dozens  of post‐choice dissonance studies, Snibbe and Markus (2005) found that non‐college educated  American adults do not (c.f.,  Sheth, 1970).   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="255" confidence="possible">2) Although Americans are the most individualistic people in the world, American  undergraduates score higher on some measures of individualism than do their non‐college  educated counterparts, particularly for those aspects associated with self‐actualization,  uniqueness, and locus of control (Kusserow, 1999; Snibbe &amp; Markus, 2005).    3) Conformity motivations were found to be weaker among college‐educated Americans than  non‐college‐educated Americans (Stephens, Markus, &amp; Townsend, 2007), who acted in ways  more similar to that observed in East Asian samples (cf., Kim &amp; Markus, 1999).    4) Non‐college educated adults are embedded in more tightly‐structured social networks than  are college students (Lamont, 2000), which raises the question of whether research on  relationship formation, dissolution, and interdependence conducted among students will  generalize to the population at large (cf., Adams, 2005; Falk, Heine, Yuki, &amp; Takemura, 2009).   5) A large study that sampled participants from the general population in Southeastern  Michigan found that working class people were more interdependent and more holistic than  middle class people (Grossmann, Na, Varunum, Kitayama, &amp; Nisbett, 2009)  6) The moral reasoning of college‐educated Americans occurs almost exclusively within the  ethic of autonomy, whereas non‐college educated Americans use the ethics of community and  divinity (Haidt et al., 1993; Jensen, 1997). Parallel differences exist in moral reasoning between  American liberals and conservatives  (Haidt &amp; Graham, 2007). </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="256">7) American college students respond more favourably toward other groups in society, are  more supportive of racial diversity, and are more motivated to mask or explain away negative  intergroup attitudes, than are American adults (Henry, 2009).  This difference is more  problematic because the percentage of psychological studies of prejudice which exclusively rely </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="257"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="258">34</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="259">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="260" confidence="possible">on student samples has increased over the last two decades (from 82.7% to 91.6%), and that  this bias is accentuated for the higher impact social psychology journals (Henry, 2009).  8) A meta‐analysis reveals that college‐students (the vast majority of whom were American)  respond with more cultural worldview defense to death thoughts (r = .36) than do non‐college  students (r = 0.25: Burke et al., n.d.).  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="261">More broadly, a second‐order meta‐analysis (N &gt; 650,000, Number of studies &gt; 7000) of studies  that either included college student samples or non‐student adult samples revealed that the  two groups differed either directionally or in magnitude for approximately half of the  phenomena studied (e.g., attitudes, gender perceptions, social desirability: Peterson, 2001).  However, no clear pattern regarding the factors that accounted for the differences emerged.  Other research has found that American undergraduates have higher degrees of self‐ monitoring (Reifman, Klein, &amp; Murphy, 1989), are more susceptible to attitude change (Krosnick  &amp; Alwin, 1989), and are more susceptible to social influence (Pasupathi, 1999) compared to  non‐student adults.   5.1.2. Findings from Behavioral Economics.  Consistent and non‐trivial differences between undergraduates and fully‐fledged adults are  emerging in behavioral economics as well. When compared to diverse and sometimes  representative adult samples, undergraduate subjects consistently set the lower bound for  prosociality in experimental measures of trust, fairness, cooperation and punishment of  unfairness or free‐riding. For example, in both the Ultimatum and Dictator Games non‐student  Americans (both rural and urban participants) make significantly higher offers than  undergraduate subjects (Henrich &amp; Henrich, 2007). The difference is most pronounced in  Dictator games in which samples of non‐student American adults from Missouri (urban and  rural Missouri did not differ) offered a of mean 47% of the total stake while undergraduate  freshman gave 32%, well within the typical range for undergraduates in this game (Camerer,  2003; Ensminger &amp; Cook, n.d.; Henrich &amp; Henrich, n.d.). These seemingly high offers among  non‐students in the Dictator Game are similar to those found in other non‐student samples in  the U.S. (Carpenter, Burks, &amp; Verhoogen, 2005; Henrich &amp; Henrich, 2007). It’s the student  results that are anomalous. Similarly, more recent research comparing students to both  representative or selectively diverse samples of adults using the Trust Game, Ultimatum Game,  and Public Goods Game show that undergraduates ride the lower bound on prosociality  measures (Bellemare et al., 2008; Bellemare &amp; Kroger, 2007; Carpenter, Connolly, &amp; Myers,  2008; Fehr &amp; List, 2004). In fact, “being an undergraduate” (or being young and educated) is  one of the few demographic variables that seem to matter in explaining within‐country  variability.   </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="262"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="263">35</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="264">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="265" confidence="possible">Behavioral economics research also indicates that developmental or acculturative changes to  some motivations and preferences are still occurring within the age range of undergraduates  (Henrich, 2008). For example, Ultimatum Game offers continue to change over the university  years, with freshman making lower offers than seniors (Carter &amp; Irons, 1991). Other work  shows that offers do not hit their adult plateau in behavioral games until around age 24  (Carpenter et al., 2005), after which time offers do not change with age until people reach old  age. In trust games, measures of trust and trustworthiness increase with age until they reach a  plateau, close to age 30 (Sutter &amp; Kocher, 2007).  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="267">Such research may explain why treatment effects also depend on the subject pool used, with  students being the most sensitive. For example, Dictator Game treatments involving double‐ blind setups such that the experimenter cannot know how much a subject contributes, have  dramatically smaller effects on offers among non‐student adults, and sometimes no effect at all  in adult populations outside the U.S. (Lesorogol &amp; Ensminger, n.d.). Similarly, unconscious  religious primes increased Dictator Game offers in a Canadian student sample of religious and  nonreligious participants alike, but when non‐student adults were sampled, no significant effect  emerged for the nonreligious adults (Shariff &amp; Norenzayan, 2007). <marker type="block"/> For several of these economics measures, such as public good contributions (Egas &amp; Riedl,  2008), undergraduate behavior is qualitatively similar to fully‐fledged adults, just less prosocial.  However, in at least one area (so far), it appears that a particularly interesting phenomenon is  qualitatively absent in undergraduates by comparison with fully‐fledged adults from the same  populations. As discussed above for small‐scale societies, researchers using the Ultimatum  Game have found systematic, non‐trivial tendencies in many populations to reject offers  greater than 50% of the stake, a phenomenon neither previously observed in students nor  intuited by researchers. Recent work using representative adult samples has revealed this  tendency for “hyper‐fair rejections” among non‐student adults in Western populations, though  it is substantially weaker than in many of the non‐Western populations discussed above  (Bellemare et al., 2008; Guth et al., 2003; Wallace et al., 2007).   5.2. Comparisons Among Subpopulations of American Children  Although studying young children is one important strategy for discerning universals, it does  not completely avoid these challenges since developmental studies are frequently biased  toward middle‐ and upper‐class American children. Recent evidence indicates that something  as seemingly basic as the differences in spatial reasoning between males and females (Hyde,  1981; Mann, Sasanuma, Sakuma, &amp; Masaki, 1990; Voyer, Voyer, &amp; Bryden, 1995) does not  generalize well to poor American children. On two different spatial tasks, repeated four times  over two years with 547 second and third graders, low SES children did not show the sex  differences observed in middle and high SES children from Chicago (Levine, Vasilyeva, Lourenco, </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="268"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="269">36</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="270">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="271" confidence="possible">Newcombe, &amp; Huttenlocher, 2005). Such findings, when combined with other research  indicating no sex differences on spatial tasks among migratory foragers (Berry, 1966), suggest  that a proper theory of the origins of sex differences in spatial abilities needs to explain why  both poor Chicago children and foragers do not show any sex differences. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="273">Research on IQ using analytical tools from behavioral genetics has long shown that IQ is highly  heritable, and not strongly influenced by shared family environment (Bouchard, 2004).  However, research using 7‐year old twins drawn from a wide range of socioeconomic statuses,  shows that contributions of genetic variation and shared environment varies dramatically from  low to high SES children (Turkheimer, Haley, Waldron, D'Onofrio, &amp; Gottesman, 2003). For high  SES children, where environmental variability is negligible, genetic differences account for 70‐ 80% of the variation, with shared environment contributing less than 10%. For low SES children,  where there is far more variability in environmental contributions to intelligence, genetic  differences account for 0‐10% of the variance, with shared environment contributing about  60%. This raises the specter that much of what we think we have learned from behavioral  genetics may be misleading, as the data are disproportionately influenced by WEIRD people,  and their children (Nisbett, 2009). <marker type="block"/> A similar problem of generalizing from narrow samples exists for genetics research more  broadly. Genetic findings obtained with one sample frequently do not replicate in a second  sample, to the point that Nature Genetics now requires all empirical papers to include data  from two independent samples. There are at least two ways in which geographically‐limited  samples may give rise to spurious genotype‐phenotype associations. First, the proportions of  various polymorphisms vary across different regions of the world due to different migratory  patterns and histories of selection (e.g., Cavalli‐Sforza, Menozzi, &amp; Piazza, 1994). A genetic  association identified in a sample obtained from one region may not replicate in a sample from  another region because it involves interactions with other genetic variants that are not equally  distributed across regions. Second, the same gene may be expressed differently across  populations. For example, Kim et al., (in press) found that a particular serotonin receptor  polymorphism (5‐HTR1A) was associated with increased attention to focal objects among  Americans, but that the same allele was associated with decreased attention to focal objects  among Koreans. Researchers would draw different conclusions regarding the function of this  polymorphism depending upon the location of their sample. A more complete investigation of  heritability and genetic associations demands a comparison of measures across diverse  environments and populations.   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="274" confidence="possible">5.3. Contemporary Americans compared with Previous Generations   Contemporary Americans may also be psychologically unusual compared to their forebears 50  or 100 years ago. Some documented changes among Americans over the past few decades </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="275"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="276">37</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="277">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="279">include increasing individualism, as indicated by increasingly solitary lifestyles dominated by  individual‐centered activities and a decrease in group‐participation (Putnam, 2000), increasingly  positive self‐esteem (Twenge &amp; Campbell, 2001), and a lower need for social approval (Twenge  &amp; Im, 2007). These findings suggest that the unusual nature of Americans in these domains, as  we reviewed earlier, may be a relatively recent phenomenon. For example, Rozin (2003) found  that attitudes towards tradition are more similar between Indian college students and  American grandparents than they are between Indian and American college students. Although  more research is needed to reach firm conclusions, these initial findings raise doubts as to  whether research on contemporary American students (and WEIRD people more generally) is  even extendable to American students of previous decades. <marker type="block"/> The evidence of temporal change is probably best for IQ   . Research by Flynn (1987; 2007) shows  that IQ scores increased over the last half century by an average of 18 points across all  industrialized nations for which there were adequate data. Moreover, this rise was driven  primarily by increasing scores on the analytic subtests. This is a striking finding considering  recent work showing how unusual Westerners are in their analytic reasoning styles. Given such  findings, it seems plausible that Americans of only 50 or 100 years ago were reasoning in ways  much more similar to the rest of the non‐Western world than Americans of today.  5.4. Similarities between typical experimental subjects and other  Americans     We expect that typical American subjects are very similar to other Americans in myriad ways.  The problem with this expectation, however, is that it is not immediately apparent in which  domains they should be similar. We think that there are enough differences between these two  groups to raise concerns about speaking incautiously on the thoughts and behaviors of  Americans, in general. There have been rather few studies that have explicitly contrasted  whether undergraduates or college‐educated Americans differ in various psychological  measures from those who are not currently students, or who were never college‐educated.   There are numerous meta‐analyses that include data from both college student and non‐ student samples that speak partially to this issue. Although the meta‐analyses do not specify  the national origin of the participants, we assume that most of the subjects were American.  Some of these analyses indicate considerable similarity between student and non‐student  samples. For example, the aforementioned second‐order meta‐analysis (Peterson, 2001)  revealed similarities between students and non‐student samples for about half of the  phenomena. Similarly, the relation between attribution styles and depression (Sweeney,  Anderson, &amp; Bailey, 1986), and the relations among intentions, attitudes, and norms (Farley,  Lehmann, &amp; Ryan, 1981) do not show any appreciable differences between student and non‐ student samples. In these instances, there do not appear to be any problems generalizing from </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="280"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="281">38</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="282">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="283" confidence="possible">student to non‐student samples, which may suggest that college‐education, and SES more  generally, are not related to these phenomena. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="285">5.5. Summary of Contrast 4    Numerous findings from multiple disciplines indicate that, in addition to many similarities, there  are differences among typical subjects and the rest of the American population in unexpected  domains. In some of these domains (e.g., individualism, moral reasoning, worldview defense in  response to death thoughts, and perceptions of choice) the data from American  undergraduates represent even more dramatic departures from the patterns identified in non‐ Western samples. Further, contemporary American college students appear further removed  along some of these dimensions than did their predecessors a few decades earlier. Typical  subjects may be outliers within an outlier population. <marker type="block"/> 6. General Discussion  As the four contrasts summarized above reveal, WEIRD subjects are unusual in the context of  the world in some key ways. In this section we first discuss the main conclusions and  implications of our empirical review.  We then address two common challenges to our claim  that WEIRD subjects are frequent outliers. Finally, we offer some recommendations for how the  behavioral sciences may address these challenges.   6.1. Summary of Conclusions and Implications  6.1.1. Pronounced Population Variation is Commonplace in the Behavioral  Sciences.   There are now enough sources of experimental evidence, using widely differing methods from  diverse disciplines, to indicate that there is substantial psychological and behavioral variation  among human populations. As we have seen, some of this variability involves differences in the  magnitude of effects, motivations, or biases. There is also considerable variability in both  whether certain effects or biases exist in some populations (as with anti‐social punishment and  the Mueller‐Lyer illusion), and in which direction they go (as with preferences for analytic vs.  holistic reasoning). The causal origins of such population‐level variation may be manifold,  including behavioral plasticity in response to different environments, epigenetic effects,  divergent trajectories of cultural evolution, and even the differential distribution of genes  across groups in response to divergent evolutionary histories. With all these causal possibilities  on the table, we think the existence of this population‐level variation alone should suffice to  energize course corrections in our research directions. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="286" confidence="possible">We have also identified many domains in which there are striking similarities across  populations. These similarities could indicate reliably developing adaptations (theory of mind), </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="287"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="288">39</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="289">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="290">byproducts of innate adaptations (such as some aspects of religious cognition), or independent  inventions or diffusions of learned responses that have universal utility (such as counting  systems, dance, cooking practices, or techniques for making fire). We have no doubt that there  are many more pan‐human similarities than we have mentioned (e.g., movement perception,  taste for sugar, chunking, habituation, or depth computation); however, thus far there are few  databases with individual‐level measures sufficient to evaluate the similarities or differences  across populations.   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="291" confidence="possible">Many of the processes identified above that vary dramatically across populations would seem  to be “basic” psychological processes. The reviewed findings identified variation in aspects of  visual perception, memory, attention, fairness motivations, categorization, induction, spatial  cognition, self‐enhancement, moral reasoning, defensive responses to thoughts about death,  and heritability estimates of IQ.  These domains are not unique to the social world—they span  social as well as non‐social aspects of the environment, and do not appear to be any less  “fundamental” than those domains for which much similarity has been identified. At this point  we know of no strong grounds to make a priori claims to the “fundamentalness” or the likely  universality of a given psychological process.   </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="292">The application of evolutionary theory does not provide grounds for such a priori claims of  “fundamental” or “basic” processes, at least in general. Evolutionary theory is a powerful tool  for generating and eliminating hypotheses. However, despite its power (or perhaps because of  it), it is often overly fecund, as it generates multiple competing hypotheses, with predictions  sometimes dependent on unknown or at least debatable aspects of ancestral environments.  Thus, adjudicating among alternative evolutionary hypotheses often requires comparative  work. Moreover, theoretical work is increasingly recognizing that natural selection has favored  ontogenetic adaptations that allow humans, and other species, to adapt non‐genetically to local  environments (Henrich, 2008).  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="293" confidence="possible">Although we do not yet know of a principled way to predict whether a given psychological  process or behavioral pattern will be similar across populations in the absence of comparative  empirical research, it would surely be of much value to the field if there were a set of criteria  that could be used to anticipate universality (Norenzayan, 2006; Norenzayan &amp; Heine, 2005).  Here we discuss some possible criteria that might be considered. First, perhaps there are some  domains in which researchers could expect phenomena to be more universal than they are in  other domains. We believe that the degree of universality does likely vary across domains,  although this has yet to be demonstrated. Many researchers (including us) have the intuition  that there are cognitive domains related to attention, memory, and perception in which inter‐ population variability is likely to be low. Our review of the data, however, does not bolster this  intuition. Second, it might be reasonable to assume that some phenomena are more </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="294"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="295">40</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="296">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="303">fundamental to the extent that they are measured at a physiological or genetic level, such as  genotype‐phenotype relations or neural activity. However, recall that the same genes can be  expressed differently across populations (e.g., Kim et al., in press), and the same cognitive task  may be associated with activity in different neural activations across populations (e.g., Hedden  et al., 2008).  Third, there may be criteria by which one could confidently make generalizations  from one well‐studied universal phenomenon to another similar phenomenon; for example,  because a pride display is highly similar across populations (e.g., Tracy &amp; Matsumoto 2008), it  might follow that the conceptually‐related shame display should also be similar across  populations as well (Fessler, 1999). Fourth, it would seem that demonstrating a process or  effect in other species, such as rats or pigeons, would indicate human universality (and more).  Although this may generally be true, several researchers have argued that culture‐gene  coevolution has dramatically shaped human evolution in a manner uncharacteristic of other  species (Richerson &amp; Boyd, 2005). Part of this process may involve the off‐loading of previously  genetically encoded preferences and abilities into culture (e.g., tastes for spices). Fifth,  phenomena which are evident among infants might be reasonably assumed to be more  universal than phenomena identified in older children or adults. We suspect this is the case, but  it is possible that early biases can be reversed by later ontogeny. Showing parallel findings or  effects in both adults and infants from the same population is powerful, and raises the  likelihood of universality, but quite different environments might still shape adult psychologies  away from infant patterns (consider the spatial cognition finding with apes, children and  adults). Finally, perhaps particular brain regions are less responsive to experience, such that if a  given phenomenon was localized to those regions one could anticipate more universality. <marker type="block"/> Whatever the relevant principles, it is an important goal to develop theories that predict which  elements of our psychological processes are reliably developing across normal human  environments and which are locally variable (focusing on the how and why of that variability)  (Barrett, 2006).  We note that behavioral scientists have typically been overly confident  regarding the universality of what they study, and as this review reveals, our intuitions for what  is universal do not have a particularly good track record—we also think this paper explains why  those intuitions are so poor: most scientists are WEIRD. Hence, any set of criteria by which  universality can be successfully predicted must be grounded in substantial empirical data. We  look forward to seeing data that can help to identify criteria to anticipate universality in future  research.  6.1.2. WEIRD subjects may often be the worst population from which to make  generalizations.  The empirical foundation of the behavioral sciences comes principally from experiments with  American undergraduates. The patterns we have identified in the available (albeit limited) data  indicate that this sub‐subpopulation is highly unusual along many important psychological and <marker type="page" number="44"/><marker type="block"/> behavioral dimensions. It is not merely that researchers frequently make generalizations from a  narrow subpopulation. The concern is that this particular subpopulation is highly  unrepresentative of the species. The fact that WEIRD people are the outliers in so many key  domains of the behavioral sciences may render them one of the worst subpopulations one  could study for generalizing about Homo sapiens.  <marker type="block"/> To many anthropologically‐savvy researchers it is not surprising that Americans, and people  from modern industrialized societies more generally, appear unusual vis‐à‐vis the rest of the  species. For the vast majority of its evolutionary history, humans have lived in small‐scale  societies without formal schools, governments, hospitals, police, complex divisions of labor,  markets, militaries, formal laws, or mechanized transportation. Every household provisioned  much or all of its own food, made its own clothes, tools, and shelters, and—aside from sexual  divisions of labor—most everyone had to master the same skills and domains of knowledge.  Children typically did not grow up in small, monogamous nuclear families with few kin around,  nor were they away from their families at school for much of the day. Rather, children have  typically grown up in mixed age play‐groups, where they received little active instruction or  exposure to books or TV (Fiske, 1998; Lancy, 1996; 2009); they learned largely by observation  and imitation, received more directives, more physical punishment, less praise, and were less  likely to be engaged in conversation by adults (and there’s no “why” phase). By age 10, children  in some foraging societies obtain sufficient calories to feed themselves, and routinely kill and  butcher animals. Adolescent females in particular take on most of the work‐related  responsibilities of adult women. People in small scale societies tend to have less reliable  nutrition, greater exposure to hunger, pain, chronic diseases and lethal dangers, and more  frequently experience the death of family members. WEIRD people, from this perspective, grow  up in, and adapt to, a rather atypical environment vis‐à‐vis those of most of human history. It  should not be surprising that their psychological world is unusual as well.   </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="299"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="300">41</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="301">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="304" confidence="possible">6.1.3. Research Topics have been Limited by the Heavy Reliance on WEIRD  Populations.  Relying on WEIRD populations may cause researchers to miss important dimensions of  variation, and devote undue attention to behavioral tendencies that are unusual in a global  context. There are good arguments for choosing topics that are of primary interest to the  readers of the literature (i.e., largely WEIRD people); however, if the goal of the research  program is to shed light on the human condition, then this narrow unrepresentative sample  may lead to an uneven and incomplete understanding. We suspect that some topics such as  self‐enhancement, cognitive dissonance, fairness, and analytic reasoning might not have been  sufficiently interesting to justify in‐depth investigation for most humans at most times  throughout history. Alternatively, the behavioral sciences have shown a rather limited interest  in such topics as kinship, food, ethnicity (not race), religion, sacred values, polygamy, animal </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="305"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="306">42</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="307">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="309">behavior, and rituals (see Rozin, 2001 for further critiques on this point; Rozin et al., 2006). Had  the behavioral sciences developed elsewhere, important theoretical foci and central lines of  research might likely look very different (Medin &amp; Bang, 2008). Moreover, it may be  unnecessarily difficult to study psychological phenomena in populations where they are  unusually weak, as is the case for conformity or shame among Americans (see Fessler, 2004).  6.1.4. Studying Children and Primates is Crucial, But not a Replacement for  Comparative Work  Working with children and non‐human primates is essential for understanding human  psychology. However, it is important to note that despite its great utility and intuitive appeal,  such research does not fully obviate these challenges. In the case of primate research,  discovering parallel results in great apes and in one human population is an important step, but  it doesn’t tell us how reliably developing a particular aspect of psychology is. As the spatial  cognition work indicates, since language and cultural practices can—but need not—influence  the cognition humans acquired from their phylogenetic history as apes, establishing the same  patterns of cognition in apes and Westerners is insufficient to make any strong claims about  universality. Suppose most psychologists were Hai\\om speakers (instead of Indo‐European  speakers), they might have studied only Hai\\om‐speaking children and adults, as well as non‐ human apes, and concluded (incorrectly) that allocentric spatial reasoning was universal.  Similarly, imagine if Tsimane economists compared Ultimatum Game results for Tsimane adults  to chimpanzees (Gurven, 2004; Henrich &amp; Smith, 2001; Jensen, Call, &amp; Tomasello, 2007). These  researchers would have found the same results for both species, and concluded that standard  game theoretic models (assuming pure self‐interest) and evolutionary analyses (Nowak et al.,  2000) were a fairly accurate predictors in Ultimatum Game behavior for both chimpanzees and  humans—a very tidy finding. In both of these cases, the conclusions would be opposite to those  drawn from studies with WEIRD populations. 14 <marker type="block"/> Studying children is crucial for developing universal theories. However, evidence suggests that  psychological differences among populations can emerge relatively early in children (as with  folkbiological reasoning), and sometimes differences are even larger in children than in adults,  as with the Mueller‐Lyer Illusion. Moreover, developmental patterns may be different in  different populations, as with sex differences in spatial cognition between low income vs.  middle and high income subpopulations in the U.S., or with performance in the false belief task.  This suggests a need for converging lines of research. The most compelling conclusions  regarding universality would derive from comparative work among diverse human populations  with both adults and with children, including infants if possible. Human work can then be  properly compared with work among non‐human species (including but not limited to  primates), based on a combination of field and laboratory work.   </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="310"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="311">43</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="312">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="313" confidence="possible">6.1.5. Understanding Human Diversity is Crucial for Constructing Evolutionary  Theories of Human Behavior.   Evolution has equipped humans with ontogenetic programs, including cultural learning, that  help us adapt our bodies and brains to the local physical and social environment. Over human  history, convergent forms of cultural evolution have effectively altered (1) our physical  environments with tools, technology, and knowledge, (2) our cognitive environments with  counting systems, color terms, written symbols, novel grammatical structures, categories, and  heuristics; and (3) our social environments with norms, institutions, laws, and punishments.  Broad patterns of psychology may be—in part—a product of our genetic program’s common  response to culturally‐constructed environments that have emerged and converged over  thousands of years. This means the odd results from small‐scale societies, instead of being  dismissed as unusual exceptions, ought to be considered as crucial data points that help us  understand the ontogenetic processes that build our psychologies in locally adaptive and  context‐specific ways.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="314">Based on this and the previous point, it seems clear that comparative developmental studies  involving diverse human societies combined with parallel studies of non‐human primates (and  other relevant species) provide an approach to understanding human psychology and behavior  that can allow us to go well beyond merely establishing universality or variability. Such a  systematic multi‐pronged approach can allow us to test a richer array of hypotheses about the  processes by which both the reliable universal patterns and the diversity of psychological and  behavioral variation emerge.  6.1.6. Exclusive Use of WEIRD Samples is Justified When Seeking Existential  Proofs 15    Our argument should not be construed to suggest that the exclusive use of WEIRD samples  should always be avoided. There are cases where the exclusive use of these samples would be  legitimate to the extent that generalizability is not a relevant goal of the research, at least  initially (Mook, 1983). Research programs that are seeking existential proofs for psychological  or behavioral phenomena, such as in the case of altruistic punishment discussed earlier (e.g.,  Fehr &amp; Gächter, 2002), could certainly start with WEIRD samples. That is, if the question is  whether a certain phenomenon can be found in humans at all, reliance on any slice of humanity  would be a legitimate sampling strategy. For another example, Tversky, Kahneman and their  colleagues sought to demonstrate the existence of systematic biases in decision‐making that  violate the basic principles of rationality (Gilovich, Griffin , &amp; Kahneman, 2002). Most of their  work was done with WEIRD samples. Counterexamples to standard rationality predictions could  come from any sample in the world. 16  Furthermore, existential proof for a psychological  phenomenon in WEIRD samples can be especially compelling when such a finding is </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="315"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="316">44</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="317">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="318" confidence="possible">theoretically unexpected. Thus Rozin and Nemeroff (1990) found surprisingly (to many) that  even elite U.S. university students show some magical thinking. Nevertheless, even in such  cases, learning about the extent to which population variability affects such phenomena is a  necessary subsequent phase of the enterprise, since any theory of human behavior ultimately  has to account for such variability (if it exists).  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="326">6.2. Concerns with our argument  We have encountered two quite different sets of concerns about our argument. Those with the  first set of concerns, elaborated below, worry that our findings are exaggerated because (a) we  may have cherry‐picked only the most extreme cases that fit our argument, and have thus  exaggerated the degree to which WEIRD people are outliers, and/or (b) the observed variation  across populations may be due to various methodological artifacts that arise from translating  experiments across contexts. The second concern is quite the opposite: some researchers  dismissively claim that we are making an obvious point, which everyone already recognizes.  Perhaps the most productive thing we offer is for these two groups of readers to confront each  other. <marker type="block"/> We preface our response to the first concern with an admonition: of course, many patterns and  processes of human behavior and psychology will be generally shared across the species. We  recognize that human thought and behavior is importantly tethered to our common biology  and our common experiences.  Given this, the real challenge is to design a research program  that can explain the manifest patterns of similarity and variation by clarifying the underlying  evolutionary and development processes.  <marker type="block"/> We offer three general responses to the concern that our review presents a biased picture. To  begin, we constructed our empirical review by targeting studies involving important  psychological or behavioral concepts which were, or still are, considered to be universal, and  that have been tested across diverse populations. We also listed and discussed major  comparative studies that have identified important cross‐population similarities. Since we have  surely overlooked relevant material, we invite commentators to add to our efforts in identifying  phenomena which have been widely tested across diverse subpopulations.  <marker type="block"/> Second, we acknowledge that since proper comparative data is lacking for most studied  phenomena, we cannot accurately evaluate the full extent of how unusual WEIRD people are.  This is, however, precisely the point. We hope research teams will be inspired to span the globe  and prove our claims of non‐representativeness wrong. The problem is that we simply do not  know how well many key phenomena generalize beyond the extant database of WEIRD people.  The evidence we present aims only to challenge (provoke?) those who assume undergraduates  are sufficient to make claims about human psychology and behavior.  <marker type="page" number="48"/><marker type="block"/> Third, to address the concern that the observed population‐level differences originate from the  methodological challenges of working across diverse contexts, we emphasize that the above  evidence derives from diverse disciplines, theoretical approaches, and methodological  techniques. They include experiments involving (1) incentivized economic decisions; (2)  perceptual judgments; (3) deceptive experimental practices that prevented subjects from  knowing what was being measured; and (4) children, who are less likely than adults to have  motivations to shape their responses in ways that they perceive as desirable (or undesirable) to  the experimenter. These findings, often published in the best journals of their respective fields,  hinged on the researchers making a compelling case that their methodology was comparably  meaningful across the populations being studied.  </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="323"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="324">45</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="325">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="327" confidence="possible">Furthermore, the same methods that have yielded population differences in one domain have  demonstrated similarities in other domains (Atran, 2005; Haun, Rapold et al., 2006; Henrich et  al., 2006; Herrmann et al., 2008; Medin &amp; Atran, 2004; Segall et al., 1966). If one wants to  highlight the demonstrated similarities, one cannot then ignore the demonstrated differences  which relied on the same or similar methodologies.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="328">Note also that few of the findings that we reviewed involve comparing means across subjective  self‐report measures, for which there are well‐known challenges in making cross‐population  comparisons (Chen, Lee, &amp; Stevenson, 1995; Hamamura, Heine, &amp; Paulhus, 2008; Heine,  Lehman, Peng, &amp; Greenholtz, 2002; Norenzayan, Smith et al., 2002; Peng, Nisbett, &amp; Wong,  1997). Thus, while methodological challenges may certainly be an issue in some cases, we think  it strains credulity to suggest that such issues invalidate the thrust of our argument, and thus  eliminate concerns about the non‐representativeness of typical subjects.     6.3. Recommendations  Our experience is that most researchers who work exclusively with WEIRD subjects would like  to establish the broad generalizability of their findings. Even if they strongly suspect that their  findings will generalize across the species, most agree that it would be better to have  comparative data across diverse populations. The problem, then, is not exclusively a scientific  or epistemological disagreement, but one of institutionalized incentives. Hence, addressing this  issue will require adjusting the existing incentive structures for researchers. The central focus of  these adjustments should be that in presenting our research designs to granting agencies, or  our empirical findings in journals, we must explicitly address questions of generalizability and  representativeness. With this in mind, we offer the following recommendations. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="329" confidence="possible">Journal editors and reviewers should press authors to both explicitly discuss and defend the  generalizability of their findings. Claims and confidence regarding generalizability must scale  with the strength of the empirical defense. If a result is novel, being explicitly uncertain about </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="330"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="331">46</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="332">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="333" confidence="possible">generalizability should be fine, but one should not imply universality without an empirically‐ grounded argument.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="334">This does not imply that all experimentalists need to shift to performing comparative work  across diverse subject pools! As comparative evidence accumulates in different domains,  researchers will be able to assess the growing body of comparative research and thus be able to  calibrate their confidence in the generalizability of their findings. The widespread practice of  subtly implying universality by using statements like “people’s reasoning is biased...” should be  avoided. “Which people?” should be a primary question asked by reviewers. We think this  practice alone will energize more comparative work (Rozin, 2009).  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="335" confidence="possible">The experience of evolutionary‐oriented researchers attests to the power of such incentives.  More than other researchers in the social sciences, evolutionary researchers have led the way  in performing systematic comparative work, drawing data from diverse societies. This is not  because they are interested in variation per se (though some are), but because they are  compelled, through some combination of their scientific drive and the enthusiasm of their  critics, to test their hypotheses in diverse populations (e.g., Billing &amp; Sherman, 1998; Buss,  1989; Daly &amp; Wilson, 1988; Fessler et al., 2005; Gangestad et al., 2006; Henrich et al., 2005;  Kenrick &amp; Keefe, 1992a, 1992b; Low, 2000; Medin &amp; Atran, 2004; Schaller &amp; Murray, 2008;  Schmitt, 2005; Sugiyama et al., 2002; Tracy &amp; Robins, 2008).    </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="337">Meta‐analyses are often compromised because many studies provide little background  information about the subjects. Journal editors should require explicit and detailed information  on subject pool composition (see Rozin, 2001). Some granting agencies already require this.  Comparative efforts would also be greatly facilitated if researchers would make their data  readily available to any who asked, or, better yet, data files should be made available online.  Sadly, a recent investigation found that only 27% of authors in psychology journals shared their  data when an explicit request was made to them in accordance with APA guidelines (Wicherts,  Borsboom, Kats, &amp; Molenaar, 2006). Tests of generalizability require broad access to published  data. <marker type="block"/> Given the general state of ignorance with regard to the generalizability of so many findings, we  think granting agencies, reviewers, and editors would be wise to give researchers credit for  tapping and comparing diverse subject pools. Work with undergraduates and the children who  live around universities is much easier than going out into the world to find subjects. As things  stand, researchers suffer a competitive disadvantage when seeking a more diverse sampling of  subjects. Because many of the best journals routinely require that papers include several  studies to address concerns about internal validity (Carver, 2004), the current incentives greatly  favor targeting the easiest subject pool to access. There is an often unrecognized tradeoff  between the experimental rigor of using multiple studies and the concomitant lack of </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="338"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="339">47</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="340">Weird People</outsider>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="341" confidence="possible">generalizability that easy‐to‐run subject pool entail (Rozin, 2009). If the incentive structure  came to favor non‐student subject pools, we anticipate that researchers could also be more  persuasive in encouraging their universities and departments to invest in building non‐student  subject pools, for example by setting up permanent psychological and behavioral testing  facilities in bus terminals, Fijian villages, rail stations, airports, and anywhere diverse subjects  might find themselves with extra time.  </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="342">Beyond this, departments and universities should build research links to diverse subject pools.  There are literally untapped billions of people around the world who would be willing to  participate in research projects, as both paid subjects and research assistants. The amounts of  money necessary to pay people who might normally make less than $12 per day are trivial vis‐ à‐vis the average research grant. Development economists, anthropologists and public health  researchers already do extensive research among diverse populations, and thus already possess  the contacts and collaborations. Experimentalists merely need to work on building the  networks.    </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="343" confidence="possible">Funding agencies, departments, and universities can encourage and facilitate both professors  and graduate students to work on expanding sample diversity. Research partnerships with non‐ WEIRD institutions can be established to further the goal of expanding and diversifying the  empirical base of the behavioral sciences. By supplying research leaves, adjusted expectations  of student progress, special funding sources, and institutionalized relationships to populations  outside the university as well as to non‐WEIRD universities, these organizations can make an  important contribution to building a more complete understanding of human nature. </region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="344">6.4. Closing Words  While we are certainly not the first to worry about the representativeness of undergraduates  (Gergen, 1973; Medin &amp; Atran, 2004; Norenzayan &amp; Heine, 2005; Rozin, 2001, 2009; Sears,  1986; Sue, 1999) our efforts to compile an empirical case has revealed an even more alarming  situation than previously recognized. The sample of contemporary Western undergraduates  that so overwhelms our database is not just an extraordinarily restricted sample of humanity; it  is frequently a distinct outlier vis‐à‐vis other global samples. It may represent the worst  population on which to base our understanding of Homo sapiens. Behavioral scientists now face  a choice – they can either acknowledge that their findings in many domains cannot be  generalized beyond this unusual subpopulation (and leave it at that), or they can begin to take  the difficult steps to building a broader, richer and better‐grounded understanding of our  species. </region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="345"> </outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="346">48</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="347">Weird People</outsider>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="348" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">7.  References </h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="349" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Adams, G. (2005). The cultural grounding of personal relationships: Enemyship on West African  worlds. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 88, 948‐968. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="350" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Al‐Shehab, A. J. (2002). A cross‐sectional examination of levels of moral reasoning in a sample  of Kuwait University faculty memebers. Social Behavious and Personality, 30, 813‐820. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="351" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Allik, J., &amp; Mccrae, R. R. (2004). Toward a geography of personality traits: patterns of profiles  across 36 cultures. Journal of Cross‐Cultural Psychology, 35, 13‐28. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="352" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Anderson, S. L., Adams, G., &amp; Plaut, V. C. (2008). The cultural grounding of personal  relationship: The importance of attractiveness in everyday life. Journal of Personality  and Social Psychology, 95, 352‐368. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="353" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Arnett, J. (2008). The neglected 95%: Why American psychology needs to become less  American. American Psychologist, 63, 602‐614. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="354" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Asch, S. E. (1951). Effects of group pressure upon the modification and distortion of judgments.  In H. Guetzkow (Ed.), Groups, Leadership and Men (pp. 177‐190). Pittsburgh: Carnegie. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="355" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Asch, S. E. (1952). Effects of group pressure on the modification and distortion of judgments. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="356" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Astuti, R. (2001). Are we all natural dualists? A cognitive developmental approach. Journal of  the Royal Anthropological Institute, 7(3), 429‐447. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="357" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Astuti, R., Solomon, G. E. A., &amp; Carey, S. (2004). Constraints on conceptual development.  Monographs of the Society for Research in Child Development, 69(3), vii‐135. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="358" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Atran, S. (1993). Ethnobiological Classification ‐ Principles of Categorization of Plants and  Animals in Traditional Societies ‐ Berlin,B. Current Anthropology, 34(2), 195‐198. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="359" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Atran, S. (2005). Adaptationism for human cognition: Strong, spurious or weak ? Mind &amp;  Language, 20(1), 39‐67. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="360" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Atran, S., Medin, D. L., Lynch, E., Vapnarsky, V., Ucan, E. E., &amp; Sousa, P. (2001). Folkbiology  doesn't come from folkpsychology: Evidence from Yukatek Maya in Cross‐Cultural  Perspective. Journal of Cognition and Culture, 1(1), 3‐42. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="361" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Atran, S., Medin, D. L., &amp; Ross, N. (2005). The cultural mind: environmental decision making and  cultural modeling within and across populations. Psychological Review, 112, 744‐776. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="362" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Baek, H. (2002). A comparative study og moral development of Korean and British children.  Journal of Moral Education, 31, 373‐391. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="363" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Bahry, D. L., &amp; Wilson, R. K. (2006). Confusion or Fairness in the Field? Rejection in the  Ultimatum Game under the Strategy Method. Journal of Economic Behavior &amp;  Organization, 60(1), 37‐54. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="364" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Bandura, A. (1982). Self‐efficacy mechanism in human agency. American Psychologist, 37, 122‐ 147. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="365" confidence="possible" page="51" column="1">Bang, M., Medin, D. L., &amp; Atran, S. (2007). Cultural Mosaics and Mental Models of Nature.  Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 104, 13868‐13874. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="369" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Barrett, H. C. (Ed.). (2006). Modularity and design reincarnation. New York: Oxford University  Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="370" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Barrett, H. C., &amp; Behne, T. (2005). Children's understanding of death as the cessation of agency:  a test using sleep versus death. Cognition, 96(2), 93‐108. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="371" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Becker, E. (1973). The denial of death. New York: Free Press. </ref>
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="372" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Beja‐Pereira, A., Luikart, G., England, P. R., Bradley, D. G., Jann, O. C., Berotorelle, G.,  Chamberlain, A. T., P., N. T., Metodiev, S., Ferrand, N., &amp; Erhardt, G. (2003). Gene‐ culture coevolution between cattle milk protein genes and human lactase genes. Nature  Genetics 35, 311‐313. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="373" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Bellemare, C., Kroeger, S., &amp; Van Soest, A. (2008). Measuring inequity aversion in a  heterogeneous population using experimental decisions and subjective probabilities.  Econometrica, 76(4), 815‐839. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="374" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Bellemare, C., &amp; Kroger, S. (2007). On representative social capital. European Economic Review,  51, 183‐202. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="375" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Benet‐Martinez, V., &amp; Waller, N. G. (1995). The Big Seven factor model of personality  description: Evidence for its cross‐cultural generality in a Spanish sample. Journal of  Personality and Social Psychology, 69, 701‐718. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="376" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Berlin, B. (1992). Ethnobiological classification : principles of categorization of plants and  animals in traditional societies. Princeton, N.J.: Princeton University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="377" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Berry, J. W. (1966). Emne and Eskimo perceptual skills. International Journal of Psychology, 1,  207‐229. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="378" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Billing, J., &amp; Sherman, P. W. (1998). Antimicrobial functions of spices: Why some like it hot.  Quarterly Review of Biology, 73(1), 3‐49. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="379" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Boesch, C. (2007). What Makes US Human (Homo sapiens)? The Challenge of Cognitive Cross‐ Species Comparision Journal of Comparative Psychology, 121(3), 227‐240. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="380" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Bond, R., &amp; Smith, P. B. (1996). Culture and conformity: a meta‐analysis of studies using asch's  (1952b, 1956) line judgment task. Psychological Bulletin, 119(1), 111‐137. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="381" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Bouchard, T. J. (2004). Genetic influence on human psychological traits ‐ A survey. Current  Directions in Psychological Science, 13(4), 148‐151. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="382" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Boyd, R., &amp; Richerson, P. J. (1985). Culture and the Evolutionary Process. Chicago, IL: University  of Chicago Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="383" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Brown, D. E. (1991). Human Universals. New York: McGraw Hill. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="384" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Brown, R. (1986). Social psychology: The second edition. New York: The Free Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="385" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Buchtel, E., &amp; Norenzayan, A. (2008). Which should you use, intuition of logic? Cultural  differences in injunctive norms about reasoning. Asian Journal of Social Psychology. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="386" confidence="possible" page="52" column="1">Burke, B., Martens, A., &amp; Faucher, E. (n.d.). Two decades of terror management theory: A meta‐ analysis of mortality salience research.Unpublished manuscript. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="390" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Burton, R., &amp; Whiting, J. (1961). The absent father and cross‐sex identity. Merrill‐Palmer  Quarterly, 7(85‐95), 85. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="391" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Buss, D. M. (1989). Sex‐Differences in Human Mate Preferences ‐ Evolutionary Hypothesis  Tested in 37 Cultures. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 12(1), 1‐14. </ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="392" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Callaghan, T., Rochat, P., Lillard, A., Claux, M. L., Odden, H., Itakura, S., Tapanya, S., &amp; Singh, S.  (2005). Synchrony in the onset of mental‐state reasoning ‐ Evidence from five cultures.  Psychological Science, 16(5), 378‐384. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="393" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Camerer, C. (2003). Behavior Game Theory: Experiments in Strategic Interaction. Princeton:  Princeton University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="394" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Cardenas, J. C., &amp; Carpenter, J. (2008). Behavioural development economics: Lessons from field  labs in the developing world. Journal of Development Studies, 44(3), 311‐338. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="395" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Carey, S. (1985). Conceptual change in childhood. Cambridge: MIT Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="396" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Carey, S. (1995). On the origins of causal understanding In D. Sperber &amp; D. Premack &amp; A.  Premack (Eds.), Causal Cognition. Oxford: Oxford University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="397" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Carpenter, J., Burks, S., &amp; Verhoogen, E. (2005). Comparing Students to Workers: The Effects of  Social Framing on Behavior in Distribution Games. In J. Carpenter &amp; G. W. Harrison &amp; J.  A. List (Eds.), Field Experiments in Economics. Greenwich, Connecticut: JAI. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="398" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Carpenter, J., Connolly, C., &amp; Myers, C. K. (2008). Altruistic behavior in a representative dictator  experiment. Experimental Economics, 11(3), 282‐298. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="399" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Carter, J. R., &amp; Irons, M. D. (1991). Are Economists Different, and If So, Why? Journal of  Economic Perspectives, 5(Spring), 171‐177. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="400" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Carver, C. S. (2004). Editorial. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 86, 95. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="401" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Cavalli‐Sforza, L. L., Menozzi, P., &amp; Piazza, A. (1994). The History and Geography of Human  Genes. Princeton: Princeton University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="402" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Chen, C., Lee, S.‐Y., &amp; Stevenson, H. W. (1995). Response style and cross‐cultural comparisons  of rating scales amongst East Asian and North American students. Psychological Science,  6, 170‐175. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="403" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Cheung, F. M., Leung, K., Fan, R. M., Song, W., Zhang, J., &amp; Zhang, J. (1996). Development of the  Chinese Personality Assessment Inventory. Journal of Cross‐Cultural Psychology, 27(181‐ 199), 181. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="404" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Choi, I., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (1998). Situational salience and cultural differences in correspondence  bias and the actor‐observer bias. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 24, 949‐960. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="405" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Choi, I., Nisbett, R. E., &amp; Norenzayan, A. (1999). Causal attribution across cultures: Variation and  universality. Psychological Bulletin, 125(1), 47‐61. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="406" confidence="possible" page="53" column="1">Chua, H. F., Boland, J. E., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (2005). Cultural variation in eye movements during  scene perception. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 102, 12629‐12633. </ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="410" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Church, A. T., Katigbak, M. S., Del Prado, A. M., Ortiz, F. A., Mastor, K. A., Harumi, Y., Tanaka‐ Matsumi, J., De Jesús Vargas‐Flores, J., Ibáñez‐reyes, J., White, F. A., Miramontes, L. G.,  Reyes, J. A. S., &amp; Cabrera, H. F. (2006). Implicit theories and self‐perceptions of  traitedness across cultures: Toward Integration of Cultural and Trait Psychology  Perspectives. Journal of Cross‐Cultural Psychology, 37(6), 694‐716. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="411" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Cohen, D., Hoshino‐Browne, E., &amp; Leung, A. (2007). Culture and the structure of personal  experience: Insider and outsider phenomenologies of the self and social world. In M. P.  Zanna (Ed.), Advances in Experimental Social Psychology (Vol. 39). San Diego: Academic  Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="412" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Cross, P. (1977). Not can but will college teaching be improved. New Directions for Higher  Education, 17(1‐15), 1. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="413" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">D'Andrade, R. G. (1995). The development of cognitive anthropology. Cambridge ; New York:  Cambridge University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="414" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Daly, M., &amp; Wilson, M. (1988). Homicide. New York: Aldine de Gruyter. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="415" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Dasen, P., Mishra, R. C., Niraula, S., &amp; Wassmann, J. (2006). Développement du langage et de la  cognition spatiale géocentrique. Enfance, 58, 146‐158. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="416" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Dehaene, S. (1997). The number sense : how the mind creates mathematics. New York: Oxford  University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="417" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Diener, E., Diener, M., &amp; Diener, C. (1995). Factors predicting the subjective well‐being of  nations. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 69(815‐864), 815. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="418" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Eagly, A. H., &amp; Wood, W. (1999). The origins of sex differences in human behavior: Evolved  dispositions versus social roles. American Psychologist, 54(408‐423), 408. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="419" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Earley, P. C. (1993). East meets West meets Mideast: Further explorations of collectivistic and  individualistic work groups. Academy of Management  Journal, 36, 319‐348. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="420" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Egas, M., &amp; Riedl, A. (2008). The economics of altruistic punishment and the maintenance of  cooperation. Proceedings of the Royal Society B‐Biological Sciences, 275(1637), 871‐878. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="421" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Ekman, P. (1999a). Basic Emotions. In T. Dalgleish &amp; T. Power (Eds.), The Handbook of Cognition  and Emotion (pp. 45‐60). Sussex: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="422" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Ekman, P. (1999b). Facial Expressions. In T. Dalgleish &amp; T. Power (Eds.), The Handbook of  Cognition and Emotion (pp. 301‐320). Sussex: John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="423" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Elfenbein, H. A., &amp; Ambady, N. (2002). On the universality and cultural specificity of emotion  recognition: A meta‐analysis. Psychological Bulletin, 128, 203‐235. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="424" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Elliot, I. T., Chirkov, V. I., Kim, Y., &amp; Sheldon, K. M. (2001). A cross‐cultural analysis of avoidance  (relative to approach) personal goals. Psychological Science, 12, 505‐510. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="425" confidence="possible" page="54" column="1">Ensminger, J., &amp; Cook, K. (n.d.). Pro‐social Norms among Rural and Urban Small Communities in  America:  Evidence from Dictator, Ultimatum, and Public Goods Games. In J. Ensminger  &amp; J. Henrich (Eds.), Experimenting with Social Norms: Fairness and Punishment in Cross‐ Cultural Perspective New York: Russell Sage Foundation Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="429" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Falk, C. F., Heine, S. J., Yuki, M., &amp; Takemura, K. (2009). Why Do Westerners Self‐Enhance More  than East Asians? European Journal of Personality, 23(3), 183‐203. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="430" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Farley, J. U., Lehmann, D. R., &amp; Ryan, M. J. (1981). Generalizing from 'imperfect' replication.  Journal of Business, 54, 597‐610. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="431" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fehr, E., Fischbacher, U., von Rosenbladt, B., Schupp, J., &amp; Wagner, G. G. (2002). A Nation‐Wide  Laboratory: Examining trust and trustworthiness by integrating behavioral experiments  into representative surveys. Schmoller Fahrbuch, 122, 519‐542. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="432" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fehr, E., &amp; Gächter, S. (1998). Reciprocity and Economic: The economic implications of Homo  reciprocans. European Economic Review, 42(3‐5), 845‐859. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="433" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fehr, E., &amp; Gächter, S. (2002). Altruistic Punishment in Humans. Nature, 415, 137‐140. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="434" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fehr, E., &amp; List, J. A. (2004). The Hidden Costs and Returns of Incentives‐‐Trust and  Trustworthiness among CEOs. Journal of the European Economic Association, 2(5), 743‐ 771. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="435" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fessler, D. M. T. (1999). Toward an Understanding of the Universality of Second Order  Emotions. In A. Hinton (Ed.), Beyond Nature or Nurture: Biocultural Approaches to the  Emotions (pp. 75‐116). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="436" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fessler, D. M. T. (2004). Shame in two cultures. Journal of Cognition and Culture, 4(2), 207‐262. </ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="437" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fessler, D. M. T., Nettle, D., Afshar, Y., Pinheiro, I. D., Bolyanatz, A., Mulder, M. B., Cravalho, M.,  Delgado, T., Gruzd, B., Correia, M. O., Khaltourina, D., Korotayev, A., Marrow, J., de  Souza, L. S., &amp; Zbarauskaite, A. (2005). A cross‐cultural investigation of the role of foot  size in physical attractiveness. Archives of Sexual Behavior, 34(3), 267‐276. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="438" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fiske, A. P. (1993). Social Errors in 4 Cultures ‐ Evidence About Universal Forms of Social‐ Relations. Journal of Cross‐Cultural Psychology, 24(4), 463‐494. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="439" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fiske, A. P. (1998). Learning A Culture The Way Informants Do: Observing, Imitating, and  Participating. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="440" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Flynn, J. R. (1987). Massive IQ gains in 14 nations: What IQ tests really measure. Psychological  Bulletin, 101, 171‐191. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="441" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Flynn, J. R. (2007). What is intelligence? : beyond the Flynn effect. Cambridge ; New York:  Cambridge University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="442" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fodor, J. A. (1983). The modularity of mind : an essay on faculty psychology. Cambridge, Mass.:  MIT Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="443" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Fryberg, S. A., &amp; Markus, H. R. (2003). On Being American Indian: Current and Possible Selves.  Self and Identity, 2, 325‐344. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="444" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Gachter, S., Renner, E., &amp; Sefton, M. (2008). The Long‐Run Benefits of Punishment. Science,  322(5907), 1510‐. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="445" confidence="possible" page="55" column="1">Gangestad, S. W., Haselton, M. G., &amp; Buss, D. M. (2006). Evolutionary foundations of cultural  variation: Evoked culture and mate preference. Psychological Inquiry, 17, 75‐95. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="449" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Geertz, C. (1974). "From the native's point of view": On the nature of anthropological  understanding. Bulletin of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, 28, 26‐45. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="450" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Geertz, C. (1975). On the nature of anthropological understanding. American Scientist, 63, 4‐53. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="451" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Gelman, S. A. (2003). The essential child : origins of essentialism in everyday thought. Oxford ;  New York: Oxford University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="452" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Gergen, K. J. (1973). Social psychology as history. Journal of Personality and Social Psyhology,  26, 309‐320. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="453" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Gil‐White, F. (2001). Are ethnic groups biological 'species' to the human brain? Essentialism in  our cognition of some social categories. Current Anthropology, 42(4), 515‐554. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="454" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Gilbert, D. T., &amp; Malone, P. S. (1995). The correspondence bias. Psychological Bulletin, 117, 21‐ 38. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="455" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Gilovich, T., Griffin , D., &amp; Kahneman, D. (Eds.). (2002). Heuristics and biases: The psychology of  intuitive judgment. New York: Cambridge University Press. </ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="456" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Godoy, R., Byron, E., Reyes‐Garcia, V., Leonard, W. R., Patel, K., Apaza, L., Perez, E., Vadez, V., &amp;  Wilkie, D. (2004). Patience in a foraging‐horticultural society: A test of competing  hypotheses. Journal of Anthropological Research, 60(2), 179‐202. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="457" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Gordon, P. (2005). Numerical Cognition Without Words: Evidence from Amazonia. Science, 306,  496‐499. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="458" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Greenberg, J., Solomon, S., &amp; Pyszczynski, T. (1997). Terror management theory of self‐esteem  and cultural worldviews: Empirical assessments and conceptual refinements. Advances  in Experimental Social Psychology, Vol 29, 29, 61‐139. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="459" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Grossmann, I., Na, J., Varunum, M., Kitayama, S., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (2008). Russia  interdependence and holistic cognition. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="460" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Grossmann, I., Na, J., Varunum, M., Kitayama, S., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (2009). Unpublished raw data.  Ann Arbor: University of Michigan. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="461" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Gurven, M. (2004). Does market Exposure Affect Economic Game Behavior? The Ultimatum  Game and the Public Goods Game among the Tsimane of Bolivia. In J. Henrich &amp; R. Boyd  &amp; S. Bowles &amp; C. Camerer &amp; E. Fehr &amp; H. Gintis (Eds.), Foundations of Human Sociality:  Economic experiments and ethnographic evidence from fifteen small‐scale societies (pp.  194‐231). Oxford: Oxford University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="462" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Gutchess, A. H., Welsh, R. C., Boduroglu, A., &amp; Park, D. C. (2006). Cultural differences in neural  function associated with object processing. Cognitive, Affective, &amp; Behavioral  Neuroscience, 6, 102‐109. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="463" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Guth, W., Schmidt, C., &amp; Sutter, M. (2003). Fairness in the Mail and Opportunism in the  Internet: A Newspaper Experiment on Ultimatum Bargaining. Economic Review, 4(2),  456‐475. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="464" confidence="possible" page="56" column="1">Haidt, J., &amp; Graham, J. (2007). When morality opposes justice: Conservatives have moral  intuitions that liberals may not recognize. Social Justice Research, 20, 98‐116. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="468" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Haidt, J., Koller, S. H., &amp; Dias, M. G. (1993). Affect, Culture, and Morality, or Is It Wrong to Eat  Your Dog. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 65(4), 613‐628. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="469" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Hamamura, T., Heine, S. J., &amp; Paulhus, D. L. (2008). Cultural differences in response styles: The  role of dialectical thinking. Personality and Individual Differences, 44, 932‐942. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="470" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Harrington, L., &amp; Liu, J. H. (2002). Self‐enhancement and attitudes toward high achievers: A  bicultural view of the independent and interdependent self. Journal of Cross‐Cultural  Psychology, 33, 37‐55. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="471" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Harrison, G. W., Lau, M. I., &amp; Williams, M. B. (2002). Estimating Individual Discount Rates in  Denmark: A Field Experiment. American Economic Review, 92(5), 1606‐1617. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="472" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Haun, D. B. M., Call, J., Janzen, G., &amp; Levinson, S. C. (2006). Evolutionary psychology of spatial  representations in the hominidae. Current Biology, 16(17), 1736‐1740. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="473" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Haun, D. B. M., Rapold, C. J., Call, J., Janzen, G., &amp; Levinson, S. C. (2006). Cognitive cladistics and  cultural override in Hominid spatial cognition. Proceedings of the National Academy of  Sciences of the United States of America, 103(46), 17568‐17573. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="474" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Hedden, T., Ketay, S., Aron, A., Markus, H. R., &amp; Gabrieli, J. D. E. (2008). Cultural influences on  neural substrates of attentional control. Psychological Science, 19, 12‐17. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="475" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Heine, S. J. (2008). Cultural psychology. New York: W. W. Norton. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="476" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Heine, S. J., &amp; Hamamura, T. (2007). In search of East Asian self‐enhancement. Personality and  Social Psychology Review, 11, 1‐24. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="477" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Heine, S. J., Lehman, D. R., Peng, K., &amp; Greenholtz, J. (2002). What's wrong with cross‐cultural  comparisons of subjective Likert scales?  The reference‐group problem. Journal of  Personality and Social Psychology, 82, 903‐918. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="478" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Heine, S. J., &amp; Raineri, A. (2009). Self‐improving motivations and culture: The case of Chileans.  Journal of Cross‐Cultural Psychology, 40, 158‐163. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="479" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Hennig‐Schmidt, H., Li, Z.‐Y., &amp; Yang, C. (2008). Why People Reject Advantageous Offers: Non‐ monotone Strategies in Ultimatum Bargaining: First Results from a Video Experiment in  the People's Republic of China. Journal of Economic Behavior and Organization, 65, 373‐ 384. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="480" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Henrich, J. (2008). A cultural species. In M. Brown (Ed.), Explaining Culture Scientifically. Seattle:  University of Washington Press. </ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="481" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Henrich, J., Boyd, R., Bowles, S., Camerer, C., Fehr, E., Gintis, H., McElreath, R., Alvard, M., Barr,  A., Ensminger, J., Henrich, N., Hill, K., Gil‐White, F., Gurven, M., Marlowe, F. W., Patton,  J. Q., &amp; Tracer, D. (2005). 'Economic Man' in Cross‐cultural Perspective: Behavioral  Experiments in 15 Small‐Scale Societies. Behavioral &amp; Brain Sciences, 28, 795‐815. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="482" confidence="possible" page="57" column="1">Henrich, J., Ensminger, J., McElreath, R., Barr, A., Barrett, C., Bolyanatz, A., Cardenas, J. C.,  Gurven, M., Gwako, E., Henrich, N., Lesorogol, C., Marlowe, F., Tracer, D., &amp; Ziker, J.  (n.d.). Market, religion, community size and the evolution of fairness and  punishment.Unpublished manuscript, Vancouver. </ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="486" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Henrich, J., &amp; Henrich, N. (n.d.). Fairness without punishment: behavioral experiments in the  Yasawa Island, Fiji. In J. Henrich &amp; J. Ensminger (Eds.), Experimenting with Social Norms:  Fairness and Punishment in Cross‐Cultural Perspective New York: Russell Sage Press.  Henrich, J., &amp; McElreath, R. (2002). Are Peasants Risk‐Averse Decision Makers? Current  Anthropology, 43(1), 172‐181. </ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="487" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Henrich, J., McElreath, R., Ensminger, J., Barr, A., Barrett, C., Bolyanatz, A., Cardenas, J. C.,  Gurven, M., Gwako, E., Henrich, N., Lesorogol, C., Marlowe, F., Tracer, D., &amp; Ziker, J.  (2006). Costly Punishment Across Human Societies. Science, 312, 1767‐1770. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="488" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Henrich, J., &amp; Smith, N. (2001). Culture matters in bargaining and cooperation: cross‐cultural  evidence from the Machiguenga, the Mapuche and Americans, Cooperation, reciprocity  and punishment: experiments in fifteen small‐scale societies; Manuscript. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="489" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Henrich, N., &amp; Henrich, J. (2007). Why Humans Cooperate: A Cultural and Evolutionary  Explanation Oxford: Oxford University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="490" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Henry, P. J. (2009). College sophomores in the laboratory redux: Influences of a narrow  database on social psychology's view of the nature of prejudice. Psychological Inquiry,  19, 49‐71. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="491" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Herdt, G. H. (Ed.). (1984). Ritualized Homosexuality in Melsanesia. Berkeley: University of  California. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="492" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Herdt, G. H. (Ed.). (1993). Ritualized Homosexuality in Melsanesia. Berkeley: University of  California. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="493" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Herrmann, B., Thoni, C., &amp; Gächter, S. (2008). Antisocial punishment across Societies. Science,  319(5868), 1362‐1367. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="494" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Hoffman, E., McCabe, K., &amp; Smith, V. (1998). Behavioral Foundations of Reciprocity:  Experimental Economics and Evolutionary Psychology. Economic Inquiry, 36, 335‐352. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="495" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Hofstede, G. (1980). Culture's consequences: International differences in work‐related values.  Beverly Hills, CA: Sage. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="496" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Hofstede, G. (2001). Culture's consequences: Comparing values, behaviors, institutions, and  organizations across nations. Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="497" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Hsu, M., Krajbich, I., Zhao, C., &amp; Camerer, C. F. (2009). Neural Response to Reward Anticipation  under Risk Is Nonlinear in Probabilities. Journal of Neuroscience, 29(7), 2231‐2237. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="498" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Humphrey, S. J., &amp; Verschoor, A. (2004a). Decision‐making under risk among small farmers in  East Uganda. Journal of African Economies, 13(1), 44‐101. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="499" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Humphrey, S. J., &amp; Verschoor, A. (2004b). The probability weighting function: experimental  evidence from Uganda, India and Ethiopia. Economics Letters, 84(3), 419‐425. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="500" confidence="possible" page="58" column="1">Hyde, J. S. (1981). How large are cognitive gender differences? American Psychologist, 36, 892‐ 901. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="504" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Inglehart, R., Basanez, M., &amp; Moreno, A. (1998). Human values and beliefs: A cross‐cultural  sourcebook. Ann Arbor, MI: University of Michigan Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="505" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Iyengar, S. S., &amp; DeVoe, S. E. (2003). Rethinking the value of choice: Considering cultural  mediators of intrinsic motivation. In V. Murphy‐Berman &amp; J. J. Berman (Eds.), Nebraska  Symposium on Motivation:  Vol. 49.  Cross‐cultural differences in perspectives on the self  Lincoln: University of Nebraska Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="506" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Iyengar, S. S., &amp; Lepper, M. R. (1999). Rethinking the value of choice: A cultural perspective on  intrinsic motivation. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 76, 349‐366. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="507" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Jensen, K., Call, J., &amp; Tomasello, M. (2007). Chimpanzees are rational maximizers in an  ultimatum game. Science, 318(5847), 107‐109. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="508" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Jensen, L. A. (1997). Culture wars: American moral divisions across the adult lifespan. Journal of  Adult Development, 4, 107‐121. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="509" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Ji, L., Nisbett, R. E., &amp; Zhang, Z. (2004). Is It Culture or Is It Language? Examination of Language  Effects in Cross‐Cultural Research on Categorization. Journal of Personality and Social  Psychology, 87, 57‐65. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="510" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Ji, L., Peng, K., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (2000). Culture, control and perception of relationships in the  environment. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 78, 943‐955. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="511" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Jones, E. E., &amp; Harris, V. A. (1967). The attribution of attitudes. Journal of Experimental Social  Psychology, 3, 1‐24. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="512" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Kahneman, D., Slovic, P., &amp; Tversky, A. (1982). Judgment under uncertainty : heuristics and  biases. Cambridge ; New York: Cambridge University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="513" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Kahneman, D., &amp; Tversky, A. (2000). Choices, values, and frames. New York: Cambridge  University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="514" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Kanagawa, C., Cross, S. E., &amp; Markus, H. R. (2001). “Who am I?”: The cultural psychology of the  conceptual self. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 27, 90‐103. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="515" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Kanovsky, M. (2007). Essentialism and Folksociology: Ethnicity Again. Journal of Cognition and  Culture, 7, 241‐281. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="516" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Kay, P. (2005). Color categories are not arbitrary. Cross‐Cultural Research, 39(1), 39‐55. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="517" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Kay, P., &amp; Regier, T. (2006). Language, thought and color: recent developments. Trends in  Cognitive Sciences, 10(2), 51‐54. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="518" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Kelley, R. C. (1980). Etoro Social Structure: A Study in Structural Contradiction. Ann Arbor:  University of Michigan Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="519" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Kenrick, D. T., &amp; Keefe, R. C. (1992a). Age Preferences in Mates Reflect Sex‐Differences in  Reproductive Strategies. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 15(1), 75‐&amp;. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="520" confidence="possible" page="59" column="1">Kenrick, D. T., &amp; Keefe, R. C. (1992b). Sex‐Differences in Age Preference ‐ Universal Reality or  Ephemeral Construction ‐ Authors Response. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 15(1), 119‐ &amp;. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="524" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kim, H. S., &amp; Markus, H. R. (1999). Deviance or uniqueness, harmony or conformity? A cultural  analysis. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 77, 785‐800. </ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="525" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kim, H. S., Sherman, D. K., Taylor, S. E., Sasaki, J. Y., Chu, T. Q., Ryu, C., &amp; al., e. (in press).  Culture, serotonin receptor polymorphism (5‐HTR1A), and locus of attention. Social  Cognitive and Affective Neuroscience.  Kirby, K. N., Godoy, R., Reyes‐Garcia, V., Byron, E., Apaza, L., Leonard, W., Perez, E., Vadez, V., &amp;  Wilkie, D. (2002). Correlates of delay‐discount rates: Evidence from Tsimane'  Amerindians of the Bolivian rain forest. Journal of Economic Psychology, 23(3), 291‐316. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="526" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kitayama, S., Duffy, S., Kawamura, T., &amp; Larsen, J. T. (2003). Perceiving an object and its context  in different cultures: A cultural look at new look. Psychological Science, 14, 201‐206. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="527" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kitayama, S., Park, H., Sevincer, A. T., Karasawa, M., &amp; Uskul, A. K. (2009). A cultural task  analysis of implicit independence: Comparing North America, Western Europe, and East  Asia. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 97, 236‐255. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="528" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kleinman, A. (1988). Rethinking psychiatry : from cultural category to personal experience. New  York </ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="529" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">London: Free Press.  Knowles, E. D., Morris, M. W., Chiu, C., &amp; Hong, Y. (2001). Culture and the process of person  perception: Evidence for automaticity among East Asians in correcting for situational  influences on behavior. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 27, 1344‐1356. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="530" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kohlberg, L. (1971). From is to ought: How to commit the naturalistic fallacy and get away with  it in the study of moral development. In L. Mischel (Ed.), Cognitive development and  epistemology (pp. 151‐284). New York: Academic Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="531" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kohlberg, L. (1976). Moral Stages and Moralization. In T. Lickona (Ed.), Moral Development and  Behavior: Theory, Research and Social Issues. New York: Hot, Rinehart and Winston. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="532" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kohlberg, L. (1981). The philosophy of moral development. Cambridge, UK: Harper &amp; Row. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="533" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kraul, C. (2008, April 14, 2008). Environmental pollution and encroaching narco have taken  their toll on Narino's state's Afro‐Columbians. The community's unique culture, and  altruism, is in peril. Los Angeles Time, pp. 1. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="534" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Krosnick, J. A., &amp; Alwin, D. F. (1989). Aging and susceptibility to attitude change. Journal of  Personality and Social Psychology, 57, 416‐425. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="535" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kuhn, M. H., &amp; McPartland, T. (1954). An empirical investigation of self‐attitudes. American  Sociological Review, 19, 68‐76. </ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="536" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kuhnen, U., Hannover, B., Roeder, U., Shah, A. A., Schubert, B., Upmeyer, A., &amp; Zakaria, S.  (2001). Cross‐cultural variations in identifying embedded figures ‐ Comparisons from the  United States, Germany, Russia, and Malaysia. Journal of Cross‐Cultural Psychology,  32(3), 365‐371. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="537" confidence="possible" page="60" column="1">Kusserow, A. S. (1999). De‐homogenizing American individualism: Socializing hard and soft  individualism in Manhatten and Queens. Ehtos, 27, 210‐234. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="541" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Lamont, M. (2000). The dignity of working men. New York: Russell Sage Foundation. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="542" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Lancy, D. (1996). Playing on Mother Ground: Cultural Routines for Children's Development.  London: The Guilford Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="543" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Lancy, D. (2009). The Anthropology of Childhood: Cherubs, Chattel and Changlings. Cambridge:  Cambridge University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="544" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Lee, A. Y., Aaker, J. L., &amp; Gardner, W. L. (2000). The pleasures and pains of distinct self‐ construals: The role of interdependence in regulatory focus. Journal of Personality and  Social Psychology, 78, 1122‐1134. </ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="545" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Lesorogol, C., &amp; Ensminger, J. (n.d.). Double‐Blind Dictator Games in Africa and the U.S.:   Differential Experimenter Effects. In J. Henrich &amp; J. Ensminger (Eds.), Experimenting with  Social Norms. New York: Russell Sage Press.  Levine, S. C., Vasilyeva, M., Lourenco, S. F., Newcombe, N. S., &amp; Huttenlocher, J. (2005).  Socioeconomic status modifies the sex difference in spatial skill. Psychological Science,  16(11), 841‐845. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="546" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Levinson, S. C. (2003). Space in Language and Cognition. Cambridge: Cambridge University  Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="547" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Levinson, S. C., Kita, S., Haun, D., &amp; Rasch, B. H. (2002). Returning the tables: Language affects  spatial reasoning. Cognition, 84, 155‐188. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="548" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Lewis, C. C. (1995). Educating hearts and minds. New York: Cambridge University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="549" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Li, P., &amp; Gleitman, L. (2002). Turning the tables: Language and spatial reasoning. Cognition, 83  265‐294. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="550" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Lieberman, M. D., Jarcho, J. M., &amp; Obayashi, J. (2005). Attributional inference across cultures:  Similar automatic attributions and different controlled corrections. Personality and  Social Psychology Bulletin, 31, 889‐901. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="551" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Lipset, S. M. (1996). American exceptionalism: A double‐edged sword. New York: W. W. Norton  &amp; Company. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="552" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">List, J. A. (2004). Neoclassical theory versus Prospect Theory: Evidence from the Marketplace.  Econometrica, 72, 615‐625. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="553" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Liu, D., Wellman, H. M., Tardif, T., &amp; Sabbagh, M. A. (2008). Theory of mind development in  Chinese children: A meta‐analysis of false‐belief understanding across cultures and  languages. Developmental Psychology, 44(2), 523‐531. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="554" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Low, B. S. (2000). Why Sex Matters: a Darwinian look at Human Behavior. Princeton: Princeton  University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="555" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Luria, A. R. (1976). Cognitive development: Its cultural and social foundations. Cambridge, MA:  Harvard University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="556" confidence="possible" page="61" column="1">Majid, A., Bowerman, M., Kita, S., Haun, D. B. M., &amp; Levinson, S. C. (2004). Can language  restructure cognition? The case for space. Trends in Cognitive Sciences, 8(3), 108‐114. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="560" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Mann, V. A., Sasanuma, S., Sakuma, N., &amp; Masaki, S. (1990). Sex differences in cognitive  abilities: A cross‐cultural perspective. Neuropsychologia, 28, 1063‐1077. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="561" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Markus, H. R., &amp; Kitayama, S. (1991). Culture and the self: Implications for cognition, emotion,  and motivation. Psychological Review, 98, 224‐253. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="562" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Marlowe, F. (2004). Mate preferences among Hadza hunter‐gatherers. Human Nature, 15(4),  365‐376. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="563" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Marlowe, F., Apicella, C., &amp; Reed, D. (2005). Men's preferences for women's profile waist‐to‐hip  ratio in two societies. Evolution and Human Behavior, 26(6), 458‐468. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="564" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Marlowe, F., &amp; Wetsman, A. (2001). Preferred waist‐to‐hip ratio and ecology. Personality and  Individual Differences, 30(3), 481‐489. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="565" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Masuda, T., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (2001). Attending holistically versus analytically: Comparing the  context sensitivity of Japanese and Americans. Journal of Personality and Social  Psychology, 81(992‐934). </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="566" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">May, R. M. (1997). The scientific wealth of nations. Science, 275, 793‐796. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="567" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">McCauley, R., &amp; Henrich, J. (2006). Susceptibility to the Muller‐Lyer Illusion, Theory‐Neutral  Observation, and the Diachronic Penetrability of the Visual Input System. Philosophical  Psychology, 19(1), 1‐23. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="568" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">McCrae, R. R., Terraciano, A., &amp; Project. (2005). Universal features of personality traits from the  observer’s perspective: Data from 50 cultures. Journal of Personality and Social  Psychology, 88, 547‐561. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="569" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Medin, D. L., &amp; Atran, S. (2004). The native mind: Biological categorization and reasoning in  development and across cultures. Psychological Review, 111(4), 960‐983. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="570" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Medin, D. L., &amp; Bang, M. (2008). Perspective Taking, Diversity and Partnerships. American  Psychological Association, 22(2). </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="571" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Mezulis, A. H., Abramson, L. Y., Hyde, J. S., &amp; Hankin, B. L. (2004). Is there a universal positive  bias in attributions?: A meta‐analytic review of individual, developmental, and cultural  differences in the self‐serving attributional bias. Psychological Bulletin, 130, 711‐747. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="572" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Miller, J. G. (1984). Culture and the development of everyday social explanation. Journal of  Personality and Social Psychology, 46, 961‐978. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="573" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Miller, J. G., &amp; Bersoff, D. M. (1992). Culture and moral judgment: How are conflicts between  justice and interpersonal responsibilities resolved? Journal of Personality and Social  Psychology, 62, 541‐554. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="574" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Miller, J. G., Bersoff, D. M., &amp; Harwood, R. L. (1990). Perceptions of social responsibilities in  India and the United States: Moral imperatives or personal decisions? . Journal of  Personality and Social Psychology, 58, 33‐47. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="575" confidence="possible" page="62" column="1">Miyamoto, Y., &amp; Kitayama, S. (2002). Cultural variation in correspondence bias: The critical role  of attitude diagnosticity of socially constrained behavior. Journal of Personality and  Social Psychology, 83, 1239‐1248. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="579" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Mook, D. G. (1983). In defense of external invalidity. American Psychologist, 38(4), 379‐387. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="580" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Moore, F. R., Cassidy, C., Law Smith, M. J., &amp; Perrett, D. I. (2006). The effects of female control  of resources on sex‐differentiated mate preferences. Evolution and Human Behavior,  27(3), 193‐205. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="581" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Morling, B., &amp; Lamoreaux, M. (2008). Measuring culture outside the head: A meta‐analysis of  individualism‐collectivism in cultural products. Personality and Social Psychology Review,  12, 199‐221. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="582" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Morris, M., &amp; Peng, K. (1994). Culture and cause: American and Chinese attributions for social  and physical events. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 67, 949‐971. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="583" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Neisser, U. (1963). The multiplicity of thought. British Journal of Psychology, 54, 1‐14. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="584" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Nisbett, R. E. (2003). The Geography of Thought: How Asians and Westerners Think  Differently...and Why. New York: The Free Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="585" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Nisbett, R. E. (2009). Intelligence and how to get it: Why schools and cultures count. New York,  NY: Norton. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="586" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Nisbett, R. E., Peng, K., Choi, I., &amp; Norenzayan, A. (2001). Culture and systems of thought:  Holistic versus analytic cognition. Psychological Review, 108, 291‐310. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="587" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Norenzayan, A. (2006). Evolution and transmitted culture. Psychological Inquiry, 17(2), 123‐128. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="588" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Norenzayan, A., Choi, I., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (2002). Cultural similarities and differences in social  inference: Evidence from behavioral predictions and lay theories of behavior.  Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 28(1), 109‐120. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="589" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Norenzayan, A., Choi, I., &amp; Peng, K. (2007). Cognition and Perception. In S. K. D. Cohen (Ed.),  Handbook of Cultural Psychology (pp. 569‐594). New York: Guilford Publications. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="590" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Norenzayan, A., &amp; Heine, S. J. (2005). Psychological universals: What are they and how can we  know? Psychological Bulletin, 131, 763‐784. </ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="591" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Norenzayan, A., Henrich, J., &amp; McElreath, R. (n.d.). More Chinese than the Chinese. Vancouver:  University of British Columbia.  Norenzayan, A., Smith, E. E., Kim, B. J., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (2002). Cultural preferences for formal  versus intuitive reasoning. Cognitive Science, 26(5), 653‐684. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="592" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Nowak, M. A., Page, K. M., &amp; Sigmund, K. (2000). Fairness versus reason in the Ultimatum  Game. Science, 289(5485), 1773‐1775. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="593" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Oyserman, D., Coon, H. M., &amp; Kemmelmeier, M. (2002). Rethinking individualism and  collectivism: Evaluation of theoretical assumptions and meta‐analyses. Psychological  Bulletin, 128, 1773‐1775. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="594" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Oyserman, D., &amp; Lee, S. (2008). Does culture influence what and how we think? Effects of  priming individualism and collectivism. Psychol Bull, 134(2), 311‐342. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="595" confidence="possible" page="63" column="1">Pasupathi, M. (1999). Age differences in response to conformity pressure for emotional and  nonemotional material. Psychology and Aging, 14, 170‐174. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="599" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Peng, K., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (1999). Culture, dialectics, and reasoning about contradiction.  American Psychologist, 54(9), 741‐754. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="600" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Peng, K., Nisbett, R. E., &amp; Wong, N. Y. C. (1997). Validity problems comparing values across  cultures and possible solutions. Psychological Methods, 2, 329‐344. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="601" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Peterson, R. A. (2001). On the use of college students in social science research: Insights from a  second‐order meta‐analysis. Journal of Consumer Research, 28, 450‐461. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="602" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Pica, P., Lerner, C., Izard, V., &amp; Dehaene, S. (2004). Exact and approximate arithmetic in an  Amazonian indigenous group. Science, 306, 499‐501. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="603" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Pillsworth, E. G. (2008). Mate preferences among the Shuar of Ecuador: trait rankings and peer  evaluations. Evolution and Human Behavior, 29(4), 256‐267. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="604" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Putnam, R. (2000). Bowling alone: the collapse and revival of American community. New York:  Simon and Schuster. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="605" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Regier, T., Kay, P., &amp; Cook, R. S. (2005). Focal colors are universal after all. Proceedings of the  National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 102(23), 8386‐8391. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="606" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Reifman, A., Klein, J. G., &amp; Murphy, S. T. (1989). Self‐monitoring and age. Psychology and Aging,  4, 245‐246. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="607" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Rennie, L. J., &amp; Dunne, M. (1994). Gender, ethnicity, and student's perceptiosn about science  and science‐related careers in Fiji. Science Education, 78, 285‐300. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="608" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Richerson, P., &amp; Boyd, R. (2005). Not by Genes Alone: How Culture Transformed Human  Evolution. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="609" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Rivers, W. H. R. (1901). Introduction and vision. In A. C. Haddon (Ed.), Reports of the Cambridge  anthropological expedition to the Torres Straits (Vol. II). Cambridge: The University  Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="610" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Roberson, D., Davies, I., &amp; Davidoff, J. (2000). Color categories are not universal: Replications  and new evidence from a stone‐age culture. Journal of Experimental Psychology:  General, 129(3), 369‐398. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="611" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Rogers, C. R. (1951). Client‐centered therapy. New York: Houghton Mifflin. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="612" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Rogoff, B. (2003). The cultural nature of human development. Oxford [UK] ;a New York: Oxford  University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="613" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Ross, L. D., Amabile, T. M., &amp; Steinmetz, J. L. (1977). Social roles, social control, and biases in  social‐perception processes. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 35, 485‐494. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="614" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Ross, N., Medin, D. L., Coley, J. D., &amp; Atran, S. (2003). Cultural and experiential differences in the  development of folkbiological induction. Cognitive Development, 18(1), 25‐47. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="615" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Rozin, P. (2001). Social psychology and science: Some lessons from Solomon Asch. Personality  and Social Psychology Review, 5, 2‐14. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="616" confidence="possible" page="64" column="1">Rozin, P. (2003). Five potential principles for understanding cultural differences in relation to  individual differences. Journal of Research in Personality, 37(4), 273‐283. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="620" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Rozin, P. (2009). What kind of empirical research should we publish, fund, and reward? A  different perspective. Perspectives on Psychological Science, 4, 435‐439. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="621" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Rozin, P., Fischler, C., Shields, C., &amp; Masson, E. (2006). Attitudes towards large numbers of  choices in the food domain: A cross‐cultural study of five countries in Europe and the  USA. Appetite, 46, 304‐308. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="622" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Rozin, P., &amp; Nemeroff, C. J. (1990). The laws of sympathetic magic: A psychological analysis of  similarity and contagion. In J. Stigler &amp; G. Herdt &amp; R. A. Shweder (Eds.), Cultural  Psychology: Essays on comparative human development (pp. 205‐232). Cambridge,  England: Cambridge. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="623" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Sanchez‐Burks, J. (2005). Protestant relational ideology: The cognitive underpinnings and  organizational implications of an American anomaly. Research in Organizational  Behavior: An Annual Series of Analytical Essays and Critical Reviews, Vol 26, 26, 265‐305. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="624" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Saucier, G., Georgiades, S., Tsaousis, I., &amp; Goldberg, L. R. (2005). The factor structure of Greek  personality adjectives. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 88, 856‐875. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="625" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Savani, K., Markus, H. R., &amp; Conner, A. L. (2008). Let your preference be your guid? Preferences  and choices are more tightly linked for North Americans than for Indians. Journal of  Personality and Social Psychology, 95, 861‐876. </ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="626" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Savani, K., Markus, H. R., Naidu, N. V. R., Kumar, S., &amp; Berlia, N. (in press). What counts as  choice? Americans are more likely than Indians to construe actions as choices.  Psychological Science.  Schaller, M., &amp; Murray, D. R. (2008). Pathogens, personality, and culture: Disease prevalence  predicts worldwide variability in sociosexuality, extraversion, and openness to  experience. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 95(1), 212‐221. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="627" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Schmitt, D. P. (2005). Sociosexuality from Argentina to Zimbabwe: A 48‐nation study of sex,  culture, and strategies of human mating. Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 28(2), 247‐+. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="628" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Schmitt, D. P., Allik, J., McCrae, R. R., Benet‐Martinez, V., &amp; al., e. (2007). The geographic  distribution of big five personality traits: Patterns and profiles of human self‐description  across 56 nations. Journal of Cross‐Cultural Psychology, 38, 173‐212. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="629" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Schwartz, B. (2004). The paradox of choice: Why more is less. New York: Harper‐Collins. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="630" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Schwartz, S. H., &amp; Bilsky, W. (1990). Toward a theory of the universal content and structure of  values: Extensions and cross‐cultural replications. Journal of Personality and Social  Psychology, 58, 878‐891. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="631" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Sears, D. (1986). College sophomores in the laboratory: Influences of a narrow data base on  social psychology’s view of human nature. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology,  51, 515‐530. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="632" confidence="possible" page="65" column="1">Segall, M., Campbell, D., &amp; Herskovits, M. J. (1966). The Influence of Culture on Visual  Perception. New York: The Bobbs‐Merrill Company. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="636" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Shariff, A. F., &amp; Norenzayan, A. (2007). God is watching you ‐ Priming god concepts increases  prosocial behavior in an anonymous economic game. Psychological Science, 18(9), 803‐ 809. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="637" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Sheth, J. N. (1970). Are there differences in dissonance reduction behavior among students and  housewives? Journal of Marketing Research, 7, 243‐245. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="638" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Shweder, R. A., &amp; Bourne, E. J. (1982). Does the concept of the person vary cross‐culturally? . In  A. J. Marsella &amp; G. M. White (Eds.), Cultural conceptions of mental health and therapy.  New York: Kluwer. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="639" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Shweder, R. A., Much, N. C., Mahapatra, M., &amp; Park, L. (1997). The "big three" of morality  (autonomy, community, divinity) and the "big three" explanations of suffering. In A. M.  Brandt &amp; P. Rozin (Eds.), Morality and health (pp. 119‐169). New York: Routledge. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="640" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Singh, D. (2006). Universal Allure of the Hourglass Figure: An Evolutionary Theory of Female  Physical Attractiveness. Clinics in Plastic Surgery, 33(3), 359‐370. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="641" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Singh, D., &amp; Luis, S. (1994). Ethnic and gender consensus for the effect of WHR on judgment of  women's attractiveness. Human Nature, 6, 51‐65. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="642" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Slingerland, E. G. (2008). What science offers the humanities : integrating body and culture.  Cambridge [U.K.] ; New York: Cambridge University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="643" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Sloman, S. (1996). The empirical case for two systems of reasoning. Psychological Bulletin, 119,  22‐30. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="644" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Snarey, J. R. (1985). The cross‐cultural universality of social‐moral development: A critical  review of Kohlbergian research. Psychological Bulletin, 97(2), 202‐232. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="645" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Snibbe, A. C., &amp; Markus, H. R. (2005). You can’t always get what you want: Social class, agency,  and choice. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 88, 703‐720. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="646" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Sousa, P., Atran, S., &amp; Medin, D. L. (2002). Essentialism and folkbiology: Evidence from Brazil.  Journal of Cognition and Culture, 2, 195‐223. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="647" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Stephens, N. M., Markus, H. R., &amp; Townsend, S. S. M. (2007). Choice as an act of meaning: The  case of social class. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 93, 814‐830. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="648" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Streeter, S. A., &amp; McBurney, D. H. (2003). Waist‐hip ratio and attractiveness: New evidence and  a critique of "a critical test". Evolution and Human Behavior, 24(2), 88‐98. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="649" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Sue, S. (1999). Science, ethnicity, and bias. Where have we gone wrong? American Psychologist,  54, 1070‐1077. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="650" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Sugiyama, L. S. (2004). Is beauty in the context‐sensitive adaptations of the beholder?: Shiwiar  use of waist‐to‐hip ratio in assessments of female mate value. Evolution and Human  Behavior, 25(1), 51‐62. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="651" confidence="possible" page="66" column="1">Sugiyama, L. S., Tooby, J., &amp; Cosmides, L. (2002). Cross‐cultural evidence of cognitive  adaptations for social exchange among the Shiwiar of Ecuadorian Amazonia.  Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America,  99(17), 11537‐11542. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="655" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Suh, E. M. (2002). Culture, identity consistency, and subjective well‐being. Journal of Personality  and Social Psychology, 83, 1378‐1319. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="656" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Sutter, M., &amp; Kocher, M. (2007). Age and the development of trust and reciprocity. Games and  Economic Behavior, 59, 364‐382. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="657" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Swami, V., Neto, F., Tovée, M. J., &amp; Furnham, A. (2007). Preferences for Female Body Weight  and Shape in Three European Countries. European Psychologist, 12(3), 220‐228. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="658" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Swami, V., &amp; Tovée, M. J. (2007). The relative contribution of profile body shape and weight to  judgements of women's physical attractiveness in Britain and Malaysia. Body Image,  4(4), 391‐396. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="659" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Sweeney, P. D., Anderson, K., &amp; Bailey, S. (1986). Attributional style in depression: A meta‐ analytic review. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 50, 974‐991. </ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="660" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Tanaka, T., Camerer, C., &amp; Nguyen, Q. (forthcoming). Risk and time preferences: Experimental  and household survey data from Vietnam. American Economic Review.  Tesser, A. (1988). Toward a self‐evaluation maintenance model of social behavior. In L.  Berkowitz (Ed.), Advances in experimental social psychology (Vol. Vol. 21, pp. 181‐227).  San Diego, CA: Academic Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="661" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Tocqueville, A. (1835). Democracy in America (G. Lawrence, Trans.). Garden City, NY: University  of Chicago Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="662" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Tooby, J., &amp; Cosmides, L. (1992). The psychological foundations of culture. In J. Barkow &amp; L.  Cosmides &amp; J. Tooby (Eds.), The Adapted Mind: Evolutionary Psychology and the  Generation of Culture (pp. 19‐136). New York: Oxford University Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="663" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Tracy, J. L., &amp; Matsumoto, D. (2008). The spontaneous expression of pride and shame: Evidence  for biologically innate nonverbal displays. Proceedings of the National Academy of  Sciences, 105(33), 11655‐11660. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="664" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Tracy, J. L., &amp; Robins, R. W. (2008). The nonverbal expression of pride: Evidence for cross‐ cultural recognition. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 94(3), 516‐530. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="665" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Triandis, H. C. (1989). The Self and Social‐Behavior in Differing Cultural Contexts. Psychological  Review, 96(3), 506‐520. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="666" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Triandis, H. C. (1994). Culture and social behavior. New York: McGraw‐Hill. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="667" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Triandis, H. C., Mccusker, C., &amp; Hui, C. H. (1990). Multimethod Probes of Individualism and  Collectivism. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 59(5), 1006‐1020. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="668" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Tropp, L. R., &amp; Wright, S. C. (2003). Evaluations and perceptions of self, ingroup, and outgroup:  Comparisons between Mexican‐American and European‐American children. Self and  Identity, 2, 203‐221. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="669" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Tsai, J. L. (2007). Ideal affect: Cultural causes and behavioral consequences. Perspectives on  Psychological Science, 19, 242‐259. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="670" confidence="possible" page="67" column="1">Tseng, W.‐S. (2001). Handbook of cultural psychiatry. San Diego: Academic Press. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="674" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Turkheimer, E., Haley, A., Waldron, M., D'Onofrio, B., &amp; Gottesman, I. I. (2003). Socioeconomic  status modifies heritability of IQ in young children. Psychological Science, 14(6), 623‐ 628. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="675" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Twenge, J. M., &amp; Campbell, W. K. (2001). Age and birth cohort differences in self‐esteem: A  cross‐temporal meta‐analysis. Personality and Social Psychology Review, 5(4), 321‐344. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="676" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Twenge, J. M., &amp; Im, C. (2007). Changes in the need for social approval, 1958‐2001. Journal of  Research in Personality, 41, 171‐189. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="677" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Uskul, A. K., Kitayama, S., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (2008). Ecocultural basis of cognition: Farmers and  fishermen are more holistic than herders (vol 105, pg 8552, 2008). Proceedings of the  National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 105(33), 12094‐12094. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="678" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Van Boven, L., Kamada, A., &amp; Gilovich, T. (1999). The perceiver as perceived: Everyday intuitions  about the correspondence bias. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 77, 1188‐ 1199. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="679" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Varnum, M., Grossmann, I., Kitayama, S., &amp; Nisbett, R. E. (2008). The origin of cultural  differences in cognition: the social orientation hypothesis. Ann Arbor: University of  Michigan. </ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="680" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Vohs, K. D., Baumeister, R. F., Schmeichel, B. J., Twenge, J. M., Nelson, N. M., &amp; Tice, D. M.  (2008). Making choices impairs subsequent self‐control: A limited‐resource account of  decision making, self‐regulation, and active initiative. Journal of Personality and Social  Psychology, 94(883‐898), 883. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="681" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Voyer, D., Voyer, S., &amp; Bryden, M. P. (1995). Magnitude of sex differences in spatial abilities: A  meta‐analysis and consideration of critical variables. Psychol Bull, 117, 250. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="682" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Wallace, B., Cesarini, D., Lichtenstein, P., &amp; Johannesson, M. (2007). Heritability of ultimatum  game responder behavior. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the  United States of America, 104(40), 15631‐15634. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="683" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Waxman, S., &amp; Medin, D. L. (2007). Experience and cultural models matter: Placing firm limits  on childhood anthropocentrism. Human Development, 50(1), 23‐30. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="684" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Waxman, S., Medin, D. L., &amp; Ross, N. (2007). Folk‐biological reasoning‐from a cross‐cultural  developmental perspective: Early essentialist notions are shaped by cultural beliefs.  Developmental Psychology, 43(2), 294‐308. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="685" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Wicherts, J. M., Borsboom, D., Kats, J., &amp; Molenaar, D. (2006). The poor availability of  psychological research for reanalysis. American Psychologist, 61, 726‐728. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="686" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Wintre, M. G., North, C., &amp; Sugar, L. A. (2001). Psychologists' response to criticisms about  research based on undergraduate participants: A developmental perspective. Canadian  Psychology, 42, 216‐225. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="687" confidence="possible" page="68" column="1">Witkin, H. A., &amp; Berry, J. W. (1975). Psychological Differentiation in Cross‐Cultural Perspective.  Journal of Cross‐Cultural Psychology, 6(1), 5‐78. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="691" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">Wu, S., &amp; Keysar, B. (2007). Cultural effects on perspective taking. Psychological Science, 18,  600‐606. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="692" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">Yik, M. S. M., Russell, J. A., Ahn, C., Fernandez‐Dols, J. M., &amp; Suzuki, N. (2002). Relating the five‐ factor model of personality to a circumplex model of affect: A five language study. In R.  R. McCrae &amp; J. Allik (Eds.), The Five‐Factor Model of Personality Across Cultures (pp. 79‐ 104). New York: Kluwer. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="693" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">Yu, D. W., &amp; Shepard, G. H. (1998). Is beauty in the eye of the beholder? Nature, 396(6709),  321‐322. </ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="694" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">Zebian, S., &amp; Denny, J. P. (2001). Integrative cognitive style in Middle Eastern and Western  groups. Journal of Cross‐Cultural Psychology, 32, 58‐75. </ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="695" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">    Endnotes  1 We also use the term “WEIRD” throughout this paper to refer to the exceptional nature of this sample, and do not intend any negative connotations or moral judgments by the acronym. 2 Key steps include (1) establishing nationally representative experimental samples in Europe (Fehr, Fischbacher, von Rosenbladt, Schupp, &amp; Wagner, 2002; Guth, Schmidt, &amp; Sutter, 2003), (2) applying experimental methods in developing countries (Cardenas &amp; Carpenter, 2008; Tanaka, Camerer, &amp; Nguyen, forthcoming), (3) creating</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="696" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">university-wide subject recruiting rather than discipline-specific subject pools (most economic experiments), and (4) targeting specific samples of non-student subjects (Bellemare, Kroeger, &amp; Van Soest, 2008; Bellemare &amp; Kroger,</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="697" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">2007; Harrison, Lau, &amp; Williams, 2002; List, 2004).</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="698" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">3 Comparative studies of individual decision-making processes using samples from small-scale and WEIRD populations, including explorations of risk aversion, prospect theory and inter-temporal choice, yield mixed results. Sometimes similarities, both qualitative and quantitative, are found. Other times differences emerge (Cardenas &amp; Carpenter, 2008; Henrich &amp; McElreath, 2002; Hsu, Krajbich, Zhao, &amp; Camerer, 2009; Humphrey &amp; Verschoor, 2004a, 2004b; Kirby et al., 2002; Tanaka et al., forthcoming). So far, we do not see how to figure out which features</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="699" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">will vary and which will not. 4 Rivers, for instance, found that cultures with a single color term for blue and green could still tell the difference between a blue and a green thread. 5 Fessler also emphasizes important differences in shame and guilt between Americans and Indonesians. 6 To illustrate the limits of inferring universality from two-population comparisons we note the finding that field independence on the Rod and Frame task is shown both for migratory foragers and Americans (Witkin &amp; Berry, 1975), yet East Asians and sedentary foragers show evidence for field dependence (Ji, Peng, &amp; Nisbett, 2000).</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="700" confidence="possible" page="69" column="1">7 We are using “Western” to refer to those countries clustered in the north-west of Europe (the U.K., France, Germany, Switzerland, the Netherlands, etc.), and British-descent societies such as the U.S. Canada, New Zealand, and Australia. In particular, we are concerned about those populations from which most subjects in behavioral and psychological experiments are drawn. We recognize that there are important limitations and problems with this label, but we use it for convenience.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="704" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">                                                                                                                                                                               8 See also Knowles et. al. (2001); but, for contrary findings see Lieberman, Jarcho, &amp; Obayashi (2005).</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="705" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">9 Interestingly, evidence indicates a somewhat different pattern in small-scale societies, see Marlowe (2004), Moore</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="706" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">et al. (2006), and Pillsworth (2008).</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="707" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">10 Efforts to replicate these findings in various small-scale societies have all failed (Marlowe &amp; Wetsman, 2001;</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="708" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">Sugiyama, 2004; Yu &amp; Shepard, 1998). These failures suggest a more complicated, and context-specific set of</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="709" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">evolutionary hypotheses (Marlowe, Apicella, &amp; Reed, 2005; Swami &amp; Tovée, 2007).</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="710" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">11 The factor structure was less evident in a number of developing populations (e.g., Botswana, Ethiopia, Lebanon, Malaysia, Puerto Rico, Uganda), where independent assessments revealed that the data quality was poor. Future efforts to obtain better quality data from these countries are important for demonstrating the universality of the Five Factor Model. 12 The robustness of the Five Factor Model is considerably weaker when it is derived from indigenous personality traits from other languages, although some of the five traits do still emerge (Benet-Martinez &amp; Waller, 1995;</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="711" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">Cheung et al., 1996; Saucier, Georgiades, Tsaousis, &amp; Goldberg, 2005).</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="712" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">13 As American and Canadian researchers at a Canadian university we note that Canada is also a highly unusual population along the same lines as the US, although perhaps not quite as pronounced as the US, at least in terms of individualism (Hofstede, 1980).</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="713" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">14 These examples illustrate a parallel problem for those interested in the differences between human and non-human cognition. Since most ape-human comparisons involve WEIRD people (or their children) as subjects, some seeming ape-human differences may not represent real species-level contrasts, but may instead reflect the psychological peculiarities of WEIRD people (Boesch, 2007).</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="714" confidence="possible" page="70" column="1">15 Thanks to Shaun Nichols for pointing this out. 16 We note that the heuristics and biases derived from this empirical work were, however, readily extended to “people” without hesitation (Kahneman, Slovic, &amp; Tversky, 1982).</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="366" page="51" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="367" page="51" column="1">49</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="368" page="52" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="387" page="52" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="388" page="52" column="1">50</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="389" page="53" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="407" page="53" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="408" page="53" column="1">51</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="409" page="54" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="426" page="54" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="427" page="54" column="1">52</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="428" page="55" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="446" page="55" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="447" page="55" column="1">53</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="448" page="56" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="465" page="56" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="466" page="56" column="1">54</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="467" page="57" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="483" page="57" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="484" page="57" column="1">55</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="485" page="58" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="501" page="58" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="502" page="58" column="1">56</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="503" page="59" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="521" page="59" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="522" page="59" column="1">57</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="523" page="60" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="538" page="60" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="539" page="60" column="1">58</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="540" page="61" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="557" page="61" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="558" page="61" column="1">59</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="559" page="62" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="576" page="62" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="577" page="62" column="1">60</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="578" page="63" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="596" page="63" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="597" page="63" column="1">61</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="598" page="64" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="617" page="64" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="618" page="64" column="1">62</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="619" page="65" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="633" page="65" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="634" page="65" column="1">63</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="635" page="66" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="652" page="66" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="653" page="66" column="1">64</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="654" page="67" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="671" page="67" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="672" page="67" column="1">65</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="673" page="68" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="688" page="68" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="689" page="68" column="1">66</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="690" page="69" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="701" page="69" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="702" page="69" column="1">67</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="703" page="70" column="1">Weird People</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="715" page="70" column="1"> </outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="page_nr" id="716" page="70" column="1">68</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
