<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<pdfx xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://pdfx.cs.man.ac.uk/static/article-schema.xsd">
  <meta>
    <job>e4c54a097f51b747546af095eb4840ee1c6dfc427b2ad00909a87c5730336803</job>
    <base_name>60</base_name>
    <doi>10.1177/0022022108330992</doi>
    <warning>Name identification was not possible. </warning>
  </meta>
  <article>
    <front class="DoCO:FrontMatter">
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="2">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="1">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link></outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="3">Sylvia</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="4">Xiaohua Chen, Journal of</region>
      <title-group>
        <article-title class="DoCO:Title" id="5">Behavioral Manifestations of Modesty Michael Harris Bond, Bacon Chan, Donghui Tang Cross-Cultural Psychology 2009; 40; 603 originally published</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <region class="unknown" id="6">and Emma E. Buchtel online Feb 6, 2009;</region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="8" confidence="possible">DOI: 10.1177/0022022108330992 The online version of this article can be found at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/40/4/603" id="7">http://jcc.sagepub.com/cgi/content/abstract/40/4/603</ext-link></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="9" confidence="possible">Published by:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx10">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="60.page_001.image_01.png" thmb="60.page_001.image_01-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="12"> <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.sagepublications.com" id="11">http://www.sagepublications.com</ext-link></region>
      <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="13" confidence="possible">On behalf of:</region>
      <region class="DoCO:FigureBox" id="Fx14">
        <image class="DoCO:Figure" src="60.page_001.image_02.png" thmb="60.page_001.image_02-thumb.png"/>
      </region>
      <region class="unknown" id="20">International Association for Cross-Cultural Psychology Additional services and information for Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology can be found at: Email Alerts: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com/cgi/alerts" id="15">http://jcc.sagepub.com/cgi/alerts</ext-link> Subscriptions: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com/subscriptions" id="16">http://jcc.sagepub.com/subscriptions</ext-link> Reprints: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.sagepub.com/journalsReprints.nav" id="17">http://www.sagepub.com/journalsReprints.nav</ext-link> Permissions: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.sagepub.com/journalsPermissions.nav" id="18">http://www.sagepub.com/journalsPermissions.nav</ext-link> Citations <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com/cgi/content/refs/40/4/603" id="19">http://jcc.sagepub.com/cgi/content/refs/40/4/603</ext-link></region>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="22">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="21">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="23">Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
      <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="sidenote" id="24">4</outsider>
      <region class="unknown" id="26">Volume 40 Number July 2009 603-626 Behavioral Manifestations © 2009 The Author(s) 10.1177/0022022108330992 of Modesty <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jccp.sagepub.com" id="25">http://jccp.sagepub.com</ext-link> Sylvia Xiaohua Chen</region>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="27" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">The Hong Kong Polytechnic University</h2>
        <region class="unknown" id="28" page="2" column="1">Michael Harris Bond Bacon Chan</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="29" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">The Chinese University of Hong Kong Donghui Tang Beijing Normal University Emma E. Buchtel University of British Columbia</h2>
        <region class="unknown" id="30" page="2" column="1">Three studies examined the social manifestations of modesty in Chinese and Canadian cultures, conceptualizing and operationalizing it as a self-presentation tactic with communal functions. In Study 1, the authors developed a self-report Modest Behavior Scale (MBS) to tap the behavioral aspects of modesty and identified three factors: self-effacement, other-enhancement, and avoidance of attention-seeking. The authors validated the scale by establishing its nomological network with trait modesty, individuation, independent and interdependent self- construals, traditionality, and modernity, in both Hong Kong and Shanghai, which are culturally different regions of China. In Study 2, the MBS was supplemented with additional items, and a different set of predictors, including values, was used to predict the three factors in both Hong Kong and Beijing, China. In Study 3, we administered the MBS in Vancouver, Canada, adding emic items generated from this Canadian sample and using values and other variables as predictors. Gender differences are discussed in terms of the role played by modest self- presentations in promoting intragroup harmony in different cultural settings. Keywords: modesty; modest behavior; individuation; traditionality and modernity; independent and interdependent self-construals</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="32" page="2" column="1">T he chologists, construct and of modesty social psychologists has been conceptualized from various by perspectives, psycholinguists, and operationalized personality psy- in different ways accordingly. Psycholinguists study modesty as a politeness phenomenon, especially in response to compliments (e.g., Gao &amp; Ting-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R26" id="31" class="deo:Reference">Toomey, 1998</xref>; Spencer-Oatey &amp;</region>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="34" confidence="possible" page="2" column="1">Authors’ Note: We would like to express our appreciation to Darius K. S. Chan, Fanny M. Cheung, Paul Taylor, Steven J. Heine, and Rita W. M. Law for their help in improving this article, and to Wai Chan for his advice on the statistical analyses. Thanks also go to the Editor of this journal and the two reviewers for their constructive comments on earlier versions of the manuscript. This project was supported in part by Mainland Collaborative Research Grant of the Chinese University of Hong Kong and the Internal Competitive Research Grant (G-YG87) of the Hong Kong Polytechnic University. Address correspondence concerning this article to: Sylvia Chen, Department of Applied Social Sciences, Hong Kong Polytechnic University, Hung Hom, Kowloon, Hong Kong S.A.R., China; e-mail: <email id="33">ssxhchen@polyu.edu.hk</email>. 603</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="36" page="2" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="35">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="37" page="3" column="1">604 Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="100" page="3" column="1"> <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63" id="38" class="deo:Reference">Ng, 2000</xref>). In framing his politeness principle, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R43" id="39" class="deo:Reference">Leech (1983)</xref> described the modesty maxim as minimizing praise of oneself or maximizing dispraise of oneself in verbal expressions. Extending Leech’s politeness principle, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="40" class="deo:Reference">Gu (1990)</xref> developed a politeness principle for Chinese culture, consisting of four maxims: self-denigration, address, tact, and generosity. In addition to self-effacement, which is a focus of Leech’s (1983) modesty maxim, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="41" class="deo:Reference">Gu (1990)</xref> added enhancing others to the self-denigration maxim. Thus, modesty within the politeness framework focuses mostly on self-denigration, so as to show respect toward interlocutors and promote the positive face of conversation partners by minimizing self-praise. To assess modesty as a politeness tactic, linguists have designed conversational situations in which compliments are initiated, and then recipients’ responses are elicited (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="42" class="deo:Reference">Chen, 1993</xref>; Spencer-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R63" id="43" class="deo:Reference">Oatey &amp;Ng, 2000</xref>). The content of these responses was analyzed and categorized based on the politeness principle so as to identify the rules and maxims characterizing polite modesty. Patterns of linguistic features can also be compared across cultural groups to discover similarities and differences in the strategies used. The contrast can then be linked to respective social values of the cultures, especially the composition of self-concept (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R13" id="44" class="deo:Reference">Chen, 1993</xref>). As revealed by the above procedures, however, such measures are limited in nature, because they only focus on the verbal content of social interactions, so that only conversational features of politeness strategies can be detected. From the perspective of personality psychologists, modesty is construed as a personality disposition (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="45" class="deo:Reference">Costa &amp; McCrae, 1992</xref>), a trait that is consistent across time and situations. In the five-factor model of personality as assessed by the NEO Personality Inventory (NEO PI; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R18" id="46" class="deo:Reference">Costa &amp; McCrae, 1985</xref>), the Agreeableness factor is defined by six facets, including modesty. The Modesty facet denotes humble and self-effacing traits, but not necessarily a lack of self-confidence or self-esteem. A closer examination of the eight items constitut- ing the modesty facet, however, shows that these personality statements depict personal thoughts, feelings, and actions, indicating how an individual feels about himself/herself compared with others, for example, having a high opinion of oneself. Yet, research on false modesty has documented discrepancies between people’s private evaluations and their public behaviors (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R5" id="47" class="deo:Reference">Baumeister &amp; Ilko, 1995</xref>; Gould, Brounstein, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R28" id="48" class="deo:Reference">Sigall, 1977</xref>). People may downplay their achievements and express gratitude in public to avoid others’ jealousy and resentment (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R21" id="49" class="deo:Reference">Exline &amp; Lobel, 1999</xref>), or understate their abilities to reduce performance pressure and to lower the evaluation baseline being applied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R27" id="50" class="deo:Reference">Gibson &amp; Sachau, 2000</xref>). Therefore, we suggest that modesty should be examined as a constellation of social behaviors as well as a personality trait. When managing their impressions on others, people employ a variety of self-presentational strategies to create favorable images (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R4" id="51" class="deo:Reference">Baumeister, 1982</xref>; Leary, Robertson, Barnes, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R42" id="52" class="deo:Reference">Miller, 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R54" id="53" class="deo:Reference">Schlenker &amp; Leary, 1982</xref>; Wosinska, Dabul, Whetstone-Dion, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="54" class="deo:Reference">Cialdini, 1996</xref>). The motivation for these strategies is to achieve positive outcomes, or at least avoid negative consequences in social interactions (Heine, Takata, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R32" id="55" class="deo:Reference">Lehman, 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R53" id="56" class="deo:Reference">Schlenker, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R55" id="57" class="deo:Reference">Schneider, 1969</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="58" class="deo:Reference">Wosinska et al., 1996</xref>). Social psychologists view modesty as one tactic of impression management, with <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="59" class="deo:Reference">Cialdini and DeNicholas (1989)</xref> defining modesty as “the under-representation of one’s positive traits, contributions, expectations, or accom- plishments” (p. 626). One approach to studying modesty, for example, relates to earlier work on ingratiation, in which presenting one’s personal attributes indirectly was found to be more effective than expressing them directly (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="60" class="deo:Reference">Wosinska et al., 1996</xref>).<marker type="page" number="4"/><marker type="block"/> Previous studies on impression management have shown that self-enhancement strategies (e.g., exaggerating the degree of one’s success or attributing one’s success to internal factors, such as abilities or effort) may not contribute to an enhanced reputation for competence, but instead damage interpersonal relationships (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R12" id="65" class="deo:Reference">Carlson &amp; Shovar, 1983</xref>; Forsyth, Berger, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R24" id="66" class="deo:Reference">Mitchell, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R33" id="67" class="deo:Reference">Jones &amp; Wortman, 1973</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R51" id="68" class="deo:Reference">Powers &amp; Zuroff, 1988</xref>; Sadalla, Kenrick, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R52" id="69" class="deo:Reference">Vershure, 1987</xref>). These findings are consistent with the propositions of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R17" id="70" class="deo:Reference">Colvin, Block, and Funder (1995)</xref> and of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R50" id="71" class="deo:Reference">Paulhus (1998)</xref>, pointing out the social disadvantage of using self-enhancement tactics, at least across the communal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R1" id="72" class="deo:Reference">Bakan, 1966</xref>) dimension of one’s reputation. As a result, people refrain from uttering self-aggrandizing descriptions in public, unless these are normatively prescribed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="73" class="deo:Reference">Cialdini &amp; DeNicholas, 1989</xref>). Self-effacing tactics characterizing modest performances have even been found to be more effective in organizational settings (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R16" id="74" class="deo:Reference">Cialdini &amp; DeNicholas, 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="75" class="deo:Reference">Wosinska et al., 1996</xref>). By understating one’s positive qualities or contributions or by attributing one’s success to external factors, such as luck or others’ assistance (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R68" id="76" class="deo:Reference">Weiner, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R73" id="77" class="deo:Reference">Zuckerman, 1979</xref>), one is more likely to reduce the social risk of offending one’s coworkers and generate affiliative responses from these others. Consistent with this reasoning, research findings have shown that people who respond modestly to their performances are better liked than those who respond boastfully in Chinese culture (Bond, Leung, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="78" class="deo:Reference">Wan, 1982</xref>). Similar results have been found in Western culture, with modest teachers being more likable than boastful teachers (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="79" class="deo:Reference">Tetlock, 1980</xref>).<marker type="block"/> Cultural theories have suggested that self-enhancement varies across cultures, with higher levels in individualistic cultures and lower levels in collectivistic cultures (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R35" id="82" class="deo:Reference">Kurman, 2001b</xref>, 2002, 2003; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R38" id="83" class="deo:Reference">Kurman &amp; Sriram, 1997</xref>, 2002; Kurman, Yoshihara-Tanaka, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R40" id="84" class="deo:Reference">Elkoshi, 2003</xref>). According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R31" id="85" class="deo:Reference">Heine, Lehman, Markus, and Kitayama (1999)</xref>, self-enhancement, although common in Western cultures, is not universal; rather, a self-critical, self-effacing orientation is more prevalent in the East. In contrast, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R61" id="86" class="deo:Reference">Sedikides, Gaertner, and Toguchi (2003)</xref> have maintained that self-enhancement was mediated by attribute importance, with a universal motive to self-enhance on personally important dimensions, whereas collectivist attributes were perceived as more important by individuals with interdependent self-views. A growing body of studies has indicated that in collectivistic cultures, a modesty bias or an other-enhancement focus is more characteristic (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R62" id="87" class="deo:Reference">Shikanai, 1978</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R67" id="88" class="deo:Reference">Wada, 1988</xref>). These results indicate that having to perform in social contexts and cultural norms associated with performance in these contexts account for modest self-presentations. A self- restraining or other-enhancing orientation guides appropriate responses in a collectivist cultural setting (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="89" class="deo:Reference">Markus &amp; Kitayama, 1991</xref>). Accordingly, through a series of cross-cultural studies, Kurman (2001a,b, 2003) compared explanations for cultural differences in self- enhancement level and concluded that culturally derived, normative restrictions on self- presentation explained lower self-enhancement in collectivistic cultures, because modesty, rather than group relatedness or unique self-identity, mediated the relations between culture and the tendency to self-enhance.<marker type="page" number="5"/><marker type="block"/> Based on the above review, we conceptualize modesty as a self-presentation tactic and examine manifestations of modest behavior in differing cultural contexts. We suggest that modest behavior does not necessarily arise from low self-regard, but instead reflects cultural norms and examine this position in three studies: In Study 1, we developed a self- report Modest Behavior Scale (MBS) to tap the behavioral manifestations of the underlying disposition across various social contexts. The structure of modest behavior and its nomological network were examined in two Chinese cultural settings (Hong Kong and Shanghai) to validate the designed scale. In Study 2, we supplemented the MBS with additional items and further validated it in another two Chinese settings (Hong Kong and Beijing). A set of predictors including self-construals and values were included in addition to trait modesty. In Study 3, we administered the MBS to a Canadian sample, adding modest behavior items generated by this sample. Using the same set of predictors as in Study 2, we confirmed the construct validity of the MBS and generalized its nomological network from Eastern to Western cultures.<marker type="block"/> As the measurement of modesty is somewhat fragmentary and unsystematic, we sought to supplement the trait measure of modesty by developing an assessment scale for behavioral aspects of modesty. The first study was conducted in Chinese societies, where modesty has been emphasized as a traditional virtue. To validate this measure, several relevant constructs were used to establish its nomological network. A seemingly opposing construct to modesty, individuation, taps a different behavioral style and represents one’s willingness to differentiate oneself from others publicly (Kwan, Bond, Boucher, Maslach, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="96" class="deo:Reference">Gan, 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="97" class="deo:Reference">Maslach, 1974</xref>). Individuation emphasizes the need to present the self as unique and independent. Given their focus on distinctive and independent actions, individuating behaviors may be hypothesized as the polar opposite of modest behaviors. Similarly, we predicted that a modest behavioral style would be positively correlated with an interdependent self-construal, but negatively with an independent self-construal; independent self-construals guide the expression of individual desires, preferences, or abilities, whereas the interdependent worldview works at integrating the self within relationships (e.g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="98" class="deo:Reference">Markus &amp; Kitayama, 1991</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R36" id="99" class="deo:Reference">Kurman &amp; Sriram, 2002</xref>). Finally, two closely related concepts, modernity and traditionality, were extracted from Yang’s (1996) analysis of Chinese culture. The decrease of Chinese traditionality and increase of modernity have resulted from societal modernization characterized by a rise in individuation. As the traditionality concept captures a social orientation and modernity focuses on individual-oriented needs, we hypothesized that modesty would be positively related to traditionality, but negatively related to modernity. The first study was conducted in two cultural contexts, Hong Kong and Shanghai, both Chinese settings but characterized by two different sociopolitical systems. We chose these sites to control for some potential confounds, as they share the same written language system and similar customs, yet differ in their degree of modernity and openness to the West. Therefore, this study started from a Chinese perspective to examine behavioral aspects of modesty.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="63" page="3" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="62">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="64" page="4" column="1">Chen et al. / Modest Behavior Across Cultures 605</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="81" page="4" column="1">Modesty in Cultural Contexts</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="92" page="4" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="91">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="93" page="5" column="1">606 Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
        <region class="unknown" id="95" page="5" column="1">Study 1</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="102" page="5" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="101">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="103" page="6" column="1">Chen et al. / Modest Behavior Across Cultures 607</outsider>
      </section>
    </front>
    <body class="DoCO:BodyMatter">
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="104" page="6" column="1">Method</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="105" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">Participants</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="106" page="6" column="1">A total of 392 university students participated in Study 1 on a voluntary basis. Of these, 188 (86 males and 102 females) were from the Chinese University of Hong Kong, and 204 (117 males and 87 females) from Jiaotong University of Shanghai, China. Their mean age was 19.56 (SD 1.27) in Hong Kong and 19.81 (SD = 1.50) in Shanghai.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="107" confidence="possible" page="6" column="1">= Instruments</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="115" page="6" column="1">Participants in Hong Kong and Shanghai completed the following questionnaires in traditional and simplified Chinese characters, respectively. The equivalence of meaning on all items was ensured through consultations with bilinguals from Hong Kong and Mainland China. <marker type="block"/> Modest Behavior Scale (MBS). This instrument asks respondents to report on the whole range of their self-restraining behaviors. Potential items were extracted from a literature search, content review, and consultations with cultural informants. They included different aspects of modesty (e.g., self-humbling behaviors, other-enhancing comments) and various responses to compliments and criticism. Thirty-two items were developed to tap different behavioral aspects of modesty (e.g., “I admit my own faults and apologize when someone criticizes me”). Responses were anchored on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree). Some items were formulated in the reverse direction to reduce problems associated with an acquiescent response set.<marker type="block"/> Modesty Subscale of the Revised NEO Personality Inventory (NEO PI-R). Eight items assessing the modesty facet under the Agreeableness factor were selected from the NEO PI-R (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R19" id="110" class="deo:Reference">Costa &amp; McCrae, 1992</xref>), a well-validated measure of personality traits. Each item was measured on a 5-point scale ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree). A sample item is, “I feel that I am no better than others, no matter what their condition.” In the present study, the reliability coefficient for this scale was .67.<marker type="block"/> Self-Construal Scale. Designed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="112" class="deo:Reference">Gudykunst et al. (1996)</xref>, this scale assesses independent and interdependent views of the self. Following a derived-etic analysis across 5 cultural groups, Gudykunst et al. identified 14 items measuring independence in culturally equiva- lent ways (e.g., “I try not to depend on others”) and 15 items likewise identifying interdependence (e.g., “I consult with others before making important decisions”). Responses for both subscales were indicated on a 7-point scale from 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree). In this study, the reliability coefficients for independence and interdependence were .81 and .82, respectively.<marker type="block"/> The Individuation Scale. The Individuation Scale was developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="114" class="deo:Reference">Maslach (1974)</xref> to assess the willingness to differentiate oneself publicly. It is a 12-item, 5-point scale ranging from 1 (not at all willing to do this) to 5 (very much willing to do this). All 12 items focus in the respondent’s tendency to behave in individuating ways. A sample item is, “Speak up about your ideas even though you are uncertain of whether you are correct.” The Cronbach’s alpha for this scale was .84 in this study.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="117" page="6" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="116">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="118" page="7" column="1">608 Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="119" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Multidimensional Scale of Chinese Individual Traditionality (MS-CIT) and Modernity</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="123" page="7" column="1">(MS-CIM). Two scales were developed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R71" id="120" class="deo:Reference">Yang, Yu, and Yeh (1991)</xref> to measure the traditional and modern psychological characteristics during the process of societal modernization. There are five subscales in MSCIT (Submission to Authority, Filial Piety and Ancestral Worship, Passivity and Conservativeness, Fatalism and Protectionism, and Male Dominance), and five in MSCIM, including Equalitarianism and Open-Mindedness, Social Isolation and Self-Reliance, Optimism and Assertiveness, Affective Hedonism, and Sex Equality. Each subscale is assessed by eight items, resulting in a total of 40 items in MSCIT and MSCIM, respectively. Six-point Likert scales were used ranging from 1 (very strongly disagree) to 6 (very strongly agree).<marker type="block"/> The General Self-Efficacy Scale. A 10-item General Self-Efficacy Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="122" class="deo:Reference">Schwarzer &amp; Jerusalem, 1995</xref>) was used to tap one’s perceived competence. Responses were made on a 4-point scale ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 4 (strongly agree). A sample item is, “I can always manage to solve difficult problems if I try hard enough.” The alpha was .89 in this study.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="124" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">Procedure</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="125" page="7" column="1">The questionnaire sets were administered to the participants to complete privately. They also reported demographic information, including age, gender, year, and major of study. Instructions were given at the beginning of sessions, and confidentiality was ensured to encourage honest responses.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Results">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="126" page="7" column="1">Results</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="127" confidence="possible" page="7" column="1">The Modest Behavior Scale</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="132" page="7" column="1">The 32 items for the MBS were administered and evaluated. Some items were dropped later because they pertained more to self-evaluation than to behavioral style. Another two items were deleted due to their weak, negative item-total correlations. As a result, 22 items were retained. Then, exploratory factor analysis (EFA) was conducted on the 22 items after combining the two cultural samples, given their comparable number of participants and gender. Cattell’s scree test showed that 3 to 4 factors were possible. Varimax rotation was used to compare the three- and four-factor solutions. As the four-factor solution yielded some loadings greater than .3 on two or more factors, and the three-factor structure was more interpretable and chosen as the final solution. Ten items loaded highest on the first factor (eigenvalue = 2.83), accounting for 12.89% of the total variance. The items loading on this factor tapped restraint in pursuing self-interest, and could be termed self-effacement. The second factor was composed of six items (eigenvalue = 1.72), accounting for 7.8% of the variance. This factor encompassed items involving the expression of concern for others and their elevation of others, and so was labeled other-enhancement. Six items loaded on the third factor (eigenvalue = 1.54), accounting for 7.01% of the matrix variance. Items loading on this factor pertained to avoiding self-promotion and self-aggrandizement in public, so it was thus named avoidance of attention-seeking. Even though none of the items showed a negative item-whole correlation, the alphas for the three factors were .60, .54, and .38, respectively, suggesting <marker type="page" number="8"/><marker type="block"/> a need to improve the MBS. Factor scores were computed for subsequent analyses based on equal weighting of the constituent items. Descriptive statistics including means and standard deviations of the measures under study are presented in Table 1. Each scale was examined for internal consistency in both cultural samples. Item 7 from the Modernity scale showed a negative item-total correlation and was thus excluded from further analyses. Pearson correlation coefficients were computed for each factor of the MBS and other variables (see also Table 1). These three factors had moderate positive correlations with trait modesty, r(391) = .46, .22, .28, respectively, p .001, providing construct validity for the MBS.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="130" page="7" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="129">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="131" page="8" column="1">Chen et al. / Modest Behavior Across Cultures 609</outsider>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="133" confidence="possible" page="8" column="1">&lt; Predicting Modest Behavior</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="152" page="8" column="1">Three sets of hierarchical regression analyses were conducted to predict behavioral manifestations of modesty, with its three factors as criterion variables (see Table 2). Demographic variables, including age, gender, and cultural group were entered into Block 1 to control for their effects. Self-efficacy was entered into Block 2 to examine whether modesty reflected weak self-efficacy, and trait modesty and individuation into Block 3 to test their predictive power. Finally, Block 4 contained a set of predictors to test for their additional contributions: independent and interdependent self-construals, traditionality, and modernity. Results of the regression analysis for the self-effacement factor showed that the sample multiple correlation coefficient was .55, indicating that the regression model accounted for approximately 29.7% of the total variance, R 2 = .30, F(10, 382) = 16.11, p &lt; .001. Among the demographics, the effect of gender was significant, p &lt; .05, with females being more self-effacing than males. Trait modesty showed strong explanatory power, p &lt; .001. Consistent with our hypotheses, this criterion variable was positively related to interdependence and negatively to independence, p &lt; .01. Traditionality emerged as a significant contributor, but in a negative direction, p &lt; .001. In other words, more traditional individuals were less self-effacing. In predicting other-enhancement, the sample multiple correlation coefficient was .53, indicating that the regression model explained 27.6% of the variance, R 2 = .28, F(10, 382) = 14.54, p &lt; .001. The effect of cultural group was significant, p &lt; .05, with the Hong Kong Chinese less likely to enhance others than their Shanghai counterparts. Self-efficacy and trait modesty were also significantly and positively related to other-enhancement, both p &lt; .01. Among other predictors, only interdependence contributed significant variance above and beyond trait modesty, p &lt; .001. The sample multiple correlation coefficient was .44 for the regression predicting avoidance of attention-seeking, and 18.9% of its variance was explained by the predictors, R 2 = .19, F(10, 382) = 8.91, p &lt; .001. None of the demographic variables reached significance, p &gt; .05. Trait modesty was still a significant contributor, p &lt; .001, and as expected, traditionality was positively related to avoidance of attention-seeking, p &lt; .001. <marker type="block"/> In Study 1, we developed the MBS and used personality traits and cultural orientations to predict its three factors. However, the items were generated from a “top-down” process,<marker type="page" number="11"/><marker type="block"/> and the reliability coefficients of the newly constructed scale were low. To improve the validity and reliability of the scale, and to expand its nomological network, we conducted Study 2 in Hong Kong and Beijing, another cosmopolitan city in China, identifying a different set of predictors for validation purposes. As personality constructs alone have not emerged to be strong predictors of social behavior (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R23" id="146" class="deo:Reference">Fishbein &amp; Ajzen, 1975</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R48" id="147" class="deo:Reference">Mischel, 1968</xref>), Study 2 seeks to add values as predictors. Values are “desirable goals, varying in importance, that serve as guiding principles in people’s lives” (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R57" id="148" class="deo:Reference">Schwartz, 1994</xref>, p. 88). The 10 motivationally distinct types of individual values are postulated to form a quasi-circumplex structure in which adjacent values are more related and opposing ones more complementary (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="149" class="deo:Reference">Schwartz, 1992</xref>). They are grouped on two basic bipolar dimensions, each containing two higher-order value types, with the 10 value types subordinate to them. One opposing dimension consists of Openness to Change (Self-Direction and Stimulation) versus Conservation (Conformity, Tradition, and Security). The other includes Self-Transcendence (Universalism and Benevolence) versus Self-Enhancement (Achievement and Power), whereas Hedonism belongs to both Openness to Change and to Self-Enhancement. This value structure has been well-validated in samples from more than 60 countries and found to be associated with many behavioral, attitude, and personality variables (e.g., <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R58" id="150" class="deo:Reference">Schwartz &amp; Bardi, 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="151" class="deo:Reference">Schwartz &amp; Boehnke, 2004</xref>). In this study, we use the four higher-order types in our regression models to reduce the number of predictors and sim- plify interpretation. Of the four dimensions, Self-Enhancement is especially relevant to the behavioral aspects of modesty, as a strong desire for achievement and power should be negatively related to the avoidance of attention-seeking. As a traditional virtue, the modest behavioral style, especially the factor of other-enhancement, was hypothesized to associate positively with Conservation, which encompasses traditional, conservative values.</region>
          <region class="unknown" id="135" page="8" column="1">Study 2</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="138" page="8" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="137">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="139" page="9" column="1">3 – – – .63*** –.18** –.24*** –.06 .20** – – –.19** –.30*** .16* .15* 2 – – .33*** .25*** .22** .20** .25*** .39*** – – .25*** .08 .43*** .36*** 3 Study 1 – .14* .29*** .41*** –.28*** –.18* .02 .21** – – –.05 –.02 .15* .19** Alpha .73 .78 .80 .80 .83 .87 .77 .82 – – .84 .87 .86 .85 0.57 0.42 0.51 0.62 0.40 0.72 0.58 0.64 – – 1.30 1.29 1.16 1.31 3.06 3.88 3.45 3.48 3.02 3.02 5.38 5.16 – – 5.75 5.47 6.27 5.40 3 – – – .35*** –.13** –.17*** –0.03 .16** – – –.19*** –.34*** .13** .10* 2 – – .31*** .07 .12** .15** .06 .37*** – – .03 –.02 .22*** .24*** 2 Study 1 – –.11* .25*** .48*** –.24*** –.39*** –.17*** .07 – – –.05 –.06 .08 .11 Alpha .76 .79 .72 .70 .85 .84 .75 .77 – – .75 .80 .78 .76 0.65 0.44 0.43 0.50 0.47 0.61 0.60 0.58 – – 0.95 0.94 0.71 0.79 2.94 3.68 3.50 3.11 2.58 3.04 5.05 5.09 – – 3.85 3.72 4.50 3.92 3 – – – .28*** –.22*** –.22*** –.17*** –.12** .26*** –.23*** – – – – 2 – – –.09 .22*** .16** .07 .25*** .42*** –.16** .21*** – – – – 1 Study 1 – .24*** –.04 .46*** –.21*** –.18*** –.14** .13** –.21*** .01 – – – Alpha .60 .54 .38 .67 .89 .84 .81 .82 .89 .89 – – – – 0.43 0.47 0.45 0.52 0.54 0.62 0.72 0.68 0.57 0.53 – – – – .001. 3.18 3.78 2.75 3.18 2.65 2.96 5.02 5.04 2.63 4.43 – – – – Measure Self-effacement 1. 2. Other-enhancement Avoidance 3. of attention-seeking 4. modesty Trait Self-efficacy 5. 6. Individuation Independence 7. Interdependence 8. Traditionality 9. 10. Modernity 11. change to Openness Self-enhancement 12. Self-transcendence 13. Conservation 14. .05. *p **p .01. ***p 610</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="141" page="9" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="140">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="142" page="10" column="1">611</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="144" page="10" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="143">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="145" page="11" column="1">612 Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="153" page="11" column="1">Method</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="154" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Participants</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="155" page="11" column="1">A total of 405 college students participated in the second study, with 206 (106 males and 100 females) from the Chinese University of Hong Kong, and 199 (106 males and 93 females) from Beijing Normal University, China. The mean age was 20.68 (SD = 1.39) for Hong Kong and 20.52 (SD = 2.16) for Beijing. All were invited to take part in this study on a voluntary basis.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="156" confidence="possible" page="11" column="1">Measures</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="168" page="11" column="1">Similar to Study 1, participants in Hong Kong and Beijing completed the following instruments in traditional and simplified Chinese characters, respectively. Three scales were adopted from Study 1: the Individuation Scale ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="157" class="deo:Reference">Maslach, 1974</xref>), the General Self-Efficacy Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="158" class="deo:Reference">Schwarzer &amp; Jerusalem, 1995</xref>), and the Self-Construal Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="159" class="deo:Reference">Gudykunst et al., 1996</xref>).<marker type="block"/> Revised Modest Behavior Scale. A pilot study was conducted to gather additional items tapping modest behavior. Nine participants (two males, seven females), aged from 18 to 46, were asked to list behavioral items instantiating modest behavior. As a result, 17 new items<marker type="page" number="12"/><marker type="block"/> were generated, and we administered a total of 30 items, including 13 items selected from Study 1 that best represented the construct; a sample new item is, “Attribute success to luck rather than one’s own ability in front of others.” Responses were anchored on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree).<marker type="block"/> The Schwartz Value Survey (SVS). The 57-item version of the SVS (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="166" class="deo:Reference">Schwartz, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R59" id="167" class="deo:Reference">Schwartz &amp; Boehnke, 2004</xref>) was used to measure how important each value was to participants. Each item was followed by a short explanatory phrase in parentheses, for example, “equality (equal opportunity for all).” Participants were asked to rate the importance of each item as a guiding principle in their lives on a 9-point scale, ranging from –1 (opposed to my principles), through 0 (not important), 3 (important), 6 (very important), to 7 (of supreme importance).</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="163" page="11" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="162">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="164" page="12" column="1">Chen et al. / Modest Behavior Across Cultures 613</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="169" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Procedure The procedure for Study 2 was the same as that used in Study 1.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Results">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="170" page="12" column="1">Results</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="171" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">Revised Modest Behavior Scale</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="172" page="12" column="1">Exploratory factor analysis was performed on the 30 items of the revised MBS. The scree test indicated a three-factor solution. Similar to the factor structure for modest behavior in Study 1, six items loaded on self-effacement (eigenvalue = 2.16), accounting for 7.20% of the total variance. Twelve items loaded on other-enhancement (eigenvalue = 4.86), accounting for 16.19% of the variance. Eleven items loaded on avoidance of attention-seeking (eigenvalue = 3.59), accounting for 11.96% of the variance. The reliability coefficients for the three factors were .76, .79, and .72, respectively, which were greatly improved compared with the alphas of Study 1. Factor scores were computed for subsequent analyses based on an equal weighting of the constituent items from each factor. Descriptive statistics including means, standard deviations, reliability coefficients and correlation coefficients of the variables with modest behavior are presented in Table 1. Trait modesty had moderate positive correlations with self-effacement and avoidance of attention-seeking, r(405) .48, .35, respectively, p .001, but not with other-enhancement, p &lt; .05.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="173" confidence="possible" page="12" column="1">= &lt; Predicting Modest Behavior</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="184" page="12" column="1">Three sets of hierarchical regression analyses were conducted to predict the three factors of the MBS (see Table 3). As in Study 1, demographic variables, including age, gender, and cultural group were entered into Block 1 and self-efficacy into Block 2. Block 3 contained trait modesty and individuation. In contrast to Study 1, Block 4 included another set of predictors: independent and interdependent self-construals and the four value factors. Results of the first regression analysis, predicting self-effacement, showed that the sample multiple correlation coefficient was .57, so the model explained 32.7% of the total variance, R 2 = .33, F(12, 392) = 15.88, p &lt; .001. Among the demographics, the effect of cultural group was significant, p &lt; .01, with Hong Kong Chinese being more self-effacing than their Beijing counterparts. The criterion was positively related to trait modesty, but negatively to individuation, p &lt; .001. <marker type="page" number="14"/><marker type="block"/> In predicting other-enhancement, the sample multiple correlation coefficient was .45, indicating that the regression model accounted for 20.2% of the variance, R 2 = .25, F(12, 392) = 8.26, p &lt; .001. The effects of demographics were not significant, p &gt; .05. Trait modesty did not reach significance, p &gt; .05. Among other predictors, individuation, interdependence, and the value factor of Conservation made significant contributions, p &lt; .05. Predicting avoidance of attention-seeking, the sample multiple correlation coefficient was .50, with 25.2% of the variance being explained by the predictors, R 2 = .25, F (12, 392) = 11.01, p &lt; .001. The effect of cultural group was significant, with Hong Kong Chinese less likely to avoid engaging in attention-seeking behaviors than their Beijing counterparts, p &lt; .05. The criterion was positively related to trait modesty and independence, but negatively to the value factor of Self-Enhancement, p &lt; .05.<marker type="block"/> In Studies 1 and 2, we developed and revised the MBS to acceptable levels of reliability and identified various predictors of its three dimensions in different Chinese cultural groups, encompassing personality, cultural orientations, and values. The question remained whether the MBS is applicable to non-Chinese contexts and whether it would show a similar factor structure in a Western culture. Therefore, we conducted Study 3 with Canadian respondents in Vancouver, Canada, using the same set of predictors as in Study 2 to examine the nomological network for the MBS in that different cultural setting. To avoid an “imposed etic” analysis of behavior (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R6" id="183" class="deo:Reference">Berry, 1969</xref>, 1989), we adopted a “derived- etic” approach by conducting a pilot study to generate “emic” items representing a modest behavioral style from Canadians. Incorporating these items into our revised MBS, we attempted to develop an integrated measure across Eastern and Western cultures.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="176" page="12" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="175">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="177" page="13" column="1">614</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="179" page="13" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="178">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="180" page="14" column="1">Chen et al. / Modest Behavior Across Cultures 615</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="182" page="14" column="1">Study 3</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Methods">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="185" page="14" column="1">Method</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="186" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Participants</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="187" page="14" column="1">A total of 204 undergraduate students (52 males and 152 females) from the University of British Columbia participated in the third study. Their mean age was 20.48 (SD = 3.65). All of them were born in Canada. They were invited to take part in this study on a voluntary basis.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="188" confidence="possible" page="14" column="1">Measures</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="198" page="14" column="1">Similar to Study 2, participants completed the following instruments in English. The equivalence of meaning on all items was ensured through consultations with bilinguals in Hong Kong and Canada. <marker type="block"/> A culturally integrated Modest Behavior Scale. A pilot study was conducted to gather items for behavioral aspects of modesty from Canadians. Eight participants (four males, four females), aged from 18 to 25 and all born in Canada, were asked to list behavioral items showing modesty. As a result, 9 new items were generated, so that 39 items including the 30 items from Study 2 were administered in Study 3. A sample new item is, “Encourage<marker type="page" number="15"/><marker type="block"/> someone else to take the lead.” Responses were anchored on a 5-point Likert scale ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 5 (strongly agree). Other scales were used as in Study 2 including the Individuation Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="194" class="deo:Reference">Maslach, 1974</xref>), the Self-Construal Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R30" id="195" class="deo:Reference">Gudykunst et al., 1996</xref>), the General Self-Efficacy Scale (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R60" id="196" class="deo:Reference">Schwarzer &amp; Jerusalem, 1995</xref>), and the Schwartz Value Survey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R56" id="197" class="deo:Reference">Schwartz, 1992</xref>).</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="192" page="14" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="191">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="193" page="15" column="1">616 Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="199" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Procedure This study followed the same procedure outlined in Studies 1 and 2.</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="deo:Results">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="200" page="15" column="1">Results</h1>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="201" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">Integrated Modest Behavior Scale</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="202" page="15" column="1">Exploratory factor analysis was performed on the 39 items of the integrated MBS. The scree test again showed that three to four factors were possible. Varimax rotation was used to compare the three- and four-factor solutions. Given that the three-factor structure was more interpretable and consistent with our previous conceptualizations, it was chosen as the final model. Similar to the factor structure of the MBS in Study 2, eight items loaded on self-effacement (eigenvalue = 2.74), accounting for 7.0% of the total matrix variance. Fifteen items loaded on other-enhancement (eigenvalue = 5.99), accounting for 15.4% of the variance. Fourteen items loaded on avoidance of attention-seeking (eigenvalue = 3.38), accounting for 8.7% of the variance. Item content and their psychometric properties for the previous and final MBS are shown in Table 4. The alphas were .73, .78, and .80, respectively, which were also sat- isfactory, as in Study 2. Factor scores were computed for subsequent analyses based on equal weighting of each factor’s constituent items. Descriptive statistics including means, standard deviations, reliability coefficients, and correlation coefficients of the variables with the MBS are presented in Table 1. Trait modesty had modest to strong positive correlations with the three factors of the MBS, r(204) = .41, .25 and .63, respectively, p .001.</region>
        </section>
        <section class="DoCO:Section">
          <h2 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="203" confidence="possible" page="15" column="1">&lt; Predicting Modest Behavior</h2>
          <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="218" page="15" column="1">Three sets of hierarchical regression analyses were conducted to predict the three factors of the MBS using the same set of predictors as in Study 2 (see Table 5). Results of the first regression analysis showed that the sample multiple correlation coefficient was .48 and the model explained 23.4% of the total variance in self-effacement, R 2 = .23, F(11, 192) = 5.34, p &lt; .001. None of the demographics reached significance, p &gt; .05. The criterion was positively related to trait modesty and independence, but negatively to self-efficacy, p &lt; .01. In predicting other-enhancement, the sample multiple correlation coefficient was .63, indicating that the regression model accounted for 39.8% of the variance, R 2 = .40, F(11, 192) = 11.55, p &lt; .001. Again, none of the demographics reached significance, p &gt; .05. The effects of trait modesty, self-efficacy, and interdependence were significant, p &lt; .05. Among the value factors, Openness to Change, Self-Enhancement, and Conservation made significant contributions, p &lt; .05. The sample multiple correlation coefficient was .70 for the third regression, so that 49.4% of the variance in avoidance of attention-seeking was explained by the predictors, R 2 = .49, F(11, 192) = 17.03, p &lt; .001. Demographics were not significant, p &gt; .05. The criterion was positively related to trait modesty and the value factor of Conservation, but negatively to individuation and the value factor of Self-Enhancement, p &lt; .05. <marker type="page" number="19"/><marker type="block"/> The present study sought to measure modesty by developing an instrument to tap its behavioral manifestations. The results of factor analysis across the three studies suggest that modesty encompasses three behavioral components: self-effacement, other-enhancement, and avoidance of attention-seeking. All three factors were positively related to the trait measure of modesty in Mainland China, Hong Kong, and Canada, so that their moderate correlations with the three components of the MBS supported its construct validity. Furthermore, the nomological networks surrounding them revealed the breadth of the construct and signified the need to examine these aspects of modest enactments separately. In hierarchical regressions, the three factors were shown to relate to several personality and social variables above and beyond the predictive power provided by a trait measure of modesty. Prediction of modest behavioral self-reports demonstrated independent contributions from other measures of personality and values, indicating that they constitute a complex social psychological phenomenon.</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="206" page="15" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="205">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="207" page="16" column="1">617</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="209" page="16" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="208">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="210" page="17" column="1">618</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="212" page="17" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="211">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="213" page="18" column="1">619</region>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="215" page="18" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="214">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
          <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="216" page="19" column="1">620 Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
          <region class="unknown" id="217" page="19" column="1">General Discussion</region>
        </section>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="219" page="19" column="1">Deconstructing Modesty</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="225" page="19" column="1">The first two factors of the MBS have provided empirical evidence to support previous conceptions of politeness (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="220" class="deo:Reference">Gu, 1990</xref>) and self-effacement (Bond, Kwan, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="221" class="deo:Reference">Li, 2000</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R29" id="222" class="deo:Reference">Gu (1990)</xref> considered that the modesty notion underlying politeness maxims comprised two clauses or submaxims: denigrating oneself and elevating others. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="223" class="deo:Reference">Bond et al. (2000)</xref> decom- posed the sense of superiority/inferiority (i.e., rater-derived enhancement) into two components, self-regard and regard for others. These interrelated concepts not only focus on self-regard and self-interest, but also concentrate on concern for others and orientation toward others. They parallel the first two factors identified by the MBS: self-effacement and other-enhancement. We also further derived a third factor from these respondent-derived judgments of modesty: avoidance of attention-seeking. This component delineates behavioral tendencies of personal restraint in public. It captures how the underlying personality disposition expresses itself in social contexts, reflecting the self in careful, reserved relation to others. Together they resemble the three aspects of the self proposed by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R66" id="224" class="deo:Reference">Triandis (1989)</xref>, namely, the private self, the collective self, and the public self. The interplay of these three components of the self provides the basis for a rich and complex social drama.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="226" page="19" column="1">Modesty and Self-Efficacy</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="236" page="19" column="1">It is intriguing to find that other-enhancement was positively correlated with self-efficacy, whereas the other two factors were negatively correlated with self-efficacy in all three studies. However, it is also notable that after controlling for trait modesty, only in Canada was the self-effacement factor negatively related to self-efficacy; for other studies, the other two factors were unrelated to self-efficacy after controlling for trait modesty. Though strong interpretations of this cultural difference are limited, we suggest that only in some cultures will self-restraining behavior go beyond an expression of modesty to reflect low self-regard. Self-efficacy denotes one’s sense of competence and mastery over the environment ( <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R2" id="227" class="deo:Reference">Bandura, 1977</xref>, 1992; Chen, Chan, Bond, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R15" id="228" class="deo:Reference">Stewart, 2006</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R72" id="229" class="deo:Reference">Zhang &amp; Schwarzer, 1995</xref>). Self-effacement and avoidance of<marker type="page" number="20"/><marker type="block"/> attention-seeking are self-humbling tactics, which might seem to be contrary to self-perceived competence and mastery. Conversely, actions to enhance others, such as ingratiation, could derive from the belief that consequences of events are controlled by oneself as well as by the surrounding environment. Hence individuals make conscious efforts to maintain interpersonal harmony and achieve desirable outcomes. In fact, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R11" id="234" class="deo:Reference">Bond and colleagues (1982)</xref> found that self-effacing individuals were better liked, though seen as less competent than self-enhancing ones. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R65" id="235" class="deo:Reference">Tetlock (1980)</xref> found that modest teachers were perceived to be more likable, competent, and self-confident than boastful teachers. These mixed findings in perceived competence across cultures echo the call to differentiate this rich, multifaceted construct. We submit that modesty does not represent low self-regard, but serves as an effective self-presentational tactic by competent social actors, used to maintain a viable persona across various cultural-situ- ational contexts.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="232" page="19" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="231">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="233" page="20" column="1">Chen et al. / Modest Behavior Across Cultures 621</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="237" page="20" column="1">Other-Enhancement and Interdependence</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="239" page="20" column="1">As other-enhancement represents regard for others and the elevation of others, it is not surprising that an interdependent self-construal emerged as a significant predictor above and beyond trait modesty in both Chinese and Canadian cultures. Other-enhancement does not originate from a negative evaluation of one’s competence. Rather, it arises in part from one’s awareness of interdependence, a sensitivity to one’s relationships with others, and a concern with maintaining harmony and achieving integration in social interactions. An interdependent view of the self gears one’s behavior toward emphasizing group member- ship and identity, focusing on in-group goals rather than personal goals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R45" id="238" class="deo:Reference">Markus &amp; Kitayama, 1991</xref>). Other-enhancing behavior, as guided by interdependence, addresses the concern for others’ feelings, respect for others’ needs, and being tactful and non-offensive.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="240" page="20" column="1">Individuation as the Opposite Pole</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="245" page="20" column="1">Regression findings revealed that individuation accounted for significant variance in avoidance of attention-seeking in Studies 2 and 3. Indeed, avoidance of attention-seeking is a state of de-individuation, the opposite pole of individuation on the continuum of self- presentation. Individuation can establish a sense of identity and individuality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R46" id="241" class="deo:Reference">Maslach, 1974</xref>; Maslach, Stapp, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R47" id="242" class="deo:Reference">Santee, 1985</xref>). Behaviors that distinguish oneself from others get attention because of their uniqueness and distinctiveness, but this public attention is what modest and humble people try to avoid. Contrarily, modest people restrain themselves in public settings. They may wear ordinary clothing and bland colors, use minimal and standard accessories, and agree with rather than criticize others. Thus, the negative relations between individuation and modest behavior represent the opposing enactments of independent and interdependent self-views. Individuating and modest behavior may serve different social functions, earlier identified by Bales (1950) as task and maintenance, and these two behavioral profiles will probably drive different reputations. Individuating behavior is more leadership-oriented, and those high in individuation are rated as extraverted by others (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R41" id="243" class="deo:Reference">Kwan et al., 2002</xref>). Modest behavior is integration-oriented, and those showing modest behavior may be perceived as helpful, agreeable, and pro-social (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="244" class="deo:Reference">Bond et al., 2000</xref>). Individuating behavior is agentic, modest behavior is communal.</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="247" page="20" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="246">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="248" page="21" column="1">622 Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="249" page="21" column="1">Values as Predictors</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="253" page="21" column="1">The regression findings partially confirmed our hypotheses concerning the value dimensions, indicating that self-enhancement motivations suppressed modest behavior, especially on avoidance of attention-seeking in Study 3. A self-promoting presentation contradicts the motive to avoid others’ attention in public. Given that the value factor of Conservation represents a traditional mindset (Chen, Bond, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R14" id="250" class="deo:Reference">Tang, 2007</xref>), Conservation was related to other-enhancement in Studies 2 and 3, consistent with our hypothesis. Since modesty has long been regarded as a traditional virtue (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R25" id="251" class="deo:Reference">Gabrenya &amp; Hwang, 1996</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R70" id="252" class="deo:Reference">Yang, 1996</xref>), it is understandable that traditionality was related to other-enhancement, but intriguing to find it related negatively to Self-Effacement. In other words, less traditional individuals were more likely to use self-restraining tactics. A plausible explanation is that participants in Study 1 are students from prestigious universities in two modern cities of China. Living and studying in such competitive social surroundings make them feel intimi- dated, and they therefore have a stronger need to use modest self-presentation strategies, such as self-effacement, to maintain interpersonal harmony and avoid social disapproval.</region>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Section">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="254" page="21" column="1">Gender Differences in the MBS</h1>
        <region class="DoCO:TextChunk" id="272" page="21" column="1">In our first study, the finding that females were higher than males in self-effacement is consistent with cultural norms about gender roles. In achievement settings, females tend to be more modest than males by taking less credit for success, but more responsibility for failure (Berg, Stephan, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R8" id="255" class="deo:Reference">Dodson, 1981</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R22" id="256" class="deo:Reference">Feather &amp; Simon, 1973</xref>; Levine, Gillman, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R44" id="257" class="deo:Reference">Reis, 1982</xref>; Pasquella, Mednick, &amp; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R49" id="258" class="deo:Reference">Murray, 1981</xref>). <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="259" class="deo:Reference">Wosinska et al. (1996)</xref> found that when the self-presenters were women, highly modest responses were preferred to moderate ones; in contrast, moderate modest responses by males were favored. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R20" id="260" class="deo:Reference">Dabul, Wosinska, Cialdini, Mandal, and Dion (1997)</xref> replicated this U.S. study in Poland and obtained similar results. Surprisingly, male participants in Study 2 showed more other-enhancement than females. As females are stereotyped as more nurturing and caring for others, the modesty norm seems more congruent with the femininity of the communal dimension, rather than the masculinity of the agentic dimension. Again, dispositions and social behaviors may be different. Possibly, males take the initiative to elevate others for the purpose of managing others’ impressions in a collectivist society. This could be explained by the societal expectations of the male gender role being more assertive and open, whereas that of the female being more humble and restrained (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R10" id="261" class="deo:Reference">Bond et al., 2000</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R69" id="262" class="deo:Reference">Wosinska et al., 1996</xref>).<marker type="block"/> According to <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="265" class="deo:Reference">Tangney (2000)</xref>, a psychological construct can be assessed by two distinct approaches: the dispositional and the situational. The modesty measures in the literature represent these two levels of interest: The dispositional approach adopted by personality researchers assesses individual differences as stable, enduring characteristics with personality inventories; the situational approach adopted by social psychologists manipulates and measures social factors (e.g., the relative status or the relational intimacy of the interact- ants), thereby discovering how individuals’ modest behavioral responses are elicited.<marker type="page" number="22"/><marker type="block"/> Further studies may identify additional predictors of the MBS, such as self-monitoring and self-consciousness, to enrich our understanding of the construct. Constructing the MBS was an attempt to go beyond the conceptualization of personality style and assess modesty in its contextual enactments. Past research often uses psychological constructs and scales developed from Western cultures and applies them to Eastern contexts to test for their generalizability. It is worthwhile to explore psychological constructs of Eastern origin, such as modesty, filial piety, and harmony, in Western contexts to examine their generalizability and role in different cultural systems. Future research can make more attempts to apply these salient constructs from Eastern cultural settings to Western cultural settings, what <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R9" id="270" class="deo:Reference">Bond (1999)</xref> earlier referred to metaphorically as Marco Polo returning to the West with noodles. When discussing the assessment of humility, a construct closely related to modesty, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R64" id="271" class="deo:Reference">Tangney (2000)</xref> contended that virtually no empirical research had established a widely recognized and well-validated measure of humility, due to the very nature of self-report in capturing the diversity of humility components. From this perspective, a limitation of the present study is our use of a self-report measure to operationalize modest behavior. We concur that more work should be done to assess actual behavior and compare different methods for validating the construct. One approach is to obtain peer ratings of a given target’s modest behavior and examine the relations between self and peer ratings. We expect that the three different components of modest behavior will be differentially sensitive to self-other differences and that the self-other correlations across these three components will be moderated by aspects of the target’s personality, including values and social beliefs.</region>
        <region class="unknown" id="264" page="21" column="1">Future Research</region>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="268" page="21" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="267">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="269" page="22" column="1">Chen et al. / Modest Behavior Across Cultures 623</outsider>
      </section>
      <section class="DoCO:Bibliography">
        <h1 class="DoCO:SectionTitle" id="273" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">References</h1>
        <ref-list class="DoCO:BiblioGraphicReferenceList">
          <ref rid="R1" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="274" page="22" column="1">Bakan, D. (1966). The duality of human existence. Chicago: Rand McNally. Bales, R. F. (1950). Interaction process analysis. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1976.</ref>
          <ref rid="R2" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="275" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Bandura, A. (1977). Self-efficacy: Toward a unifying theory of behavioral change. Psychological Review, 84, 191-215.</ref>
          <ref rid="R3" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="276" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Bandura, A. (1992). Exercise of personal agency through the self-efficacy mechanism. In R. Schwarzer (Ed.), Self-efficacy: Thought control of action (pp. 3-38). Washington, DC: Hemisphere.</ref>
          <ref rid="R4" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="277" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Baumeister, R. F. (1982). A self-presentational view of social phenomena. Psychological Bulletin, 91, 3-26.</ref>
          <ref rid="R5" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="278" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Baumeister, R. F., &amp; Ilko, S. A. (1995). Shallow gratitude: Public and private acknowledgement of external help in accounts of success. Basic and Applied Social Psychology, 16, 191-209.</ref>
          <ref rid="R6" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="279" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Berry, J. W. (1969). On cross-cultural comparability. International Journal of Psychology, 4, 119-128.</ref>
          <ref rid="R7" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="280" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Berry, J. W. (1989). Imposed etics–emics–derived etics: The operationalisation of a compelling idea. International Journal of Psychology, 24, 721-735.</ref>
          <ref rid="R8" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="281" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Berg, J. H., Stephan, W. G., &amp; Dodson, M. (1981). Attributional modesty in women. Psychology of Women Quarterly, 5, 711-727.</ref>
          <ref rid="R9" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="282" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Bond, M. H. (1999). The psychology of the Chinese people: A Marco Polo returns to Italy. Psychologia Italiana, 17, 29-33.</ref>
          <ref rid="R10" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="283" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Bond, M. H., Kwan, V. S. Y., &amp; Li, C. (2000). Decomposing a sense of superiority: The differential social impact of self-regard and regard for others. Journal of Research in Personality, 34, 537-553.</ref>
          <ref rid="R11" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="284" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Bond, M. H., Leung, K., &amp; Wan, K., C. (1982). The social impact of self-effacing attributions: The Chinese case. The Journal of Social Psychology, 118, 157-166.</ref>
          <ref rid="R12" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="285" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Carlson, D. E., &amp; Shovar, N. (1983). Effects of performance attributions on others’ perceptions of the attributor. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 44, 515-525.</ref>
          <ref rid="R13" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="286" confidence="possible" page="22" column="1">Chen, R. (1993). Responding to compliments: A contrastive study of politeness strategies between American English and Chinese speakers. Journal of Pragmatics, 20, 49-75.</ref>
          <ref rid="R14" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="290" page="23" column="1">Chen, S. X., Bond, M. H., &amp; Tang, D. (2007). Decomposing filial piety into filial attitudes and filial enactments. Asian Journal of Social Psychology, 10, 213-223.</ref>
          <ref rid="R15" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="291" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Chen, S. X., Chan, W., Bond, M. H., &amp; Stewart, S. M. (2006). The effects of self-efficacy and relationship harmony on depression across cultures: Applying level-oriented and structure-oriented analyses. Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 37, 643-658.</ref>
          <ref rid="R16" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="292" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Cialdini, R. B., &amp; De Nicholas, M. E. (1989). Self-presentation by association. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 57, 626-631.</ref>
          <ref rid="R17" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="293" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Colvin, C. R., Block, J., &amp; Funder, D. C. (1995). Overly positive self-evaluations and personality: Negative implications for mental health. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 68, 1152-1162.</ref>
          <ref rid="R18" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="294" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Costa, P. T., Jr., &amp; McCrae, R. R. (1985). The NEO Personality Inventory manual. Odessa, FL: Psychological Assessment Resources.</ref>
          <ref rid="R19" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="295" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Costa, P. T., Jr., &amp; McCrae, R. R. (1992). Revised NEO Personality Inventory (NEO PI-R) and NEO Five-Factor Inventory (NEO-FFI) Professional Manual. Odessa, FL: Psychological Assessment Resources.</ref>
          <ref rid="R20" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="296" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Dabul, A. J., Wosinska, W., Ciadini, R. B., Mandal, E., &amp; Dion, R. W. (1997). Self-presentational modesty across cultures: The effects of gender and social context in the workplace. Polish Psychological Bulletin, 28, 295-306.</ref>
          <ref rid="R21" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="297" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Exline, J. J., &amp; Lobel, M. (1999). The perils of outperformance: Sensitivity about being the target of a threaten- ing upward comparison. Psychological Bulletin, 125, 307-337.</ref>
          <ref rid="R22" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="298" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Feather, N. T., &amp; Simon, J. G. (1973). Fear of success and causal attributions for outcome. Journal of Personality, 41, 525-542.</ref>
          <ref rid="R23" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="299" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Fishbein, M., &amp; Ajzen, I. (1975). Belief, attitude, intention, and behavior: An introduction to theory and research. Reading, MA: Addison-Wesley.</ref>
          <ref rid="R24" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="300" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Forsyth, D. R., Berger, R. E., &amp; Mitchell, T. (1981). The effects of self-serving vs. other-serving claims of responsibility on attraction and attribution in groups. Social Psychology Quarterly, 44, 59-64.</ref>
          <ref rid="R25" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="301" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Gabrenya, Jr., W. K., &amp; Hwang, K.-K. (1996). Chinese social interaction: Harmony and hierarchy on the good earth. In M. H. Bond (Ed.), The handbook of Chinese psychology (pp. 309-321). Hong Kong, China: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R26" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="302" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Gao, G., &amp; Ting-Toomey, S. (1998). Communicating effectively with the Chinese. London: Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R27" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="303" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Gibson, B., &amp; Sachau, D. (2000). Sandbagging as a self-presentational strategy: Claiming to be less than you are. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 26, 56-70.</ref>
          <ref rid="R28" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="304" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Gould, R., Brounstein, P. J., &amp; Sigall, H. (1977). Attributing ability to an opponent: Public aggrandizement and private denigration. Sociometry, 40, 254-261.</ref>
          <ref rid="R29" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="305" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Gu, Y. (1990). Politeness phenomena in modern Chinese. Journal of Pragmatics, 14, 237-257.</ref>
          <ref rid="R30" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="306" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Gudykunst, W. B., Matsumoto, Y., Ting-Toomey, S., Nishida, T., Kim, K., &amp; Heyman, S. (1996). The influence of cultural individualism-collectivism, self-construals, and individual values on communication styles across cultures. Human Communication Research, 22, 510-543.</ref>
          <ref rid="R31" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="307" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Heine, S. J., Lehman, D. R., Markus, H. R., &amp; Kitayama, S. (1999). Is there a universal need for positive self-regard? Psychological Review, 106, 766-794.</ref>
          <ref rid="R32" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="308" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Heine, S. J., Takata, T., &amp; Lehman, D. R. (2000). Beyond self-presentation: Evidence for self-criticism among Japanese. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 26, 71-78.</ref>
          <ref rid="R33" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="309" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Jones, E. E., &amp; Wortman, C. (1973). Ingratiation: An attributional approach. New York: General Learning Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R34" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="310" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Kurman, J. (2001a). Is self-enhancement related to modesty or to individualism-collectivism? A test with four Israeli groups. Asian Journal of Social Psychology, 4, 225-237.</ref>
          <ref rid="R35" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="311" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Kurman, J. (2001b). Self-enhancement: Is it restricted to individualistic cultures? Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 27, 1705-1716.</ref>
          <ref rid="R36" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="312" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Kurman, J. (2002). Measured cross-cultural differences in self-enhancement and the sensitivity of the self-enhancement measure to modesty response. Cross-Cultural Research, 36, 73-95.</ref>
          <ref rid="R37" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="313" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Kurman, J. (2003). Why is self-enhancement low in certain collectivist cultures: An investigation of two com- peting explanations. Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 34, 496-510.</ref>
          <ref rid="R38" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="314" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Kurman, J., &amp; Sriram, N. (1997). Self-enhancement, generality level of self-evaluation and affectivity in Israel and Singapore. Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 28, 421-441.</ref>
          <ref rid="R39" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="315" confidence="possible" page="23" column="1">Kurman, J., &amp; Sriram, N. (2002). Interrelationships among vertical and horizontal collectivism, modesty, and self-enhancement. Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 33, 71-86.</ref>
          <ref rid="R40" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="319" page="24" column="1">Kurman, J., Yoshihara-Tanaka, C., &amp; Elkoshi, T. (2003). Is self-enhancement negatively related to constructive self-criticism? Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 34, 24-37.</ref>
          <ref rid="R41" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="320" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Kwan, V. S. Y., Bond, M. H., Boucher, H. C., Maslach, C., &amp; Gan, Y. (2002). The construct of individuation: More complex in collectivist than in individualist cultures. Personality and Social Psychology Bulletin, 28, 300-310.</ref>
          <ref rid="R42" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="321" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Leary, M. R., Robertson, R. B., Barnes, B. D., &amp; Miller, R. S. (1986). Self-presentations of small group leaders: Effects of role requirements and leadership orientation. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 51, 742-748.</ref>
          <ref rid="R43" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="322" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Leech, G. (1983). Principles of pragmatics. New York: Longman.</ref>
          <ref rid="R44" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="323" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Levine, R., Gillman, M. J., &amp; Reis, H. (1982). Individual differences for sex differences in achievement attributions? Sex Roles, 8, 455-466.</ref>
          <ref rid="R45" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="324" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Markus, H. R., &amp; Kitayama, S. (1991). Culture and the self: Implications for cognition, emotion, and motivation. Psychological Review, 98, 224-253.</ref>
          <ref rid="R46" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="325" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Maslach, C. (1974). Social and personal bases of individuation. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 29, 411-425.</ref>
          <ref rid="R47" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="326" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Maslach, C., Stapp, J., &amp; Santee, R. T. (1985). Individuation: Conceptual analysis and assessment. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 49, 729-738.</ref>
          <ref rid="R48" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="327" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Mischel, W. (1968). Personality and assessment. New York: Wiley.</ref>
          <ref rid="R49" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="328" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Pasquella, M. H., Mednick, M. T., &amp; Murray, S. R. (1981). Causal attributions for achievement outcomes: Sex-role identity, sex and outcome comparisons. Psychology of Women Quarterly, 5, 586-589.</ref>
          <ref rid="R50" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="329" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Paulhus, D. L. (1998). Interpersonal and intrapsychic adaptiveness of trait self-enhancement: A mixed blessing? Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 74, 1197-1208.</ref>
          <ref rid="R51" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="330" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Powers, T. A., &amp; Zuroff, D. C. (1988). Interpersonal consequences of overt self-criticism: A comparison with neutral and self-enhancing presentations of self. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 54, 1054- 1062.</ref>
          <ref rid="R52" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="331" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Sadalla, E. K., Kenrick, D. T., &amp; Vershure, B. (1987). Dominance and heterosexual attraction. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 52, 730-738.</ref>
          <ref rid="R53" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="332" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Schlenker, B. R. (1975). Self-presentation: Managing the impression of consistency when reality interferes with self-enhancement. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 32, 1030-1037.</ref>
          <ref rid="R54" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="333" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Schlenker, B. R., &amp; Leary, M. R. (1982). Audiences’ reactions to self-enhancing, self-denigrating, and accurate self-presentations. Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 18, 89-104.</ref>
          <ref rid="R55" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="334" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Schneider, D. J. (1969). Tactical self-presentation after success and failure. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 13, 262-268.</ref>
          <ref rid="R56" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="335" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Schwartz, S. H. (1992). The universal content and structure of values: Theoretical advances and empirical tests in 20 countries. In M. P. Zanna (Ed.), Advances in experimental social psychology (Vol. 25, pp. 1-65). New York: Academic.</ref>
          <ref rid="R57" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="336" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Schwartz, S. H. (1994). Cultural dimensions of values: Toward an understanding of national differences. In U. Kim, H. C. Triandis, C. Kagitcibasi, S. C. Choi, &amp; G. Yoon (Eds.), Individualism and collectivism: Theory, method, and applications (pp. 85-121). Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage.</ref>
          <ref rid="R58" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="337" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Schwartz, S. H., &amp; Bardi, A. (2001). Value hierarchies across cultures: Taking a similarities perspective. Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology, 32, 268-290.</ref>
          <ref rid="R59" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="338" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Schwartz, S. H., &amp; Boehnke, K. (2004). Evaluating the structure of human values with confirmatory factor analysis. Journal of Research in Personality, 38, 230-255.</ref>
          <ref rid="R60" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="339" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Schwarzer, R., &amp; Jerusalem, M. (1995). Generalized Self-Efficacy scale. In J. Weinman, S. Wright, &amp; M. Johnston (Eds.), Measures in health psychology: A user’s portfolio. Causal and control beliefs (pp. 35-37). Windsor, England: NFER-NELSON.</ref>
          <ref rid="R61" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="340" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Sedikides, C., Gaertner, L., &amp; Toguchi, Y. (2003). Pancultural self-enhancement. Journal of Personality and Social Psychology, 84, 60-79.</ref>
          <ref rid="R62" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="341" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Shikanai, K. (1978). Effects of self-esteem on attribution of success-failure. Japanese Journal of Experimental Social Psychology, 18, 47-55.</ref>
          <ref rid="R63" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="342" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Spencer-Oatey, H., &amp; Ng, P. (2000). Reconsidering Chinese modesty: Hong Kong and mainland Chinese evaluative judgments of compliment responses. Journal of Asian Pacific Communication, 11, 181-201.</ref>
          <ref rid="R64" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="343" confidence="possible" page="24" column="1">Tangney, J. P. (2000). Humility: Theoretical perspectives, empirical findings and directions for future research. Journal of Social and Clinical Psychology, 19, 70-82.</ref>
          <ref rid="R65" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="347" page="25" column="1">Tetlock, P. E. (1980). Explaining teacher explanations of pupil performance: A self-presentation interpretation. Social Psychology Quarterly, 43, 283-290.</ref>
          <ref rid="R66" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="348" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Triandis, H. C. (1989). Self and social behavior in differing cultural contexts. Psychological Review, 96, 269-289.</ref>
          <ref rid="R67" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="349" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Wada, M. (1988). Information seeking in self-evaluation of ability [Abstract]. Proceedings of Japanese Psychological Association Meeting, 52, 222.</ref>
          <ref rid="R68" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="350" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Weiner, B. (1979). A theory of motivation for some classroom experiences. Journal of Educational Psychology, 71, 3-25.</ref>
          <ref rid="R69" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="351" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Wosinska, W., &amp; Dabul, A. J., Whetstone-Dion, R., &amp; Cialdini. (1996). Self-presentational responses to success in the organization: The costs and benefits of modesty. Basic and Applied Social Psychology, 18, 229-242.</ref>
          <ref rid="R70" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="352" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Yang, K. S. (1996). The psychological transformation of the Chinese people as a result of societal modernization. In M. H. Bond (Ed.), The handbook of Chinese psychology (pp. 479-498). Hong Kong, China: Oxford University Press.</ref>
          <ref rid="R71" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="353" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Yang, K. S., Yu, A. B., &amp; Yeh, K. H. (1991). Zhongguoren de geren chuantongxing yu xiandaixing: Gainian yu celiang [Chinese individual traditionality and modernity: Conceptualization and measurement]. In K. S. Yang &amp; K. K. Hwang (Eds.), The mind and behavior of the Chinese: Selected papers of the 1989 Taipei conference (pp. 241-306). Taipei, Taiwan: Laureate Publishing Co.</ref>
          <ref rid="R72" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="354" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Zhang, J. X., &amp; Schwarzer, R. (1995). Measuring optimistic self-beliefs: A Chinese adaptation of the general self-efficacy scale. Psychologia, 38, 174-181.</ref>
          <ref rid="R73" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="355" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Zuckerman, M. (1979). Attribution of success and failure revisited, or: The motivational bias is alive and well in attribution theory. Journal of Personality, 47, 245-287.</ref>
          <ref rid="R74" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="356" page="25" column="1">Sylvia Xiaohua Chen is an assistant professor in the Department of Applied Social Sciences at the Hong Kong Polytechnic University. She has a PhD in psychology from the Chinese University of Hong Kong and an MA in counseling psychology from Santa Clara University, U.S.A. Her research interests include the social psychology of bilingualism and biculturalism, personality and social behaviors in cultural contexts, cross-cultural research methodology, and sociocultural influences on illness behaviors and help-seeking patterns. Michael Harris Bond has been practicing social psychology for the last three-plus decades at the Chinese University of Hong Kong, where he now is Research Professor of Psychology. He is fascinated by culture, having been socialized into an English-Canadian variant, followed by an American graduate education in exotic California, and an extended intercultural immersion as a Research Associate from 1971 to 1974 at Kwansei</ref>
          <ref rid="R75" class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="357" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Gakuin University in Japan. Throughout much of this cultural awareness-raising, he has been a member of the Baha’i Faith. This religious practice has further extended his contact with representatives of other cultural realities, sharpened his appreciation of pervasive societal influences on human social performance, and opened his sensibilities to Islamic art, literature, and philosophy. He is the author of Beyond the Chinese Face (Oxford, 1991) and co-author of Understanding Social Psychology Across Cultures (Sage, 2006).</ref>
          <ref class="deo:BibliographicReference" id="359" confidence="possible" page="25" column="1">Bacon Chan, BSSc, was an undergraduate student at The Chinese University of Hong Kong. He assisted the first author in data collection and statistical analysis of the Canadian sample. His research interest focuses on social axioms and individualism-collectivism. Donghui Tang received her master’s degree in education from Beijing Normal University. She is currently an associate professor at Beijing Normal University. Her main research and publications are in the areas of health promotion and health psychology. Emma E. Buchtel is currently pursuing her PhD at the University of British Columbia, Canada. Her research interests include cultural-moral relativism and the effect of culture on values about reasoning, helping behavior, and use of personality trait information. For reprints and permissions queries, please visit SAGE’s Web site at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://www.sagepub.com/journals" id="358">http://www.sagepub.com/journals</ext-link> Permissions.nav.</ref>
        </ref-list>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="288" page="22" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="287">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="289" page="23" column="1">624 Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="317" page="23" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="316">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="318" page="24" column="1">Chen et al. / Modest Behavior Across Cultures 625</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="345" page="24" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="344">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="header" id="346" page="25" column="1">626 Journal of Cross-Cultural Psychology</outsider>
        <outsider class="DoCO:TextBox" type="footer" id="361" page="25" column="1">Downloaded from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" href="http://jcc.sagepub.com" id="360">http://jcc.sagepub.com</ext-link> at CITY UNIV OF HONG KONG on June 15, 2009 All in-text references underlined in blue are linked to publications on ResearchGate, letting you access and read them immedia</outsider>
      </section>
    </body>
  </article>
</pdfx>
